So I will get the recording started and wait for a
little while in case there are questions from you,
anything lingering from last time or arising from
the asynchronous materials to to bring up today
and
to give you a little while to think about that and
just reiterate that you can feel free to put it on
hold everywhere. A question that has been linked
in the chat window directly in the chat window, or
just go ahead and undo yourselves and speak up
whatever is most convenient for you, this is your
secret session to get the maximal use out of. And
it's the only logistical notice today is just the
reminder that the first homework assignment is due
next Tuesday. That's the 16th. So a little over
five days away, this will be a bit more of the
sort of assignment you were used to as opposed to
that computer project, which are still being
marked. Should get back over the weekend. Well, in
time for the term break, along with the second
part of that assignment.
And to continue giving you a bit of an opportunity
to raise any questions that you may have, don't
worry about interrupting me. If you do have any
questions I can give you. Recap the
material we went through earlier this week or
Monday, synchronous session where we wrapped up
the ideal gas law as an example of the equation of
states and got through about the first half of the
year synchronous material on thermodynamic cycles
that are based on that ideal gas law, along with
other aspects of ideal gases. How their entropy is
kept constant and
in the first law of thermodynamics, generalized
for the canonical ensemble where the energy is
allowed to fluctuate. By exchange with a large
reservoir that fixes the temperature. And we saw
it in the first half of the week, five material
how?
Work and heat are formally defined and enter into
that generalized first law of thermodynamics,
where the change in energy is simply given by the
heat and work that are being done by the system.
And how these changes in the the large scale
macroscopic state of the limbic system can be
represented graphically in the form of pressure,
volume, diagrams or PV diagrams, a couple of
examples of which were where we left off on page
75. And while I was going through that recap
question did come in for the first get on page 80,
looking at the work done in the adiabatic
expansion of the Karno cycle. So we will. Get to
that, I think, today and. Building up to that
might be. Useful just to consolidate the stuff
that came up on Monday and combine these PV
diagrams with. The definition of work in heat by.
Asking to see.
A fairly technical question, so say that I have
some gas in some volume that I want to present, I
want to compress this ideal gas in some volume and
say also that I'm lazy and I want to do this
compression while doing the least amount of work
possible.
So I'm I have to exert some force on the container
holding this ideal gas to reduce its volume. I
don't really care about how much the volume is
reduced, how long it takes me to reduce that
volume. Just want to consider what strategy I
should take to make the. Compression is easy as
possible for me with the thought of two limiting
cases being to compress that volume quickly so
that no heat is expelled as I exert this force on
it. Alternately, I could and the other extreme
compress it very slowly. So that heat is always
being exchanged between this gas and surroundings
and as a consequence, its temperature stays fixed.
Or I could do something in between that balances
these two considerations of of temperature and
heat flow.
And so there's not any.
Detailed calculation that needs to be done for
this, and it's just a more conceptual and generic
question. Of the relation between. Compression,
heat and work will give you a little while to
think about those relations.
Or to ask any questions if the set up being
proposed here is unclear.
And at this point, I think there are enough
responses to see that a consensus is developing
but not unanimous around the option of slow
compression so that the temperature stays the same.
Indeed, the graphical way to see this on this TV
diagram we were looking at at the end of last
week's session is by recalling that the work is.
The. Negative of the.
Pressure times, the change in volume integrated
over that.
Whatever that compression is, so in other words,
with the volume on the horizontal axis of this TV
diagram, the work is just the.
It is related to the area under the curve, drawn
by the line and perhaps using blue.
Coloring, I should just fill in the area under
that isothermal curve where what we have to do
with the negative sign is just keep track of which
direction we are going, whether we are compressing
or expanding the gas, where if we were expanding
the gas, we would have the usual integral from a
small volume to a large volume. The integral then
would be the positive area under the graph, and
the negative sign would be an overall negative
sign indicating that work was being done by the
system on its surroundings.
Since we're going in the other direction and
compressing the gas, I can see that the smallest
amount of work, which is the smallest area,
corresponds to that isothermal line and any.
Any change in the temperature is going to open up
some other additional region on this diagram,
contributing additional work that has to be done.
So that's the the mathematical response in terms
of integration. In the the more physical response
would be that.
By allowing the heat to flow, we are familiar with
the relation between heat and temperature. We're
lowering the temperature of the gas, keeping it
constant in the isothermal limit. And by lowering
the temperature, we lower the pressure by the
ideal gas law. So by keeping the temperature
constant, we have to do less work pushing up that
pressure compared to what we would do if he were
allowed, if no heat were allowed to exchange to
flow and the pressure were pushed all the way up
to that maximum value resulting from the adiabatic
limit. So
with that
seeming clear to everyone, we can maybe consider a
slightly different and more
abstract question, which comes now from the
generality of these PV diagrams. They provide an
easy way to define thermodynamic cycles with all
sorts of different behavior, some of which is
physically motivated, some of which may be a more
mathematical abstraction. So, for example, we
could consider just the abstract cycle that
corresponds to the following close loop in apre
diagram.
Where?
I'm drawing this so that each of these three lines
is
meant to be a straight line, one of them at a
constant volume, one of them at a constant
pressure, and the other going along the diagonal,
connecting those two.
Limits of the cycle and the question to ask is
whether this triangular cycle.
Performs work on its surroundings as we go across
around the cycle over and over again. Alternately,
it's possible that the cycle would require work to
be done on it by its surroundings in order to
successfully complete.
Or it could just be a wash, a balance between.
The work that the cycle does on its surroundings
and the work that has to be done on it by those of
us from outside of joining forces and
doing work on the system to to get it to close as
it goes all the way around.
You know, I'll give you some time to think about
that or ask for clarifications if.
What I've described is unclear.
I see responses are coming in and moving around,
so I'll wait a bit longer for things to settle
down.
And if we take a look and the results, there's not
quite an even split, but a variety of responses,
there's anyone able and willing to motivate their
choice before I motivate mine.
Not hearing any volunteers will flip back to the
illustration of this diagram to consider and see
if I can.
Zoom out to, well, it's legitimate far enough to
get the equations back on the screen. It'll be a
bit awkward. I can write them again
just as easily. Was that the work was.
The negative integral over the volume of that
pressure as a function of the volume or the area
on these PV diagrams. Up to considerations of that
overall negative sign, so I drew this triangle
starting from this point in going along this
diagonal path where we increase the volume and
increase the pressure simultaneously, the at least
the magnitude of the work that's being done is the
area under.
That's.
Diagonal line. And then the question is, how did
the science work out to tell whether this process
is doing work on its surroundings or requires work
being input to the gas by the surroundings in
order to happen?
Well.
If we.
Recall the cartoon that we started off with of a
gas in.
A.
In Volume one. All of which was a. Movable piston.
That is how we allow this volume to. Expand or
contract as the volume increases in the piston
moves outward. That can be connected to some gears,
doing work on the surroundings. It's pushing out
into the external environment, shifting whatever
is there away from where it was sitting. This is
caused by the gas heating up, energy being added
in the form of of heat. So along this diagonal
line here, heat is coming in and work is going out,
being done on the surroundings by the expansion of
our system.
So the overall.
Work that is being done is the area under this
diagonal. Which comes with that overall negative
sign as we're integrating from a smaller, larger
volumes, so that is less than zero in this first
stage.
Which is the.
Sign that corresponds to work being done by the
system on its surroundings. Now, when we get up to
the end of that process and starts considering the
next one, what happens there is that we fix that
volume, locking that piston into place and allow
the system to cool. It loses energy in the form of
heat flowing out into its core reservoir.
That lowers the temperature, that lowers the
pressure at a fixed volume, and because the volume
is fixed, this change in volume is zero in the
overall work being done to zero. So that is not
relevant to the question of. Whether this cycle
performs more or less work than it requires to
operate, we can move straight ahead to the final
process where.
The volume now is being compressed, so the force
from the outside is being exerted on this piston
to squeeze the system into a smaller volume in
this compression is happening in such a way that
the pressure is constant. The easy way to
accomplish that is, well, that corresponds to just
exerting a constant force on this piston. If we
had drawn the orientation of the spikes the other
way around so that the pistons were on the top, we
could have just added a weight to it and let the
force of gravity do the compression for us. That
would guarantee you that the force was always
constant. And as that constant force compresses
the volume by the ideal gas law, it tends to
increase the pressure. So we have to wait for
additional heat to leave the system of flowing out
back into that cold reservoir
so that the temperature and the pressure fall back
down again to the point that this constant force
is again able to do a little bit more compression.
So that corresponds to work being done, being done
on the system by surroundings that is being put
into the system. We can also see that now that
we're going in the opposite direction in our
integration from a larger volume to a smaller one.
That's overall. Work those two negative signs from
the limits of integration and from the cost factor
out front.
I mean, that in this stage, in this process of the
cycle, it has to be done on the system by its
surroundings. And the question now is. Which of
those two is larger you I should have told him
that this work going in, being done by the
surroundings, was the area under that horizontal
counterpressure line. So we can see that adding up
those two contributions with the relative sign the
area in the pre diagram traced out by the cycle.
Is the network being done? And that came that
comes from the area under the. First diagonal
process, but still above the final horizontal
process so that there is more work coming out,
being done by the system than there is work going
in, being done. On the system, so the cycle is
able to perform work, making its an engine rather
than a refrigerator, using external inputs of of
energy and work to shift heat from one place to
another.
In all that discussion of reservoirs and shifting
heats and so on was looking ahead a bit to the
final section in the material for this week, the
Karno cycle, which is a particularly famous
thought, a cycle that introduced. You know, even
before the concepts of heat and entropy were
mathematically well-defined, it introduced the
framework, the concept of the conceptual paradigm
that is still used by a lot of the real heat
engines
and not just heat engines, the real engines like
internal combustion engines that are used all over
in this modern age, featuring the system in
contact with two different thermal reservoirs,
a hot reservoir with a high temperature and a cold
reservoir with a low temperature.
That the system is in equilibrium with as it
expands and contracts.
In these now four stages, rather than the three of
the triangular cycle we were looking at, so maybe
before going into more detail with the Kano's
cycle, I should pause and ask to see if there were
if the explanation of that triangular cycle was
satisfactory or if questions are lingering about
that.
Not hearing any questions, I took that opportunity
to draw in to this diagram some of the.
Information in the text about the set up for the
carto cycle. That makes it a particularly simple
and special system to consider where the expansion
from its smallest volume points A to its largest
volume point C proceeds in these two stages. First,
a slow isothermal expansion where.
Heat is.
Added to the system to keep the temperature
constant as the volume expands and just as we were
seeing with the previous cycle, that expansion of
the volume means that the system is able to do
work on its surroundings, putting out output work
that can be put to put to use in impractical
devices. At least in principle.
Then at some intermediate points that we've
labeled here, B, we switch from that slow
isothermal expansion to a fast adiabatic expansion
and we can recall the definition of adiabatic
processes are that no heat is exchanged so that
there is no change in the entropy. But still,
since this is.
A expansion, it is still doing work
on its surroundings, so work is being taken out of
the system and put to use in its surroundings and
then simply the the mirror image is done in
principle to get back to that starting point.
Where we do another round of slow isothermal
expansion, sorry, slow isothermal change in volume,
now we are compressing it, so work has to be so he
has to be expelled out into that cold reservoir
now to keep the temperature from increasing as the
system is compressed.
And this compression.
Itself requires work being put in, being done on
it, just as we've considered for.
The the question of.
Of compressing an arbitrary system with the least
amount of work possible at the start of today's
session.
I was just distracted by looking at some of the
questions about the Kerno cycle, the last stage
here is, again, that same adiabatic compression
with no heat exchange and still work being put in.
And I suspect a good.
Order which to to go through some of the
calculations for this system, which will address
the question that came in at the start of today's
session, is first to ask.
What is the the ratio of those?
Two temperatures for the carbon cycle, this is
something that ends up being. Uniquely determined
by the other properties of the system through the
key equations for summer Olympic cycles, the
conservation of energy, the first law of
thermodynamics. Definition of entropy and the
ideal gas law.
In this temperature ratio, we will see as we go
through other aspects of considering this cycle
turns out to pop up in, you know, other sorts of
features of it.
Responses are coming in, so wait another minute or
so
and feel free to let me know if you are still
working, any need more time to consider this
question?
If I flip back to the current state of the results
there.
Is a bit of a spread. Does anyone? Want to explain
to us.
How any one of these. Three options, they got some
support were were derived.
Well, I can take a stab at it myself, partly in
the interest of time, so that we can get through a
couple more things today and just have one left
for
for one day, so. This is the. This box here at the
top of page 78 is the one asking about. The low
temperature T.L. in terms of the the inputs,
quantities that we were given, and we're also told
here that the entropy is the same at points B and
C, one of which we might recall had that high
temperature. The other, the low temperature going
from B to C, so that gives us access to. The low
temperature at point C. In terms of the high
temperature at point B, just recalling the
condition for the entropy to be constant is that
this combination of volume and temperature for a
constant entropy I might have misspoken earlier of
entropy means that this combination
of volume and temperature is fixed. Which then
tells us just rearranging this, that the ratio of
the temperatures.
Low temperature to the high temperature is given
directly by this ratio of the volumes with the
two thirds power taken to cancel out. That's that
three 1/2 hour on the temperature in the course of
entropy condition, which was the the most popular
response in this whole.
And with this set up and skip ahead to. The
question that came in. At the start of today's
session, looking at the first box on page 80,
where the question here is motivated by
considering the efficiency of the kanoa cycle,
which will wrap up on Monday, I suspect.
But we've seen in the setup for computing the work
being done by this adiabatic expansion from point
A to point C, because no heat is exchanged in that
adiabatic process, the work is. Exactly the change
in the internal energy of the gas, which from one
of those key equations in a box earlier in this
document, is just driven by the change in
temperature going from theart to. T. high to see
low THC l since that number of.
Of particles in in the system is always fixed and
we end at the low temperature and start at the
high temperature going from point B to C. Which
means that if we pull out that factor of the high
temperature, we have just our
ratio that we just computed here that he low over
t hard we can recognize. This combination of end
times to high as the input, pressure and volume
from the ideal gas law. At either point A to point
B, they both have the same number of particles and
the same high temperature and then plugging in the
result we just had for that temperature ratio in
terms of those volumes to the power two thirds, we
have that result for the work being done by the
idiomatic expansion and we can check to see.
That's because this is expansion of the volume at
point C v subsea is larger than the volume and B,
this ratio is less than one. When it's raised to
any power remains less than one, so the overall
factor within the. Parentheses here is negative on
the whole. So with the work being negative, we
confirm that this is work being put out by the
system being done on its surroundings.
I'll pause briefly for any questions about that
and. While waiting to hear, I will. Just spin up
the the last question to ask today, which is.
Going back to the set up for the Karno cycle, we
skipped ahead a bit when computing hits its work
there just because that was so closely related to
the temperature ratio. There is a
in principle, a question that we should ask before.
Spending a lot of efforts trying to figure out how
much work this cycle is able to do in general,
which is is it a well-defined thermodynamic cycle
in principle? Is it possible to. Align the
sequence of isothermal and adiabatic expansion and
compression in such a way that the system gets
back exactly to its starting macro state and the
cycle can can be repeated over and over again
without. Spinning off, either requiring an
infinite amount of work or an infinite amount of
heat.
And I guess it's not a spoiler to say that the
Kado cycle is a well defined cycle, but this is
only true for a particular choice. Of the the
final unspecified volume up in. The diagram, the
Peevey diagram that we started off with.
Up on page seventy six.
Depending on how we choose that free volume, we
may or may not get a well-defined thermodynamic
cycle that can be put to work either as an engine
or a refrigerator.
A couple of responses had already come in, and
since we're getting close to the end of time, I
won't wait too much longer for more consideration
unless there are requests that I do so.
And there is agreement here that
the condition is that the the ratios of these
volumes match up, which in case anyone didn't have
time to. To check this in and vote here, that's
just coming from applying that same concept,
entropy condition now to hearing about a
compression going from point D to point A.
Where the cost of entropy condition is that same
relation between the volumes and the temperatures,
so that video is VÉ times, this ratio of high and
low temperatures to the power three halves.
Which we just saw was exactly that ratio
of the two specified volumes on the other
adiabatic cycle, the. The expansion phase that
does work. Leading to the constellation that the
ratio of volumes at high temperatures for the
Kano's cycle. Is.
A and B rather than A and D is equal to the ratio
of volumes at the low temperatures D and C.
And that brings us to the end of time, Will.
Discuss the efficiency of the carto cycle on one
day and have plenty of time to dive into the grand
canonical ensemble and any questions about the
homework do. On Tuesday and. If there are any
further questions now, feel free to. To ask them
and I will in a few minutes, shut down the zoo
meeting, extract that recording and then restarted
again for the usual office hours. So those of you
without questions can enjoy the rest of your day.