Well, while we wait for a few more people to join
us for week four, I have started recording this in
Ken.
Get under way with some of the logistical
organization.
So as that recording indicates, the there was
consensus to record the Synchronoss sessions in
that Week three questionnaire and take a brief
look at some of the other feedback and responses
to that questionnaire just after giving folks a
couple more minutes to accumulate. And I realized
last night that this also saves me from having to
record an asynchronous discussion of that
questionnaire. I can just upload this recording
and then it is available to everyone with no
further work from me. In the meantime, while we go
through that questionnaire, I'm also going to.
Activate the usual first question for every
meeting, if you have any questions for me about
the asynchronous materials, the computer project
that is due tomorrow or requests for supplemental
recordings.
You have now the whole everywhere, usual full
everywhere link is up and activated for those to
come in.
While we go through. The. Week three questionnaire,
which is. Over on. This is here.
So we got about 30 percent response rate, which I
believe is typical and suggests 70 percent are
sufficiently content not to bother. And of the 30
percent responses we got the.
Difficulty of the course is, on average, just a
bit more difficult than easy, and I should say, I
don't know why this canvas quiz is suggesting
there was a right answer for any of these and that
wasn't set. That's just being silly.
The difficulty is a little bit more than we got in
this quiz last year, which is not surprising given
the challenges of learning remotely. So those of
you who are finding it moderately or very
difficult, I encourage you to get in touch with
any questions or confusions that arise, whether
that's in relation to the asynchronous materials,
these discussions or the assignments and the pace
is also just about.
Slightly more fast and slow, but hands are split
between those, there was a free tax response
saying that one of the little fast answers there
was selected by accident and canvas wasn't
allowing it to be changed, which is another
interesting shortcoming of that quiz. Almost
everyone finds the materials accessible, findable,
audible, illegible. Almost no one finds them
sufficient. And as I mentioned, there's is
consensus for the recording that is going on now.
And let's see, 70 percent of the free response
answers down at the end were also left blank. But
almost all of the others in relation to the
insufficiency of these materials asked for while
these recessions, these synchronous sessions to be
recorded and sample responses to the the gaps of
the notes, those active learning activities to be
uploaded to the canvas site, which started
happening last week while the quiz was still
running. So hopefully those two steps will suffice
to flip the balance for the. Sufficiency of the
materials and. Let's see.
Can also.
Open up the.
Questions to any further remarks on that
questionnaire, if there are any, and I see there
is. One question coming through the. Polls so far.
That.
And see. What should I share on which screen?
You know, I guess the last bit of logistics before
diving into materials is that the computer project
is due by the end of the day in the U.K. tomorrow.
I've got some questions about it.
Over the past week and some submissions as well
over the past week, and seeing that there are
questions coming in through people everywhere,
both about the week for notes and the computer
project.
So let me deal with the computer project versus
that is a bit more urgent, perhaps, and also part
of the logistical introduction to the session. One
question is. Available here? Not exactly on.
If this opens up.
Things are slowly loading. And there is this
question, are marks available for attempting to
code, even if it does not run? And I'll say yes,
the.
Now, the effort to set up the code and see how
close you get to a correct solution will be
acknowledged and provided with some marks. That's
a quick answer to that question and then question
about talking through the demo. Examples of what
the code means, which I can certainly spend a few
minutes doing right now, should be able to get to
that demo from. The canvass sites. Up with this
link, for some reason, Candace tries to embed the
Google collaboratory inside itself, don't know why
it tries to do that rather than just opening the
link as it should. But here is the demo. And the
idea is that, you know, this is. A notebook set up,
so all of these little code blocks are explained
in the comments that come along in front of them.
I don't want to edit those comments just to say
that, you know, what what explanation I give here
is going to echo and summarize pretty much the the
written comments in the text, just like the.
The lecture notes are only a transcription of the
lectures I would be given if we were doing
lectures this year, so as discussed. In this first
text, Locke. We start off by loading some
libraries that maybe I should try to zoom in to
this code, see if I can make it a bit more legible.
That larger on this screen, sharing and recording
some standard libraries with mathematical
functions like the square roots and random numbers,
as well as two very widespread utilities,
numerical python, num, pi and matplotlib, both of
which simplify it more than they complicate these
sorts of exercises by providing numerical routines
like easy array manipulation, a matplotlib. By
providing fancy plots we can. Try to keep the
keyboard from popping up whenever I touch anything
on this demo. Just checking the versions of those
libraries that are being used. And going on in
this first code block, we see the random number
generator generates 100000 samples.
Using that, well, pseudo random number generator,
there's information about what pseudo random
numbers mean in. The demo and the exercise and
accumulate these two running solms, the vacuum,
expectation value and the vacuum expectation value
of the square of. Let's see. I can't use the pen
to draw on the tablet with. This window of.
Each. So this data is an array in each step of
this for loop, we append a random number to this
array, which is two times the square root of you,
drawn from the usual uniform probability
distribution that is discussed in that text. And
while we could then after the fact, reconstruct
the mean and square roots from or of the mean and
standard deviation square root of the variance
from that array directly, it's much more efficient
to do so by accumulating these rolling sums. Which
if we normalize by the number of samples, which is
called are. In the computer project, we get a
meeting of about one point thirty three, a
standard deviation of about point four seven, and
I don't think I included the exact the calculation
in here, but it's easy to do separately. The exact
meaning is for thirds for this. The distribution
produced by this transformation X is two times the
square root of you and the standard deviation is
route to over three. And easy to see that four
thirds is about one point three three three three.
Which we're reproducing there to several decimal
places, and the square root of two over three is
also point for seven and change specifically if I
put it in a calculator, it is four seven one four
zero. So only about three significant figures
reproduce there with these hundred thousand random
samples.
Now, having saved all of the information in an
array, in addition to just accumulating those
running sums, we can plot the histogram. Which is
the number of samples that land in each of these
bins, in this case, I set fifty one bins, which
give a nice little coverage here that's not too
rough and not to fine. If I were to change that to,
say, five and execute this guy, we would get
something a bit less useful if I were to change it.
To say what I do want the keyboard to pop up is
not.
NowI. That is. Changing it to say 500. Gives
something where the bins are so narrow. There are
a lot more visible statistical fluctuations just
from the randomness of the numbers we're working
with and at the same time, on top of that
histogram plotting the expected distribution.
Which is just why is one half of X?
Back in here and.
Run the 51 beans just to have that lying around
next bit is.
Something more along the lines of the question
just came in. What does the code mean in the
histogram? So this X here.
Is.
You know, the standard rate of flight functions in
Python, so that is probably all I say about it,
that is the range of the plots going from zero to
two and sampling points every zero point zero one
within that range. So what's being plotted here is.
The line given by X and Y, where X here is just a.
Smooth coverage of. The range from zero to two,
which is why that is automatically picked out as
the range on that plot and why is the function
being plotted? So if I were just were to say push
that up to zero to three, you would see this
orange curve extending beyond the horizontal range
of that histogram.
And the last bit of the demo is a bit more
obviously the sort of thing that is being done in
the computer project, looking at random walks
where the distance of the walk, this quantity D.
In the code is adding up some number of steps with
each step length being drawn from this random
distribution X is to square root you. At the end
of each of those step walks, we record that
distance in an array of walk lengths, all this
negative one index puts it into the last entry in
the array, which was set to be zero up there. And
then divide by the number of samples and print out
what that length is in this case, where our random
numbers are always positive, we're only walking in
one direction. So the random walk always has a.
Positive final stopping points, which is given by
those numbers that are plotted there and in this
flight, it looks like there is a fairly direct
correlation between the number of steps of the
horizontal axis and the length of the lock on the
vertical axis. And if we are confident that this
is a linear function, we can fit to that linear
function. This is one of the many things America
Python provides out of the box. It will do a fit
for us so that we don't have to code up some
fitting routine with a nonlinear minimization and
that, again, now setting the X range of the plot
to be evenly spaced from zero to 80. Looking at
what lengths up to 80. We get output from the fix
this and B that. It's plotted on top of the points,
goes through them, as we expect for fit and is.
In good agreement with the points as a linear
function.
Now, if we don't want to assume that that function
was linear to begin with, we can fit the data to a
more general power law.
Zoomed out a while ago and I forgot to zoom back
in and here power laws are non-linear functions.
As shown, there it is, the length is some constant
times, a number of steps to some power that may
not even be an integer, but there is a standard
trick to return to power law into a linear
function, which is to take the logarithm of both
sides and fit the log of the SEP lengths as a
linear function of the number of steps. Which is
exactly what's done here, taking the log, using
convenient numerical python utilities that act on
each element in the lists that they get as
arguments do that same FETs, extract that same
output, take the exponential to get back to the
constant parameter C that appears in the power
parallel itself. And then check to see how close
to linnear this general power law really is, the
answer is very close one point zero zero zero zero
zero eight and getting the same slope. Well, that
same mean. For the single step process in this
random walk is the slope of. This fit again for
thirds up to permit level fluctuations and.
PostScript says that all those fluctuations are
going to depend on the amount of data, the number
of random samples that are being used, the more
independent random samples there are, the closer
we expect the. Numerical results to agree with
those analytic predictions.
And that's something that you can test with this.
Demo, so I'll pause just for a moment to see if
there are any follow up questions in the.
In the poll everywhere or directly through zum.
And in the meantime, the. Switch to the other
question that pops.
One question came in just as I was about to leave
in the lines to start with ENPI, I was showing off
here.
You know, what that is doing is using a function
that has been imported into our code at the very
start with these import lines, we get access to
all of the routines that are provided by those
libraries, numerical python routines from Dumphy,
which is abbreviated as ENPI, just to keep things
shorter and then plotting routines from matplotlib,
which is abbreviated as p.l.c. just to keep that
shorter. So all of these commands that start with
ENPI are using. Some functions, subroutines,
utilities, capabilities that come from numerical
python and.
I'm seeing here they don't show up for the first
few, there are, in addition these. Commands that
start with the math library in Python. So, for
instance, the square root here, that's the same
sort of principle. Once we import mathematical
functions and numerical python, everything that is
implemented in. Those libraries is accessed by
telling you the code where to look to find a
subroutine known as Holly Fit, which is a
polynomial fitting Rasyid. And if there's ever any
doubt about what a routine is called or what
functionality is available, then the thing to do
is to Google it in. Python is so widely used that
you will get tons of hits and explanations telling
you the proper syntax and capabilities that are
available which make everything you need is
illustrated here so you can copy and paste with no
searching or. Independent study done, that is what
is going on with those lines, math, MPLX and TLT.
OK.
So the last.
Tablet is doing that thing of rearranging.
These questions, again, as I touch them, and I
think this was the.
First, well, let's see. Go back here if it loads
and there was one question about the week four
notes, equation fifty four.
And let me just. Remind myself what. Was in. That
equation 54. Here and this, I think. I will
proceed by. Wrapping up the. Last question to.
I plan to ask about week three just to make sure
that all of everything interesting in the
canonical ensemble setup is covered, and then
we'll make sure we get to equation 50 for the
effective indistinguishably to do that either
later today or more likely on Thursday.
That might give more of you more of a chance to
get through these notes after the computer project
is done and dusted and all submitted, so hopefully
that is not putting putting off the question, but.
Promising to get to it in due course. And that
will let us go a bit more linearly through the
remainder of week. Three, where I just really
wanted to ask. That one more of these gaffes,
which was the one that got shuffled around this
here on page 52.
Where I can. Activate that question and just check
in what the internal energy.
Was. For. The system of indistinguishable spins in
a solid considered in the last section of the. The
week three.
Notes.
So let me.
Pull that up here, this is the box I'm talking
about.
And I'll pause for a minute or two to let some
responses to that poll come in.
And some are still coming in, so just a slight bit
longer for those who.
Maybe working through the. Calculation.
Rather than pulling up.
Something that was already available.
And the responses seem to have. Stabilized.
With a.
Preference for this hyperbolic tangent, but some
some responses for one overall hyperbolic.
Cosine squared, so just quickly. Run through this
derivative without going into too much commentary
that. Know, multiplying through the speed on if
somebody the.
Helmholtz, free energy for the case of
distinguishable spin's. We have minus in out front,
and then the beat is on top and bottom canceled.
So is the derivative of the log. Of.
Twice this hyperbolic cosine with the derivative
of log is.
Won over the arguments of the law, the.
And then the chain rule gives us the derivative of
what is inside the log, so that then is to H and
then derivative of hyperbolic.
Cosine is the positive. Hyperbolic sign the synch,
and that then is to cancel and there's a minus in
age in synch over. Coche is Tange, which hopefully
was, yes, one of the. Answers here, where the one
that was preferred and go on from there directly
to ask now about. The heat capacity for the same
system, so given the.
Energy that.
We just checked in that gap, the heat capacity was
not something that was asked for in. The notes for
this particular spin system, but it was discussed.
Earlier in this week and try to get myself back up
to that discussion and that definition, so this is
a calculation that you most likely did not.
Prepare in advance, so I'll give you. A couple of
minutes to. Consider it based on the results for
the. Energy for these spins in the magnetic field
h that we just went through. Quickly just now.
So does anyone want any more time to keep working
on this?
Sounds like not so hop over and see that everyone
agrees about taking the derivative of a. Maybe you
just have that memorized. I personally can't be
bothered to memorize derivatives of these hyper
geometric functions. So I always just work through
those derivatives from the definitions of the
functions. But so given that everyone agrees with
that result. I think I won't go through that
calculation, but will instead just emphasize the.
Facts that this heat capacity is generically
positive and always not negative, and I'll do that
by trying to write on the screen share tablets,
just a quick plot of.
Of dysfunction that came out, you know, normalized.
Just so that we don't have to worry about what
these parameters in and age and Bita are. So if I
import
a numerical python and matplotlib and then go back
and forth between.
The demo and this.
New
notebook to. Set up a quick plot.
Of that function.
If I can.
Get this tablet to behave.
There it is.
And why you did not call me when I told it to you,
I don't know.
Well, much easier to do on.
A actual laptop or computer where? Copying and
pasting should work as expected, and I may just
need to rewrite all of this.
From.
And that's why.
So happy somehow my keyboard got.
Reset.
So that.
The back to that.
Lay out where the keys are, where I expect them to
be and how the letter should do what I tell them
to. So let's just look at this function from, say,
zero to 10
and.
If we divide out by so this is a reminder that
heat capacity is in bid eight squared over
hyperbolic cosine of bead age, so dividing out and.
Saying that is one calling beta X, that function
is X squared over hyperbolic coshed squared
of X, where that hyperbolic Kalisz is one of the
many things that numerical python provides. And
hopefully this will show us a non-negative and
even positive function, which we are seeing here,
so that exercise took more effort than it should
have, but we got the result of the heat capacity
for a system of indistinguishable spins in an
external magnetic field, which is.
Always non-negative and approaches zero in the two
limits where X goes to zero. Which is exs, the
inverse temperatures, that is the infinite
temperature limit, and it also approaches zero
where X, which is data goes to infinity, which is
the zero temperature limit. And there are. Two
quite distinct interpretations of the vanishing
heat capacity in those two different limits, where
in the limit of infinite temperature, what's going
on is that once we have that temperature being,
you know, approaching infinity and adding just a
little bit more to.
Consider this.
Derivative here is essentially having no effect,
there's no response to a small change in the
temperature when that temperature is already
approaching infinitely large and the opposite
limit where the temperature is going to zero in
absolute zero. We saw last week that the spin
system gets stuck in its ground state. There are
never any fluctuations about that energy. And as
this is a fluctuation response relation, that
absence of fluctuations gives us an absence of
responses. So vanishing heat capacity in those two
limits and positive for all finite, non-zero
values.
So.
That is it for week three for me, this is a last
chance for you to ask any further questions about
that through Zoome and in the. The polls I will
hop over to. The first question. I was planning to
discuss on.
The week for notes, which is. A bit earlier than
the. Question that came in about equation fifty
four. We'll get to that on Thursday at this point
and not today. So that is something to look
forward to that's coming. The question now is
looking at page fifty nine. This is the first gap
in.
Week four, and that is, I think, page two of the
PDF here, that once we have introduced downspouts
to disguise the momentum that a particle could
have in an ideal gas in this container with a
particular volume, VQ the V is allocute.
And the question becomes, what are the energy
levels of that system and the question in the.
Whole everywhere now is what are the three lowest
energy levels.
Responses have started coming in and I'll give it
another minute or two and probably given the time
we'll wrap up with discussion of of these energy
levels, which will start off with. Next next time
on Thursday.
At the moment, there's an even split of responses,
so I'll wait just a little bit longer.
For tiebreakers to come in.
And in the interests of ending approximately
ontime. We'll take a look at those split results.
Which are 50 percent, four zero one and two times
this quantity, which is the same everywhere,
versus zero one and four, where those are the
the two most compelling responses, given the
energy that you presumably saw this squared over
two M with P given up there and P squared the
inner product.
You've seen that this quantity. Each bar squared,
PI squared over two and L squared appeared in all
of those possible responses, and then the inner
product is the sum KEX squared plus K Y squared
plus casette squared, each of which is a
non-negative integer. So the lowest energy comes
when all three of those are zero and that energy
is. Is just zero, the next lowest energy comes
when. One of them is one, the others are zero, and
that energy is one times that quantity, each per
squared, squared over two miles squared that
appears in. All of the responses in the poll
everywhere poll and then. The trick with the third
energy, which is. Why the.
Distractor example was in there. It is not
supposed to seem like that when I write.
The next lowest energy comes not from having.
I should also say.
That there are several possible combinations of
that one unit of momentum that give the same
energy one one zero zero zero one zero and zero
zero one. I'll give that same general energy level
one unit. If we were to put that up to two zero
zero zero two zero zero zero two, we would have
four units. What we can also.
Go to one one zero and end up with one plus one of
two and the other two combinations as well, one
zero one and zero one one. So permutations of that.
So those three lowest energies are zero one and
two times this constant result, which is now being
selected. So we'll pick up there on Thursday and
make sure to discuss the
contrast between distinguishable and
indistinguishable results on.
Paige. Fifty four. And. All the rest of the week
for notes, so let me know. Now, if there are any
further questions about what we went through in
today's.
Synchronous session in, otherwise, good luck with
the computing project, you know, I'll see you on
Thursday, if not in office hours, starting in
about eight minutes.