Well, the recording should now be underway and may
get a few more people coming by in the next few
minutes, we are in that last week before the break
that deal with some related logistical stuff while
waiting for more folks to trickle in. I guess the
obvious thing is that the first more traditional
homework assignment is due at the end of the day
tomorrow. A couple of questions have come in about
it since our last meeting on Thursday. In a couple
of the answers to those questions are.
Discussed in the discussion forum on the canvass
site for this molecule under the hole works one.
Discussion.
Mostly dealing with clarifications of what
assumptions need to be made or. How far to push
things like simplifying certain results and you're
welcome to bring in. More questions about that,
either through Paul everywhere or just directly
through zoom in the chat window or on muting
yourself.
And at the same time. The feedback and solutions
for the first part of the computer project were.
Distributed overnight. And it may be too early in
the morning in Liverpool for most of you to have
follow up questions to ask about that, the
solutions themselves. I also put we're also linked
through the discussion forum in Dorthe, the PDF
and corresponding Python code
and going through. Well, as a brief, the generic
feedback on the overall assignment, I can say that
there were not too much too many problems, not too
much difficulty encountered with the the first
couple of exercises that were mostly sampling and
random numbers from various distributions and
looking at, well, the mean standard deviation and
overall shape of those distributions. It was the
third exercise that was the more challenging one
for more folks.
And.
In particular.
If there were
a.
Relatively small fraction of the submissions that
we're able to get, the expected standard deviation
in the total length of the of the random walk,
which was this parameter L2 defined in the
exercise and not redefined here. And I was also
surprised that no one.
No one chose to take the hint from the assignment
that we could look at. Correlated results for
these random walks going up two to five hundred
steps, which let's just take, say, 400 of those
500 steps and call that a 400 step walk and not
have to recompute everything starting from scratch
each time that speeds things up quite
significantly, gets things to run in about.
Thirty seconds as opposed to. Thirty minutes.
That's shown both in the PEF Solutions as well as
they shut down some of these tabs, as well as the
corresponding Python code that can just be
downloaded rather than viewed. Online, so all of
that is up on the site and see if any questions
have.
Come in while I was taking a quick look through
that.
So with no questions from. An interview, I think,
will.
Pick up with going over the last bit of that week,
five material on thermodynamic and thermodynamic
cycles based on the ideal gas law, and I'm sure
we'll wrap that up today and see how much of the
grand economical ensemble. We'll get through and
how much will remain for Thursday.
Those of you who have taken a look at the week six
material will see there's a lot of parallels with
the introduction of the canonical ensemble, just a
messier arithmetic coming from the ability now to
change the particle number as well as changing the
entropy. But.
OK. I was just about to move on, but a question
did come in at the last minute. Relating to
question two in the homework assignment that I can.
Hopefully pull up reasonably quickly. Here looking
at.
The diffusion of an oil spill in water where we
see if I can get this into some program, that will
let me. Mark it up.
And the question was, were given that.
There is quite a bit of. Oil in the water, and
they need to rearrange the screen slightly in
order to get around the.
Zoom screen sharing.
Interface.
So there's quite a bit of oil in the water and
they want to know how long it will take until some
fraction of that.
Has reached a marine protected area in the
question was how to convert these large numbers of
one hundred or a thousand tons to a number of oil
droplets.
In the answer is that you don't need to if you.
Look at ratios of the total amount of oil. That
we're concerned about relative to the overall.
Amounts, then the units are going to drop out of
that ratio and just a pure number will result.
And if that's possibly illegible, zoom in a bit
and rewrite it and hopefully do the math correctly.
So looking at ratios.
Gets rid of the need to.
Convert's. Units between tons of oil and oil
droplets.
And. Getting.
Back to people everywhere, hopefully that was the.
Straightforward response, and I'm not hearing any
objections to it, I think Will. Hop back to. Just
catching up to where we were at the end of last
time on Thursday, looking at. The Karno cycle
shown here. In this diagram or the.
More physical illustration below it. We had gone
through.
The pressure volume diagram here where two of
these.
Curves are also therms.
And the other two
are 80 events, the temperature fixed and so therms,
the entropy fixed in 80 events.
And we had computed that. This current cycle is a
well-defined thermodynamic cycle, so long as.
This unspecified volume, the study D d obeys.
A single condition. That.
This ratio of. VTE overeasy is the same as the.
Over Vehbi.
And from that.
He moved on or we were going to move on to
considering how much work this cycle does. On its
surroundings, compared to the amount of heat that
is needed to run it, which
defines the efficiency of the cycle, so hopping
down to page 79, just to
give the a quick reminder that the efficiency ADA
is the network being done by the cycle. So the
difference between the work that the cycle is, the
system is able to do on its surroundings in each
iteration of the cycle, minus the work that the
surroundings, for example, us have to do on that
system in order to get the cycle to operate. And
then that's divided by the amount of heat that has
to be pumped into the system, into the system in
each iteration of the cycle.
Ignoring the amount of heat that is expelled as
waste feeds into into some cold reservoir. Where
the heat coming in, we think it was coming in from
some hot reservoir and that overall picture of two
reservoirs in contact with our system, one of them
hot and one of them cold, allow the heat to flow
is the basic overarching picture of. Thermodynamic
cycles, that's that was introduced by the carbon
cycle even a few decades before ideas of of heat
and entropy were in themselves well defined.
So the first question. Well, we went through the.
For processes in the cargo cycle and saw in
general that the efficiency is given with some
cancellations just by one, plus the ratio of the
work done on the low temperature isothermal
compression relative to the amount of work done in
the high temperature isothermal expansion.
And just to check in that this calculation didn't
prove problematic for anyone, they'll compute what
those two values of the work are, starting from
page 79, the work done at high temperatures. In.
In that isothermal expansion from. Point A to
point B. Let me give you a.
A couple of minutes to check that results and
the answer or get your results in from among these
four options shown here.
You know, there are so many of us today that don't
have too many responses yet, and in case that
means this is a tricky situation that you're still
working on. I'll give you another few seconds to
wrestle with it.
Let's see what we have here at this point.
Well, there is unanimous agreement on
the answer, it's a
unanimity of one, so maybe the safe thing to do is
just to make sure that you see how this goes in
case it is causing trouble for the rest of you on
here, where
from the ideal gas law, the starting point, we
have a relation between this pressure as a
function of the volume. And since this is that
expansion from point A to B on the high
temperature side of the carto cycle, when it's
bringing in from the reservoir, we know that the
appropriate temperature is the high temperature of
the reservoir, which is a constant that we can
pull up front of the integral that leaves us just
with.
Integral over of over Overbey, which is then the
logarithm of the volume and the difference of the
logs gives us the logarithm of the ratio, and I
can absorb that negative sign by reversing the
order. And at the same time, so in the pressure
and volume in place of the number of particles and
high temperature
from that top left corner of
the TV diagram for the current cycle so that the
times the log is indeed
what that one response came up with. And maybe the
thing to do now is to check, to see whether.
Going through that example.
Gives some insight into the other piece of the
work that we need for the efficiency, which is the
work that has to be done on the system rather than
being done by the system, which we compress
along those lines, CTD
expelling heat to
the cold reservoir rather than bringing heat in
from the hot reservoir.
No, wait a minute or two for that
correspondent calculation out there to be done for
or looked up.
Lyndsey's anyone.
Still working on this calculation.
Not hearing any requests for more time. Take a
look again that there is.
Unanimous response of one, which I think the safe
thing to do is to. Go through it in that case, in
case the low response rate means that finding this.
Tricky as well, we are now, it's the same
principle as the previous calculational, the this
time we have the low temperature from the cold
reservoir and the argument of the Lord has. That
opposite's.
Order. I have got the negative sign out front, so
it's VMD over D.C., which then gets.
Flipped into say.
The pressure and volume from that point see
connected to the low temperature of the cold
reservoir in B.C. over VMD, which was not one of
the options in the poll, we can.
Recognize from what we went through last week to
check that the carto cycle is a well defined cycle,
that this ratio of volumes has to be satisfied in
order for that cycle to close. And we can also.
Use the the work that we did last time.
Computing the ratio. Of the temperatures to
identify this.
In times, the low temperature in terms of.
The same pay and VA that we worked with in the
previous little activity where that ratio of
temperatures was the corresponding ratio of the
volumes
to the power, two thirds to satisfy the cost of
entropy condition of the adiabatic processes that
take us from one of those temperatures to the
other. So.
Plaguing all that in.
We end up with.
Very nearly the same.
Results as last time, just with the difference now
of this extra factor of the volumes and. A
different orientation
of the fraction in the log, the larger volume TVB,
rather than the smaller volume HVA, which we can.
Also, feel free to use the properties of logs to
flip that back and pull a negative sign out front
so that when we plug
both of those results into the expression we got
for the efficiency, this tablet behaves itself.
We just get that ratio of the volumes to the two
thirds.
You have the one out front and negative sign.
In that ratio of the volumes is just the ratio of.
The temperatures that we can check is.
Always not negative and also.
Less than one with the efficiency only reaching
one when either the.
The low temperature of the cold reservoir goes to
absolute zero or the high temperature of the
reservoir goes to infinity, neither of which are
terribly physical situations.
So.
Are there any questions about the Kado cycle,
because that's all that I had planned to discuss
about it, though it seemed to.
Proved trickier than I was anticipating.
Given that.
Trickiness it may be. Smart to keep looking at
some of the damage cycles. Maybe even more
conceptually for. A few more minutes and possibly
all of the remaining time today just to make sure
that these. Apparent difficulties grinding through
the integrals and arithmetic are not. Getting in
the way of understanding the the important
concepts in this material.
And.
Perhaps these more.
Conceptual, unless.
Listen, knowingly quantitative integration
questions might be a little more fun and
interesting for us to consider here or for. The
folks watching the recording, if anyone, is later
on.
Where if we go back to. Our starting points for.
Well, not even the Kano's cycle, but
these pressure volume diagrams in general, we saw
that they were useful because the key equations
that we have for thermodynamic cycles allow us to
relate to all of the large scale properties of the
macroscopic system, its macro state. So the
temperature, entropy, internal energy, pressure
and volume can all be related just to the pressure
and volume through the ideal gas law. The
condition for constant entropy and relation
between the energy and temperature and that lets
us represents the behavior of systems by these
pressure volume diagrams. But of course, if we can
solve for systems in terms of the two variables,
pressure and volume, we can also swap those out
for two of the other properties of the system. And
one common choice that is sometimes useful is
looking at. The properties of these systems in
terms of their temperature, so putting
temperatures high on horizontal axis and the
entropy s on the vertical axis.
And the question that we can consider is, how does
the kurnos cycle look in this representation in
terms of temperature, entropy diagrams rather than.
Pressure, volume, diagrams, so I'll sketch out,
say, for. Possibilities say. The circle.
Were some rectangle.
You have whips.
If the two stages. Going down to the right sort of
approximation of. The kind of picture that. We do
need more capably in the attacks or those sort of.
Curves that go off to the right instead of down to
the right, and those are the four options that are
now up in the latest poll.
Well, wait just a minute or so since there
detailed calculations are needed here, just. Quick
selection from that list.
Looking at the
results, there is an agreement that it's the
rectangle is.
The isothermal processes in the kanoa cycle keep
the temperature constant. And he is fixed value,
which is a vertical line on this font, and then
the adiabatic processes keep the entropy constant
leading to a fixed line there so that maybe it was.
Two simple rather than two difficult, maybe.
We can spend the remaining minutes by.
Addressing one question, that or one issue that
came up here comes up at the end of the notes,
which is that the cycle is mathematically elegant
because it realizes the maximum possible
efficiency of a thermodynamic cycle. The problem
is it's not useful for anything in practice
because these two isothermal processes. Going from
A to B and C to D have to be slow in order to keep
the temperature fixed with a sufficient amount of
of heat exchange at every stage in that process.
So trying to get any actual work out of a physical
realization of the cardio cycle is
not practical. It just takes too long in order for
the cycle to run. But even so, in the eighteen
hundreds, this relatively abstract mathematical
cycle inspired of some more practical applications,
starting with a cycle that's known as the diesel
cycle. After Rudolf Diesel, who developed it and
was directly inspired by the cycle. And there's a
similar and even simpler cycle known as the auto
cycle. Again named after a German physicist,
Nicholas Otto, which provides a good model of what
an internal combustion engine is doing. And in the
cycle,
we have a.
Pressure volume diagram of this sort.
To the extent I can grow cleanly.
The cycle goes.
From these points, one, two, three and four with.
Both of the.
Curved portions being adiabatic processes
and then back to one as a slow cycle, so quick
question just to sort of pressure volume, just to
check that you're able to read these pressure
volume diagrams without difficulty, I can ask in
this auto cycle, where are the highest and lowest
temperatures? Which are those four points? You
have the highest and lowest temperatures.
So we'll put the cycle back up on the screen.
So then you don't have to be able to look at since
it's not in the notes.
Immune responses are coming in and time is running
out, so there'll be another minute or less before
I move on to the question of the efficiency of
this cycle.
So let's see.
There is.
You're 100 percent.
Identifying will the same locations for the high
and low temperatures. As for the current cycle, so
maybe that was a way to check the results. We can
also think about what the pressure volume diagram
is describing that in the first stage, from one to
two, we compress the system, push into a smaller
volume, and then from two to three, there's a big
change in the pressure at a fixed volume, which is
an internal combustion engine is realized not by
putting the system into thermal contact with the
large external heat reservoir, but by lighting
some fuel on fire and bringing a lot of heat in
that way. That gives a very rapid change in
pressure even faster than the volume can respond
with that higher pressure than pushes the volume
back out again. Idiomatically, to point for that
expansion lowers the temperature from its peak at
three. And then the final step is reducing the
temperature at a fixed volume, which in a
practical advice is done by actually swapping out
the the hot gas and replacing it with some colder
gas. And that forms exhaust from the engine rather
than letting it cool just by heat exchange. Now, a
little exercise that we won't go through, but
might make a fun home. More question later in the
term is the efficiency of the auto cycle, which
turns out to be the.
Similar form to the efficiency of the Kano's cycle,
but with this temperature, the ratio that shows up
is the ratio of that temperature point for two
point three. So on either side of the adiabatic
process, which is also, it turns out, the ratio of
the temperatures between points one and points to
it since we saw just now in the question that this
temperature for while it is larger than
temperature three, it is less than the temperature.
One, the low temperature.
So it's less than Cee Lo, whereas T three is T
high.
You can see that because the eye should make a
better distinction between the ages of my four as
possibly.
That temperature T4 is greater than temperature C
h. So if we. Plug that in, you see that this
efficiency is strictly less than that of the Karno
cycle, as we could have expected from the results
in the notes that the cardio cycle has the maximum
possible efficiency.
So that is it for today and for three remix cycles.
Did it get to the grand canonical ensemble that
will come along on Thursday? Looking at the
chemical potential and some of the relations
between the emergent properties of grand
economical systems related to the great economical
potential, I'll wrap it up now, shut down the
meeting in a couple of minutes to get that
recording saved. And if there are any final
questions about thermodynamic cycles, feel free to
bring them up or head off to enjoy the rest of
your day.
In the office hours will be in this. Same room
about five minutes after I've got Zoom shut down
and restarted.