OK, I've got the recording underway and. It is
obviously a small crowd so far on this last
session before the term break in, that May.
Affects what we cover and how much detail we go
into have the usual first.
Question up and running for you to provide or
point out any. Point any places in the
asynchronous materials and he points that you want
to ask questions about, and this can also include
not just the notes on the grand canonical ensemble
for this week, but also the feedback and solutions
to the computer project. Now that you've had a few
days to to take a look at those. And speaking of
that computer project, the second part is now
online through the candidate site for the module.
It is due the second day after break, Tuesday the
13th of April. So while that's almost a month away,
three of those three and a half weeks are going to
be a term break. So you will benefit from getting
started on that part of the project over the break,
and I will keep. Office hours running during the
break at the usual zero lengths, including the one
that we're currently in. So those will be Mondays
at 10, Thursdays at two U.K. time. U.K. time is
also going to be shifting forward an hour in a
couple of weeks. So if you do get started with the
project over the break, have any questions about
the remainder of it, you will have those
opportunities to get in touch with me as well as
the asynchronous. Modes of communication through
the candidate site or through email.
And because this is the last session before the
break, I don't want to. Get started on anything
bigger involved, just make sure that we touch on
all of the.
Pieces that come in through the lecture notes for.
Week six on the grand canonical ensemble. And.
Given the small size, I think that whole
everywhere, maybe more trouble than it's worth
today, there are a couple of questions prepared,
but I think. It will be. Best for, you know, not
to run the polls and check in, but just sort of
discuss them in free form, you can feel free to
amuse yourself if you are able to type of the chat
window if you are not. And I'll just keep that one
open pole everywhere. Question for your requests
running throughout the.
The duration of this session, which may not even
last, the the full schedule time.
And I think we can get away with this in part
because this material from week six, setting up
the grand canonical ensemble is very much it's
very similar to a very much a parallel to the work
that we went through back in week three, moving
from the micro canonical ensemble to the canonical
ensemble. So just as a reminder, I imagine I said
this in the videos that go along with these notes,
but no harm in repeating myself that the
microeconomic ensemble was our starting point
because it very directly implements some
fundamental physical principles like conservation
of energy and conservation of article number. But
that means that it is inconvenient to work with in
experimental settings where energy is typically
flowing between the system being experimented on
and the individuals doing the experiments
themselves. And that motivated. Reformulating or
moving beyond the micro canonical formulation to a
different statistical ensemble, the canonical
ensemble where the particle number was still fixed
in the system, that that system was allowed to
exchange energy with its surroundings. And we. We.
Demanded that those surroundings were such that
the temperature of the system were kept fixed
whenever we apply to the canonical framework and
now in parallel to that, moving from a conserve
energy to a concert or to a fixed temperature, the
grand canonical ensemble removes that other
constraints conserve particle. No, and replaces
that with. Some other fixed quantity that is being
kept fixed by.
Connection with a large external reservoir where
now? If my screen wakes up. Now that external
reservoir exchanges both energy and particles with
the system. So going through the same.
Mathematical replica trick. Well, I should say we
define the chemical potential as the antidote to
the temperature that is being kept fixed and. With
that chemical potential new defined, we can go
through the same replica trick to put this. System
on a.
Solid mathematical foundation, and that involves.
Using our usual definition of thermodynamic
equilibrium as a state in which the entropy is
maximized.
To.
Determine the condition of thermodynamic
equilibrium subject now to three constraints, two
of which we saw before in week three, one of those
constraints is the usual one that probabilities
you have to add up to one. We demand that energy
is conserved in the overall universe that consists
of all of these replicas, and we now have to
demand also that the total number of particles in
the universe are similarly conserved.
So the. First question that was. Going to, he
asked.
In the sort of pull everywhere approach for this
week, there's going to be looking at this.
Constrained entropy maximization problem on page
86 and given the numbers, I think it's most
worthwhile just for me to talk that through
quickly and you can speak up if anything is
unclear or you can speak up if all of you already
have this worked out in front of you. And it would
be a waste of all our time to to consider it.
So feel free to interrupt, I'll just charge ahead
without waiting for any reactions, responses or
questions and just grind through the usual sort of
calculation that we have, which is taking a
derivative of this. Modified Essabar function,
which is both the usual entropy for this mini
replica system, along with the three constraints I
just summarized, where taking the derivative of
this, these sums over the occupation probabilities
peahi with respect to some piqué just picks out
Delta functions with Ion K and then.
Quickly gives us a.
Much simpler system.
A much simpler equation where.
The delts, the. You know, Delta function of I
think it picks up a lot of piqué, then we take the
derivative of the log, gives a one over P.
multiplied by IPE is one. Then there is just a
simple factor of Alpha with that Delta function,
that is some day over an hour. Time to speed up
with the energy coming from the Delta function.
And finally, this last. The fire. Gamma are the
particle number we are rearranging. Thing is to
isolate the.
Only place where the occupation probability now
shows up. We have. Four terms on the right hand
side.
And taking the exponential of both sides and
rearranging things slightly, we.
End up with.
A ratio of exponential. That's.
Puts things in the standard form for this
probability, one over now, a grand canonical
partition function and then a generalized
Boltzmann factor. And involves both the energy and
particle number of. The system and I realize now.
That I was going to actually skip ahead to look at
this entropy, now that's. We have. One of those.
Legrand's multipliers defined in terms of the
other two that created canonical partition
function. Is just the sum over microstates of that
exponential factor, the generalisable, some factor
into the minus beta at times energy plus Gamma
Times article number. And plugging that in to this
expression for the entropy on the bottom of page.
Six is.
Giving us. The following expression.
So I've kept one of these occupation probabilities
just hanging around with some.
Advance planning and plugging in the other
expression for the occupation probabilities one
over Z times, E to the minus beta energy plus
gamma particle. No, all we need to do is.
Distributes that's logarithm, the logarithm of a
product is the sum of the corresponding logarithms
of its terms. So that pulls out a.
Minus Log Z. And the minus signs cancels.
Star Log Z. Times that sum of probabilities. And
then the minus signs again, cancel from taking the
log of E to the minus beta energy. So it's beta
are.
And then. We have some of her I have those
probabilities with a microstates dependence factor
of the energy that we can't pull out of the sun.
And similarly for.
The last term now with a different sign and a sum
over the particle numbers rather than the micro
state entities, and you can recall the
probabilities over all microstates sum up to one
and the other. Some defined the usual expectation
values, so this all boils down to a beat. Times
are times.
The. Expectation value with this factor of, ah, we
can recognize I'm taking this ah. To the right
hand side and. Looking in occupation probability
in place of the olsun factor and. When partition
function. Oops. And slide back down and pick out.
That total energy was a factor of Beita in the
total particle number with the factor of Gamma.
And again, any questions, as we just talked
through some of these aspects of the derivation,
feel free to. Unu taught us to toss them in the
chat or toss them in everywhere, and I'll flip
back and forth between various screens to try to
keep an eye on things and. The key developments
with this replica trick, just as it was for the
canonical ensemble, was that we are able to
determine these Legrange multipliers purely in
terms of that temperature and chemical potential.
That are fixed for our small system with no or for
a grand canonical system with no reference to the
much larger external particle reservoir that it is
in contact with.
In this lets us express every aspect of our great
canonical system simply in terms of its
temperature and chemical potential. Which brings
us. To during this
similar sort of calculation. Now, toward the end
of the notes for the week on page 90, we played
this where we do the similar.
Calculation of.
Plugging in the.
Micro state probability is now high in terms of.
The temperature and chemical potential rather than
the mid-range multiplier gamma, it's the sun there
is for a single micro state, I you have the
exponential of the inverse temperature times, the
energy. Plus, the chemical potential over that
temperature in the particle number so that
expanding the logarithm of that probability. It
was just that same grand chemical partition
function. Better times, the energy and of you.
Times the particle number, which, again, something
over all the microstates with the corresponding
probabilities defines the expectation. Values.
Better times the average expectation value for the
internal energy and. Beat a few times.
The expectation value for the particle number,
which you can recognize, is.
The accommodation that. Had just been computed,
the derivative of the grand potential, the
analogue of the Helmholtz, free energy with
respect to the temperature.
And know that a few more people have joined in,
I'm wondering whether or not. It's worth.
Trying to do a whole.
Maybe we'll try it. See how it goes just to check
in. So that was the equilibrium entropy on page
eighty six we just discussed. The.
Corresponding derivative of that creative
potential with respect to. The chemical potential
now, instead of the temperature maybe worth taking
a look at, and that is on the previous page here.
Eighty nine.
Where? This. Grant medical potential itself, the
definition does not quite fit on the same screen.
And while that poll is up and running for. You to
interact with,
I can quickly copy over the. Definition that we
have this fight is. Negative temperature at times.
The longer the grand economical partition function.
We're. The legal petition function is something
over all the microstates.
With this.
Combined factor of energy and particle number,
chemical potential, having dimensions of energy to
get everything consistent in. Exponential function.
Responses are coming in and there's already a good
fractioned response who have responded so. I won't
wait another minute or less before. Moving on.
And taking a look at your responses, if the.
Screen wakes up here, they are evenly split.
Between options B and D, so going through this
myself, I would plug in.
Pull out that overall factor of the temperature,
which is not.
Affected by the. Derivative with the with respect
to the chemical potential, and then.
The derivative of the logarithm, you remember, and
let me convert this into a bit of the inverse
temperature that I. Used in the. Statement of the
problem to set us off here, the derivative of a
log is one over Z times. You acting on Z, which is.
The sun. Over this. Generalised exponential factor.
Where the chemical potential Mbewe appears in only
one place.
I'll just circle here in the same colors,
hopefully leaving things still legible, so taking
the derivative of the exponential brings down a
factor of plus Beta and I. So we have a beta over
beta, whatever zg then a sum over I of that in I.
In the exponential. Persists.
And we can recognize the one over Z in the.
Exponentially weighted probabilities as
probabilities that are defining the.
The defining the expectation value over in and I
paused because I noticed that I forgot to. Retain
the negative sign from the previous line, so we
have a negative one times that expectation value
of an. Which was an option D in the poll.
And.
Because.
This development of the the grand canonical
ensemble is.
So closely aligned with the.
Earlier development of the canonical ensemble we
end up with. Final results that look very similar,
the entropy in terms of the derivative of. This.
Minus two times the lord of the partition function
and similarly the. Internal energy is. Related to
the derivative of just the log itself, canceling
out that overall factor of the temperature. And.
In addition to letting us generalize that first
law of thermodynamics to a generalized
thermodynamic relation. The.
The one last thing and I want to to bring up today
before. This module goes on its break
would be to. Actually dig a little bit deeper into
the connection between. The grand canonical
ensemble and the canonical ensemble in the form of
the corresponding partition functions, and I made
it a bit of blank space for this, which we have
here.
What I.
Points out zooming in. Slightly.
Is if I write grand canonical partition function
and noting that it is this function of temperature
and chemical potential that we saw was the sum of
all the microstates of each of the minus beta. I
was the energy of the microstates. Plus, beta, the
inverse temperature times, the chemical potential
times, the number of particles in that microstates
and just using the properties of an exponential
function, you can break. That's. Single factor
into two factors and even two factors, one of
which is raised to a power exponentially raised to
a power, just multiply the existing argument of
the exponential and then that of the minus Beta
Etai. That is familiar from the canonical example
is still coming along for the ride. And if we do
the usual trick of supposing we have a finite
number of microstates in freely rearranging the
terms of the sun, we can break up the overall sum
into all of the microstates into actually a sum of
sums that depend on the particle number in the
corresponding microstates. So picking out all of
the microstates where there are zero particles.
We were just have, you know, an exponential factor
raised to the power of zero is unity, so only the
E to the minus in temperature times, energy,
things around and doing the same when there is a
single particle. The single factor of the chemical
potential over temperature is the same.
Eat of minus energy over temperature.
And then.
We have two particles that factor gets squared.
The Boltzmann factor is the same as always and so
on off to however many particles we may have.
And we can do two things with the equation in this
form, the first one is can define a shorthand.
This letter, Zeda, is.
This combination e to the chemical potential over
temperature.
Which is known historically as the three Cassity.
This parameter Zeta, and we can recognize that.
Each of these songs that we've written here.
The specter of the sagacity is just a concept that
does not depend on the micro state and can be
pulled out in front of the sun. And what is left
in the sun over microstates is then just the.
Canonical partition function for a fixed number of
particles where I will write. That canonical
partition function as a Z with no subscripts, with
arguments of temperature and particle, no a
capital N..
Maybe I'll even make that a lower case and so it's
not confused with any of the particles in each
microstates, so this sum here is over all of the
microstates with zero particles. So that is just
the canonical partition function at the same
temperature. We had to begin with with zero
particles, and then we can add a factor of the
sagacity by. Least favorite Greek letter to write.
The canonical partition function with a single
particle. Plus, the gas, the squared.
The two particle canonical partition function and
so on and in general.
Writing this as a sum over the total number of
particles in canonical systems. Starting from zero,
and we can take the limit now off to infinity that
we've rearranged things healthily with a finite
number of microstates, if we Kassidy to the power
of the number of particles and the economical
competition function at our fixed temperature and
fixed particle number rather than fixed chemical
potential.
So this is a direct relation between. The grand
canonical partition function as an infinite sum
over canonical partition functions for all
possible numbers of particles showing the
connection between the canonical and grand
canonical formulation in. This is known as the
focus of the expansion, you may see it
referred to in those terms in.
In the resources, in Wikipedia, possibly in a in
the next homework assignment, depending on whether
this seems interesting enough to to dig into.
And really, just to. Wrap up by.
Demonstrating why this sort of perspective can be
useful if we see those are the six notes we have
here, if we hop back to. The lecture notes for
week for. When we started off.
Investigating the canonical partition function for
an ideal gas, we began by computing.
The partition function just for a single particle
of a gas in some volume v., which fixed the
possible moment. It could have and gave us the
form of the mini particle or the end particle
partition function in terms of the single particle
partition function that someone to the power in.
Where in terms of this. Thermal generally
wavelength, that single particle partition
function was just that total volume over.
Thirroul. Wavelength cubed.
Something. Even more interesting happens if we
consider the case of indistinguishable particles
where.
We saw that the. Distinguishable and
indistinguishable partition functions were just
related by this accounting factor, one over and
factorial, so long as we can assume that all of
these in particles have different energies where
that ratio of volume to. Definitely, wavelength
cubed is the single particle partition function.
And if we hop back now to the Grand Canal context
and we want to consider an ideal gas where the
particle number can change, we just have an open
container of gas where the gas particles are able
to wander in and out of the the topic for the open
sides of this unsealed container at will. Then.
It's looking in. That indistinguishable partition
function in terms of the single particle partition
functions and one.
You can immediately. Right down the grand little
partition function in terms of. It's the bottom of
the page in terms of the temperature and chemical
potential or. You can change variables to use
sagacity in place of that chemical potential, just
as some. Over all possible particle numbers.
Of the ferocity to the power and whatever and
Vectorial and said one to the power and or
rearranging things. Slightly. Whatever in
Vectorial Times, sagacity, time, single particle
partition function to the power end, which is the
serious expansion for the exponential function put
back in now.
The capacity in terms of the chemical potential
and temperature, so we get a very compact
expression for. The grand canonical position
function of a night of not an ideal gas is
indistinguishable particles should make a note of
that.
In terms of this single particle partition
function that we. Saw before was just the ratio of
the volume to the wavelength cubed. I can plug
that in here and now.
And that comes immediately from this connection
between canonical and grand canonical formulations
through the focus, the expansion and. This.
Exponential of an exponential is a fun feature
that often pops up in in the great economical
partition function, just indicating the sort of
scale of multiplicities or. Or systems that we are
working with here.
When not only can the number of particles often be.
Enormously large, like a factor of. And the power
twenty three, but were then taking exponential of
those sorts of power, 23 factors with exponential
functions inside the arguments of other
exponential functions, things get very large very
quickly in statistical physics. And that is. But
we will see in more detail with.
New applications of the grand canonical ensemble
after the term brake applied to quantum statistics.
We'll need to spend a little time introducing. The
new wrinkle of quantum statistics, which shows up
in the assumption I mentioned. Back in week four,
where we assume that all the particles occupied
different energy levels, if we discard that
assumption, things will turn out a bit differently.
And a bit more interesting ways that allow us to
connect with experimental observations, but this
is. All that I think there was to go through with
the asynchronous materials we have up to the break.
I will stop there, invite you again to ask
questions, and I'll be back in this room in about
15 minutes for office, hours after I've shut down,
Zuman extracted this recording. So any questions
about anything we have seen or done in the past
six weeks?
And if not, you can feel free to. Head off and
start enjoying your break, at least from this
launch of.