So I expect some more people to come in as we go
on and I'll get the recording underway and go
through the usual routine that we've established
over the past month where. I'll start off by
asking you if there are any questions on the
asynchronous materials for last week or this week,
last week being the ideal gas law in this week,
applying that to thermodynamic cycles and wrapping
up the three weeks that we're spending on not
interacting systems in the canonical ensemble
before moving on to the grand canonical ensemble.
And there is also a the first part of the computer
project. A lot of those submissions look good.
They're being marked right now to get back to you
within the next week. And then the first homework
assignment is due a week from tomorrow. So.
Everything is in full swing, and I should have,
while going through that discussion of
the location we are in, the chorus I should have
brought up. The the end of the week, four notes,
the beginning of week five, which is where we left
off last time, with that transition from deriving
the ideal gas law as an example of an equation of
states to applying it to thermodynamic cycles,
processes in which we change the the macro state
of some system, it's pressure, volume, temperature,
entropy, internal energy, and can imagine
stringing together a sequence of such changes in
such a way that they all end up. Back at the
initial conditions and the processes, the sequence
can then be repeated over and over and over again
to make useful, interesting things happen.
So I'm just pausing for a moment to give you a
chance to type in questions, and I'll reiterate
that you're more than welcome to. Post them on,
zoom in the chat window or just speaking up, am
using yourself as well, and if no questions or
requests come in the next few seconds, I'll switch
over to asking you about some questions about the
material just to check the way that the concepts
are coming through well enough in the in the
asynchronous materials and build on them to to
show what all of this material is useful for.
So without further ado, I should have now
activated a
different question in the usual poll, looking at
the the ideal gas law and the application of the
ideal gas law to model the the actual atmosphere
of the Earth, which in round numbers is about 80
percent nitrogen and 20 percent oxygen. And the
ideal gas law is sufficient to let us relates the
overall pressure of the atmosphere to the pressure
of its individual. Components. I'll make sure that
those of you who have entered in the last few
minutes have that direct link to the poll, and
since this is not in the the lecture notes, the
asynchronous materials that you got beforehand,
I'll give you a few minutes to think about it and.
Judge your responses.
Let's see, we've got about a quarter of. The
participants responding so far so. If you just a
bit longer and summarize the the options here,
which maybe I should have done in the first place
to give you some more time to think about it, that.
Given these two gases forming the atmosphere of
the earth, you have four options for the overall
pressure of that atmosphere. The first just being
the average pressure of each of those. The
pressure of nitrogen, plus the pressure of oxygen
divided by two, where we can bring in information
about the relative abundance of nitrogen, oxygen
in the air. If it's 80 percent nitrogen, we might
expect the overall pressure to be consists of 80
percent of the pressure of nitrogen, plus 20
percent of the pressure of the oxygen. Or just the
the direct some of the pressure of nitrogen, plus
the pressure of oxygen giving the overall pressure
of the air, or the fourth option is that we might
imagine that the pressure of all the components is
equal both to the total pressure and also to each
other. That is, the the nitrogen in the air has an
equal pressure to the oxygen, which has an equal
pressure to its mixture.
Let's see the responses that have come in so far
are evenly split. If the page will load of.
Fifty percent saying that all the pressures should
be equal and another 50 percent saying that the
pressure should be proportional to the abundances.
And we'll ask you with this on the screen how we
might use the ideal gas law to resolve this
disagreement and come up with a definitive
mathematical answer to this question.
Not hearing any volunteers, maybe I'll take a stab
at running through the application of the ideal
gas law to this case, let me find a nice piece of
margin to.
To put this where we have the ideal gas law
related to the pressure and volume of gas is to
the number of particles in that volume and their
temperature. So if we take this as input and
consider some. Volume of gas that has, you know,
80 percent nitrogen molecules and two and 20
percent.
Oxygen, then we can assume they have the same
temperature being in the same volume, and that
tells us that, say, the number of nitrogen
molecules is given by.
The pressure of that nitrogen times, that fixed
volume over that fixed temperature and similarly
for the oxygen,
and we know that the total number of particles is
going to be related to the total pressure of this
mixture, which we'll just call p the pressure with
no underscore. And it's also, I hope, intuitively
obvious that the total number of particles is the
sum of the number of each species, which she gives
us then.
He and finds that the poverty and oxygen times
that fixed the poverty, which we can cancel out
and get the result that the total pressure is the
sum of what I call the two partial pressures,
which hopefully was an option in the. A poll that
we just had here.
Of.
And this is one of the relations that was
mentioned in the historical context at the very
end of this week's notes, that a lot of these
so-called thermodynamic thermodynamic relations
between the macro state properties of the system,
pressure, volume, temperature and number of
particles were empirically observed even as far
back as the sixteen hundreds, well before the
development of the ideal gas law or understanding
of the statistical and atomic or molecular basis
of all of these emergent thermodynamic properties.
In this result that the pressure of the mixture is
equal to this, some of the pressures of all of the
individual components of that mixture was another
one of those empirical relations discovered before
the ideal gas was formulated, and in particular
during the the growth of industry in the late
seventeen hundreds and into the eighteen hundreds
in Europe. It is.
Become known as Dalton's law of partial pressures,
the partial pressure being.
The pressure of each component of the gas, the
nitrogen and the oxygen in this case and published,
I believe, around 18 won a couple of decades
before the ideal gas law itself. And as we saw, it
comes directly out of the ideal gas law relating
the pressure to the particle number, which is
something that we are more familiar with
adding. Adding up just linearly with No.
No need for detail considerations of how much of
each species is present, the less of a of the
fewer particles of the species there are, the less
pressure there is. And that accounts for the
abundance in this direct some. So let me go back
and we'll ask if there are any.
Questions about that derivation and explanation
before I move on to. To the next question that
will transition. Out of last week and into the
coming weeks material. And I know we are right at
the start of the week, so I'll try. Not to assume
you've gone through the entirety of the week five
notes through the nemec cycles in advance. We'll
see if we can stick to the first half of that and
the.
First.
Question that I am.
Activating now on this poll should be up is
actually tying together all three of the the weeks
that we are working on the canonical ensemble and
its application to ideal gas's, first in general
and then ideally gas's in thermodynamic cycles. So
just to give some background to this question. Can.
Look back to. Our lecture notes from week three
introducing the canonical ensemble where we
introduce this heat capacity as the. The response
of the internal energy with with respect to a
change in the temperature and we mentioned in a
footnote that the subscripts V on this severe heat
capacity refers to the fact that this particular
form of the heat capacity is assuming that the
volume of our system is kept fixed. This is the
heat capacity at constant volume.
And we mentioned that we hadn't yet considered the
role of the volume in. The heat and the internal
energy which was coming up in the the first
section of the ideal gas materials where we
related the volume of the container holding that
gas to the possible energy levels that could
occupy and thereby to the properties of the. The
system and.
The tablet is. Feeling a bit twitchy, but now we
are looking at the the first few pages of the
notes for the week starting today.
Where? We are.
Drawing a distinction between two possible ways of
changing the internal energy and the temperature
of an ideal gas in a particular volume, and we
have we saw in this. First section, that's the
work that is done on the gas by, say, compressing
its volume, applying some external force to move a
piston that forms one wall of its container, for
example, is only identified with the overall
change in internal energy when the entropy is
constant, when we are considering an adiabatic
process and more generally, there are two possible
contributions that can be made to that internal
energy which we identify with. On the one hand
that working, on the other hand, the flow of heat,
a change in the temperature of the gas without
changing its volume so that both the volume and
particle number are kept constant when heat is
flowing.
There's what I really wanted to underline, that
when the volume is constant, there is no
mechanical work done and the change in energy is
exactly the change in heat. And this connects us
to that constant volume heat capacity that we had
back in week three.
World now decorate it with a reminder that the
volume is kept fixed when we take the partial
derivative of the energy with respect to
temperature and because the volume is fixed, we
have this connection. That's the change in energy.
Is exactly the heat, which gives us, of course,
the the terminology for this quantity as a heat
capacity rather than the temperature dependence of
the energy. And that is all a prelude to looking
at the more general situation where. We may allow
both the energy and the entropy to change, and the
more general change in energy then
is the some. Of both that heat and the the work
that is done by the change in volume. So if you
want to look at the.
The overall.
Heat in this context, I'm not sure why the tablet
is being very slow to respond. At the moment.
Hopefully it's settled down now of this relation
tells us.
If you will wake up that the heat whose capacity
we want to define is in this more general
situation, not only the change in the energy, but
the difference between the change in the energy
and the work that is done,
where that work we saw in that first section and
I'll put a reminder here, was the negative of the
pressure times, the change in volume. So if the
volume is compressed, the volume is reduced. We
get a positive amount of work done on our system
by that process. And this relation between the.
Heat energy and work.
Motivates the definition of a an alternative heat
capacity, which is the one being asked about in
the poll now. Which is the heat capacity at
constant pressure rather than constant volume
where. No longer imposing a constant volume, the
there may be a non-zero heat, so we have to keep
track of both the sensitivity of the internal
energy to the temperature, constant pressure. Plus,
the.
And that w, of course, was a very. Plus, the
change in the volume with that change in
temperature again and a constant pressure, so
we've seen that.
Or we've discussed that if we heat up a an ideal
gas with, say, a constant force applied.
To that movable piston in the in the diagram we
just looked at earlier, as that gas is heated up,
its pressure will change. It will be able to push
out that piston and increase the volume just as a
consequence of adding energy, adding heat to
increase its temperature. So that is the
background for the question being asked here,
which is cycling back to
connect all three weeks material on the. The
canonical ensemble leading the heat capacity now
it and pressure, rather than cast a volume to the
ideal gases and particles and to the relation
between. Heat and work and energy. And I have.
Rambled on for a while to to get that all set up
for you to consider. So I will now shut up for a
few minutes and let you consider
how you would answer this question about the
constant pressure, heat capacity on the basis of
this equation written in the margins here, which I
hope is is legible. And let me know if it is not
or if any of the build up to this question. Was
not clear.
Let's see, about a quarter of responses have come
in, so another minute or two for those who are
still. Working on this.
And at this point.
I can get to the responses I see.
Not unanimity, but a preference for five here. So
just quickly confirm that, that if we conveniently
have the expression for the energy sitting right
here so we can plug in.
The derivative of that with respect to the
temperature, just the same at counterpressure and
at constant volume, so that three halves in was
the constant volume heat capacity we looked at
last week and then from the ideal gas. We have the
expression for. The volume in terms of the number
of particles, their temperature and the pressure,
so plugging that in to this derivative up here,
take the derivative with respect to t, it just
gets rid of that linear T. We have a P times and
over P and then a five has. And they're.
And I'll just ask for questions or concerns about
that little derivation. While I move on to the
next. And maybe recentre. This page. So all of it
is is visible.
Down there.
And let's see,
the next question is up, and this is asking about.
The.
The relation between idiomatic expansion and heats,
which comes up at a similar point in the notes
that I'll just review.
To give you a chance to think about this question,
where? We saw that we earlier defined in the
previous weeks work adiabatic processes to be
those where the Entropia. Is unchanged, and we saw
in this equation 65 there any change in the
entropy corresponds to the heat that is either
flowing into or flowing out of. Our our system as
it is manipulated.
And then changed in this process. And.
A way to understand this a bit more intuitively or
at least physically, is by saying that this
exchange of heat takes some time in which to occur
more or less time, depending on how isolated the
system is from its environments. But the faster
the process is carried out, the less time there is
for heat to be exchanged with its surroundings and
the less chance there is then for entropy to to be
created either in the system or its surroundings
through that flow of heat, which gives us the
intuition that adiabatic processes are fast while
the exchange of heat.
Requires that the process be a bit slower and real
processes typically are closer to the idiomatic
extreme than the extreme, where there is enough
fluid, the maximum amount of heat flows at every
stage of the process to keep the temperature fixed.
Where isothermal. And the question that I put up
here is to consider. Two identical systems. Like
that. Container with the piston. We had a picture
of and consider pulling out that piston to double
the volume of each in one case quickly so that
it's an adiabatic process and the other case not
quite so quickly, so that there is at least some
in flowing heat from the external surroundings
with which the system is initially in equilibrium.
So just to draw a.
Picture of that.
Taking advantage of.
This picture here, we start off with two of these
systems. And.
Approximately double their size one, idiomatically,
no heat flowing.
And the second, allowing some heat to enter from
the environment, both of these systems started off
with the same pressure of volume, temperature and
particle number.
And you can call the final pressures P1 and P2,
and the question is, what is the relation between
those pressures? Is P1 greater than P2, less than
pizza, or are they equal? Depending on how much
heat is or how much heat is, zero or non-zero
amount is able to flow into the system as it is
expanding.
I'll give you a minute or two or two to think
about that.
One response has already come in
while I was going through the set up.
And in this case, with multiple responses coming
in, we do have.
A consensus that. The the pressure is smaller
after adiabatic expansion and larger with heat
entering. There are a few ways you might have
gotten to that. Conclusion. First by. Noting from
the ideal gas law that he entering the system is
going to increase its temperature and thereby
increase its pressure, so any kid that is allowed
to exchange will pump up the temperature of the
amount of energy in the gas and thereby adds
pressure or could have jumped ahead to these
pressure volume diagrams. And in particular, the
second one shows that the adiabatic. Compression
and expansion is.
Taking us, just as I said, between two different
temperatures. One with the higher pressure, one
with a lower pressure, so identifying this, you
know, reversing the arrows on these lines to look
at expansion rather than compression can see that
in the extreme case of no heat exchange, the
pressure ends up.
Higher than in the. The resulting pressure. Coming
out of that adiabatic expansion. And perhaps I
should back up and just.
Motivates these this pressure building diagram of
it in the you know, the last bit of today's
meeting. This is a useful way of representing that
overall macro status of its limbic system, given
that the if we fixed the number of particles and
then the pressure and volume. Together determine.
The the temperature.
The temperature, in turn determines the internal
energy.
And the entropy can also be found from the flow of
heat and work in these processes, work being
related to the volume and pressure plotted on
these diagrams. So
the last.
Activity we'll talk about today is just. Check in
with one of the the first gaps that were in the
written materials this week asking about the
change in temperature and change in the pressure
from this adiabatic process. Shown here and in the
interest of time, maybe I'll ask you just to.
Check out the change in that pressure, which
should now be activated. On that pole everywhere
here.
And while you're thinking I can mention or make
explicit the terminology that the the line on that
pressure volume diagram for an adiabatic process
is known as an idea that whereas the corresponding
line for an isothermal process is known as the
nisso thurm, essentially turning adjectives into
nouns.
In a way that may not be the most elegant, but is
reasonably widespread. So some responses coming in
of a couple of minutes to for the rest of you to
consider that in particular, those who might not
have gotten to this in advance of Monday morning.
Now, only one response so far may be.
Getting worn out at the end of the session, so
I'll just go through the calculation quickly.
This tablet is able to get a little less twitchy
where all we need to do is start from the given
information that due to the constant entropy. This
particular combination of volume and temperature
is constant. And in particular, in the terminology
of this plot with
T notes and P not going to be final in P final.
Lake Constance, the key to the three halves of
that statement, which is the same as saying that
the volumes of the two thirds times the
temperature is constant and plugging in the.
Temperature in terms of the ideal gas law. TV over
and over again is fixed, but the pressure and
volume.
P and V. Are able to change.
You can see that.
Canceling out the ends.
He told the not to the. Five thirds is fixed.
So that Diltz happy. Defined as the final minus
initial is.
The ratio dividing through both sides by that
violence of the five thirds minus one. Which was
indeed the option that was preferred.
So that brings us to the end of time. I will leave
that up in case I went through the algebraic
manipulations a bit quickly and leave the
recording running just a little while longer in
case any of you have any final questions here at
the end. If not, we will pick up on Thursday with
the remainder of thermodynamics cycles and the
last bit of. Our focus on the canonical ensemble
before moving into the grand canonical ensemble
and also be back in this TSOU meeting in about 10
minutes for office hours, I'll have to shut down
before then to get the recording saved and started
back up.
That is it for me today.