And I think while we wait for a few more folks to
trickle in just after the hour, it's worth getting
that recording started and setting up some or
going through some of the usual logistics,
including the usual initial question from the
people everywhere asking.
If there are any questions you want to see
discussed this week, where I do already have notes
of the question that came in on Monday to discuss
equation fifty four on what pages that page 63 of
the notes, which is the sixth page of the week for
lecture notes on. Fairly certain we will get to
that today. I just want to wrap up a bit of what
you were discussing with the energy levels for the
ideal gas in a cubic volume before moving on to
those derived quantities, the internal energy and
entropy.
And while. I have that poll up and running and.
Give you a few minutes to get any thoughts in
there can also go through the other aspects of
logistics for this week that, as you know, the
first part of the computer project was do just
about 36 hours ago. And most of those have been
submitted. There's still some time to submit
layouts for those of you who have not yet got
those in with some late penalties that are mild by
my standards. And since that is now hopefully out
of the way, the next homework assignment is
uploaded and available on canvas of all, depending
on your notification settings, you should have
gotten a notification about it when it was updated
earlier this week. Just going to the assignments
homework one and it is usual PDF linked from that
page in canvas. And available for you to work on
do at the end of Tuesday, 16th of March, so a week
from next Tuesday or 12 days from today.
And in equation 54, we will get to in due course,
but let's let me move on from that open request
for questions to.
Just wrapping up what we were discussing last week
with the.
Energy levels for.
This ideal gas in a cubic volume where you ran out
of time just before I could ask what I expected to
be, the last quick question about that, which I
will now bring up on that poll everywhere and.
That now leads that going back to this portion of
the notes just where we ended last time.
We saw that the three lowest energy levels coming
from these highest momenta are on sites to get a
well defined partitioned function for an ideal gas.
Those three energy levels for all integer
multiples of this quantity, each are squared pi
squared over 2m elsewhere where each bar is
Planck's constant and is the mass of the particles
in the gas and oil is the length of each side of
the cubic volume that the gas can find within. And
the question the follow up question to that is,
are all of the energy levels for this single
particle gas evenly spaced in general the way that
these three lowest ones are?
Debating which of these screens is the best to. To
have on the share,
let's stick with this one. You know, to keep an
eye on the responses.
Separately.
That's.
Mr..
Not many responses have come in yet, so. Continue
waiting in case you are. Reviewing the.
The general result from last week
or sorry, last time, one day this week.
So far, there's one response which is in agreement
with itself, so there's a 100 percent. Choice for
one of those four options. That's.
Why, I'm just giving it another few seconds for
those who are.
Still considering. How these energy, how these
disparities, energy levels work for just a single
particle in this volume. With our arms out for the
momentum.
Well, at this point, it's. May have gotten all the
responses that are going to come in there. There
are a serial number now. So if we look at.
What we have here, there's now an even split
between two of these options where if we.
Just recall, the general form for the energy is
coming from those inventor. You have.
From last time. It is a. Kay.
And the fact that the. Energies depend quadratics
on these integer, okay, tell us that not all of
the energies are going to be evenly spaced. They
will, in generality be quite radically spaced. And
the question is, when does that set in? Responses
have switched around now and. If we look at the
options for these three energy levels here. You
saw last time that they corresponded to.
These values of the Vector's K being all Xeros
having one non-zero entry or two and six or in
permutations thereof if we have.
Talk of one one, one that energy is three times
the usual units, which I'll call that a lowercase
E. And we can go on to consider. To.
Zero zero with an energy of four.
Two one zero. With an energy. Five.
And it looks like I actually made a mistake in the
counting of the whole everywhere problem problems
made these quiz question, which may be why there
were relatively few responses. When we get up to
two on one, that energy is 60, but there is no way
to get seven units of energy from these integer
squares. So after that seventh level, which is an
energy of six, which is where that miscounting
came from, I apologize for we jump straight up to
to come to an energy of eight units. So that
hopefully is now.
Clear to see, having written down the overall
formula went.
But a bit longer than I expected. So let's set
aside the.
Individual energy for this particle and for this
ideal gas and cubic container and skip through all
of these manipulations going from the.
Disparities moment back to continuous moments in
integrating over those to get to the partition
functions for distinguishable and
indistinguishable particles in the gas, we're now
approaching the question that was asked about
equation. Fifty four coming up. Before we get
there, though, let me.
Ask one quick question that did not appear in. The
asynchronous material, which is.
If I can get to it up here, what is the heat
capacity for this ideal gas with in particles? And
as we saw in equation fifty four, that this
doesn't depend on whether or not those particles
are distinguishable or indistinguishable. It is a
fixed answer for both cases. And since that was
not something you were asked to consider in
advance, give you a.
A minute or two to think about it.
Responses have started coming in and.
We'll wait for more to accumulate.
Spacings.
I'll make this the
last call for responses which may be slowing down.
And there is, again, a.
Even split between two of these options, so
I'll go through this briefly that recalling the
heat capacity.
Is.
The derivative of the internal energy with respect
to the temperature at a fixed volume, then this
equation 54 gives us the derivative of T with T is
one in the constant three has N comes out as the
heat capacity. And that was one of those options
that I'll select there, and that brings us to the
equation 54 that. Was asked about, so I'll turn on
the open
response polls from that back on while we look at
this equation. Fifty four.
In more detail, and I suspect the question has to
do with this footnote here and the observation
that
in contrast to the spin system considered at the
end of the week, three material introducing the
canonical ensemble. There we saw that the energy
and the entropy were both different for
distinguishable versus indistinguishable particles,
in this case distinguishable versus
indistinguishable spins. This is the energy on the
left. And the entropy on the right now that we're
looking at an ideal gas, we find that the energy
is always the same independent of the
distinguished ability or indistinguishably of the
particles. In this ideal gas, though, there is
still a difference in the entropy. So in a sense,
that difference of the entropy is what we may have
expected coming from last week and the. Identical
internal energies are potentially more surprising
in this footnote here, mentions, if you were
surprised by. That results that the reason for it
is it has to do with how the microstates match up
or how the partitioned function matches up between
these cases of distinguishable and
indistinguishable particles, which
takes us back up to the previous section of the
nose where we were computing those two partition
functions for the case of distinguishable and
indistinguishable particles. And just as a quick
reminder that I will. Reuse this box as empty
space to to scratch in rather than confining
myself to the margins. The partition function for
indistinguishable particles is the sum over all of
those microstates I. Of the bowsman factor,
exponential to the negative energy of that micro
state divided by the temperature or multiplied by
the inverse temperature beta. And we argued and
there was a gap where you hopefully convince
yourself that every microstates of
indistinguishable particles in an ideal gas
corresponds to in factorial different microstates
of if those particles are distinguishable. And
that simply comes from taking all those particles
and slapping labels on each one and declaring a
different micro state for every permutation of
those labels, which provides that an vectorial
accounting factor. So. From that, we saw that the
partition function for distinguishable particles.
I was just in factorial.
Times that sum over the microstates the N
factorial is independent of the energy. So it's a
cost factor that can come outside the sum which
gives us that factorial times the
indistinguishable, partitioned function.
And going back to last week's work on the
canonical example, in general, we had the
revelation that the internal energy is the
negative. Derivative with respect to that internal
temperature of the logarithm of the partitioned
function. So if we consider here the partition
function for the distinguishable case, that means
that we're looking at the distinguishable internal
energy there. We have the
derivative with this constant factor of log and
factorial pulled out of that product.
Just using the usual properties of logarithms, the
derivative of this constant vanishes and we then
find. That
the internal energy in the distinguishable case is
identical to the internal energy in the
indistinguishable case, regardless of what the
particular form of those energies are in each
microstates. It only depends on whether this
different counting factor or whether really the
partition functions are directly proportional
to each other. Any constant factors multiplied by
multiplying the partition function will drop out
in the determination of the internal energy simply
because it's the.
Derivative of a logarithm, perhaps another way of
writing that or seeing it is to apply the
properties of derivatives of Florida rhythms that
it ends up with a one over Z D at DeVita. So in
the overall cost and factors in this Z in the
numerator and the one over Z that comes out from
the derivative of the log are going to cancel out.
And that is, you know, for professionals, that's a
very useful result and useful facts to to be aware
of that any causal factor is just drop out of the
internal energy because of factors in the
partition function, drop out of the internal
energy. And if we hop back to the case considered
last week in the canonical ensemble, we can see
why the simplification was not applicable. So this
here is the starting expression for the
indistinguishable partition function, in that case,
something over the energy levels. Here we have a
gas of spins that are indistinguishable rather
than. Particles with some kinetic energy and if we
want to.
Relate this.
Indistinguishable partition function to the
distinguishable case, we have to think about how
many different microstates there would be with
each of those energy levels if the spin's were
distinguishable. So just to consider some simple
cases in the case equals zero ground state with
the minimum energy, there's only a single
microstates.
Regardless of whether or not the spins are
distinguishable in here, I'm assuming that the
external magnetic field is oriented downward so
that all of those guys are parallel to it,
contributing negative energy. So there is
the same number of microstates in the
distinguishable and indistinguishable cases. So
there's a causal factor of one going up to the
first excited state.
We had. There's a comment that we had we might
have gone through this exercise already in the
notes that I'll wrap it up. Since it's.
Almost done here, if we can distinguish these
spins, you know, any one of the end can be
oriented opposite to that external magnetic field.
So there are and possible states and in full
generality. We have this son of interviews, K
Times, these energy is better times, E.K., which
is minus and H plus to HK So the key here is that.
This.
Victor, I'm not sure why. This program is trying
to change the screen rather than just underlining
that factor, that counting factor going from
indistinguishable to distinguishable is
dependent. And there's no overall a constant
factor that can be pulled out to relate to
distinguishable and indistinguishable partition
functions. The thing to do is to rearrange all of
the terms of this finite sum to match up the
distinguishable micro states with positive and
negative energies, which ends up producing. That.
Result that we saw earlier, that the distinction,
the case is the exponential of.
E to the minus beta age plus either the plus B to
age race to the power of N, which if we compare
that to. The full indistinguishable case is not
directly proportional to it, so that is the
explanation. Stated here is that counting factor
that varies with the energy and so rather than the
simple constants relating those to partition
functions we ended up with.
Non constant values that did not vanish in the
logarithmic derivative, providing the energy.
Pause for just a moment to see if any other
questions have come in or if there are follow up
questions about that whole discussion, essentially.
Going through that background explanation and a
bit more detail and diving into the. Fundamental
reasons for this change in behavior.
And not hearing any, I think, the remaining time.
Today, let's see fundamental reasons.
This is the I'm not sure if.
Your last comment in the chat window is a question
or just a comment? The fundamental reason for this
difference is the. The distinction, whether or not
the distinguishable and indistinguishable
partition functions are directly proportional to
each other, they are in the case of an ideal gas
and they are not in the case of a spin system. And
that is what goes through the calculation to
produce. That
net result, that different behavior in the two
energies.
So in the time remaining, I think we will be able
to do just one quick conceptual question and then
maybe a somewhat more detailed
computation, looking at the entropy for the ideal
gas, in particular, the mixing entropy that shows
up in this conversation or this section on the we
call it so-called gives paradox, which we saw is
not actually a paradox.
So switching over to. The whole here.
Just asking something that
doesn't necessarily need any formal computation,
it's more of an.
Developing an intuition for how information and
entropy are related. The question is, how do you
expect the entropy of an ideal gas to depend on
the distinguished ability of the particles in that
gas?
And more generally, this is even something that
could be considered.
For generic statistical systems, how would entropy
in general depend on the distinguished ability of
particles? What we can consider is just the ideal
use case for
to keep things more concrete and avoid having to
worry about whether we've captured all
possibilities.
I'll give you a minute or two to think about and
respond. To that, again, without a need for
detailed calculations.
But it's just instinct or intuition or.
And understanding the concept of how. And how
entropy and information are related.
And we do have multiple responses already that all
were in agreement about.
The.
The fact that the distinguishable particles, we
should expect a larger entropy and the conceptual
reason for this is that we can think of entropy as
to some extent a measure of the amount of
information in the system. And being able to
distinguish particles provides a. Provides more
information that we can extract from a given
system, and this is also visible in both the plots
that we had last week where
the distinguishable entropy was larger than the
indices in the case and also visible in this
equation. Fifty five here for the ideal gas,
specifically where all the leading behavior of the
entropy is constant. The logarithmic correction in
the indistinguishable case is suppressed by this
factor of end, which is typically a large number.
So now the more detailed question that will wrap
up. Today's meeting is going back here to
get this up and.
Running.
It has to do with the.
Calculation gone through on page 64 of the notes,
which is Nancy see, let me get to that, the
seventh page of the PDF, where we have two initial
systems, A and B, with the same number of
particles in the same size volume with a cell wall
separating those two volumes, A and B.
When we remove that wall, the particles in those
two initial systems and B are allowed to mix in A
combined system C and then the wall is reinserted
and using gives his argument, we can assume that
to a good approximation, when that wall is
reinserted, there will be an equal or
approximately equal number of particles in each of
the two redivided systems.
A prime and be prime. And in the notes, without
too much in the way of gaffes for you to consider,
we went through the calculations in the case where
all the particles were indistinguishable, in which
case the.
Removing or reinserting the wall had no effect on
the entropy was constant from each of these stages
to the next, and we also looked at the fully
distinguishable case where every particle could be
distinguished from all the others. In that case,
there was a mixing entropy that
was added to the system upon removing the wall,
and that persisted after that wall was reinserted
just because it was not possible to get all the
way back to the initial states where the specific
particles A.B.C. were all in. The same subsystem
where they had started off, so now the question
that is up in the
polls everywhere is asking about an intermediate
case where we suppose that the three particles or
all of the particles in System A are
indistinguishable from each other, but they can be
distinguished from the particles initially in
System B, maybe say one of these these particles
are. In this case, red particles and systemis and
green particles and System B.
Or we could consider, say, oxygen consistency in
nitrogen molecules and System B that.
Are indistinguishable from each other. But
distinguishable from one set compared to that
other set, and the question is not looking at
reinserting the again, but just considering
removing the wall and combining these systems and
B to form C, so let me zoom in on. That case, is
there a. Mixing entropy in this intermediate
situation.
And I'll remind you, in case you don't have it in
front of you, that's the.
Two in law, two
mentioned in three of the possible responses, here
is the mixing entropy from the completely
distinguishable case. So we had the full
information about every single particle could
label each of them uniquely and distinguish each
of them from the other. That's equation 58 on page
sixty six, page nine of that PDF. Just a couple of
pages further down from this picture we're looking
at here.
Let's say it looks like only one response has come
in so far in the interest of time, I may.
Started going through the calculation that you
would do to to answer this question, and that
response is.
Arguing that the mixing entropy from the system
where. The particles are indistinguishable within
each of the initial cell volumes would be greater
than the mixing entropy of the fully
distinguishable case. So let's go through the
calculation and see how that comes out, where
actually the entropy in the. Initial states, s.A
plus SB. Turns out to be just the same as in the
Gap on the following page, considered here because
the particles are indistinguishable within each of
these cell volumes. So we just have twice the
quintessential entropy for a system of particles
in a volume V, which is written down up above
three N plus two and times this logarithm of e.V.
over in lambda cubed. That lambda is the thermal
devilly wavelength.
Defined above and now for the case of.
The combined system,
what do we have?
Well, we're out of time, so I will just tell you
that because the particles are not interacting
with each other, what we have is a system of in.
Indistinguishable red particles that are now in a
doubled volume.
So there are none of those guys and there are also
an indistinguishable green particles in that same
double volume, so. The change going from the
separate to the combined systems is in the volume
that the particles are. Able to occupy, which
affects their energy levels and affects their
entropies. Like so.
And if we look at the difference between.
The combined and.
Initially separated systems, well, the constant
factors of three and drop outs and all of the.
Arguments of that law cancel out with the
corresponding arguments in there, and we are left
with
two and more to two from that factor of two coming
from the volume. So the.
Response I would get is actually the same. Mixing
entropy for this sort of intermediate case, as for
the fully distinguishable case that you went
through in the notes here, which is
something I might find a bit surprising.
Just trying to work on conceptual intuition rather
than going through the calculation, given that.
You know, the partial distinguished ability
provides only part of the full information is full
distinguished ability. Despite that, it still
produces the same mixing entropy in the set up.
And it may be fun to go through the calculation to
see what happens when the wall is reinserted. I'll
leave that for you and possibly put it on the.
Second homework assignment after the break. But
for now, I'll I'll stop talking there, see if you
have any final questions for today and come back
in a few minutes for office hours at the same zoo
meeting. I will shut down the meeting in order to
extract the recording and then restart it. I'll be
back here at the top of the hour.