OK, the recording should now be running, we should
get underway on bright and Sunny. Afternoon here
in Liverpool with the usual setup and the start
off that may be familiar at this point of the term,
the. Screen shared unioned. Start off with the
usual pull, you see if there are. Any questions or
requests about things to focus on today and if
there are not, at least while folks may continue
to.
Enter and join the meeting over the next few
minutes. Can comment on. Some of the logistics
looking ahead towards the end of term, so the ramp
up for the continuous assessment, the second
homework assignment is due next Tuesday. And of
course, questions on that are. Welcome in the
synchronous sessions, there is a limit to how
directly and I can answer them. And after that, I
heard this morning that the. Semester two exam
timetable has finally now appeared with the
statistical physics exam scheduled for Tuesday,
the 25th of May. So a little over a month from now
and a little under a month after that last
homework is due.
And some sample exams and sample problems for
additional preparation are already on the canvass
sites and more will be added as the actual course
content for the for the module starts to wind down.
And checking it again to see that.
No questions have come in yet. I can. Hop over to.
Where we got to on one day and just pick up from
there, going through the materials, commenting on
both some of the actual stuff that's in here that
you can, of course, read for yourself, as well as
going beyond that to give some supplemental
background information for for those who may be
curious, it's trying to anticipate what might be
of interest and also maybe highlighting some of
the connections of this module to other aspects of
mathematics and physics. So. Where we wrapped up
last time was.
Elaborating on. How the photon energy is being
linearly proportional to their momentum rather
than proportional to the momentum squared like we
saw for non relativistic particles that can be
before, this is the opposite of a relativistic
limit. We went through the general relation
between mass energy and kinetic energy that
connects these two elements of non relativistic
appleford relativistic particles, but the. More
usual way of presenting the energy for ultra
relativistic particles like photons is to hop over
to looking at them as waves through a physics
concept known as wave particle duality that we
don't need to get into here. What this does is
connect the momentum of a photon or any other
relativistic particle to a wavelength or. The
inverse of that wavelength is known as the
frequency. The frequency is essentially
how many? Peaks and troughs of a wave past an
observer and a given amount of time, and that
depends on two things. First, how quickly the wave
is traveling, and secondly, how far apart those
peaks and troughs are spaced. That distance
between the peaks and troughs is precisely the
wave length and the speed of the wave. In the case
of photons is exactly that speed of light, see?
Which gives this generic relation for waves
between frequency and wavelength that.
The product of frequency times wavelength is equal
to the speed of propagation of the wave, which. We
can illustrate through. Some additional graphics
beyond what I included in the lecture notes here,
and we'll look at that just by observing that this
relation between the momentum of a photon and its
corresponding wavelength, once we have quanties,
these particles, by working in a finite volume. As
as we started doing way back in week four and in
reviewed over the past week, we end up with that
full time energy. Equals P, C just becomes an
expression again now proportional to the frequency
of the wave, the frequency of the photon at the
photon energy is far omega. And this is
illustrated in a bit more detail in this picture
here, which is showing a couple of aspects of
energies and wavelengths for waves of light.
Understood here we're getting a bit beyond the
core material for the module into a bit more of
the physics background that may be of interest,
where the folks on, when considered as a wave, is
specifically a wave in an electromagnetic field.
So this is the general electromagnetic spectrum.
The full range of possible wavelengths for.
For photons and as the wavelength gets longer over
on the left side. Of this picture here, which I.
Looks like I should be able to draw on. We'll see.
And will that works. Nothing showing up, so.
Looks like it will just be commentary and not
colouring in, but over on the left side. Off the
top of the stigma, we have the the long wavelength
regime looking at waves getting up to
a kilometer or more in size, similar to the size
of buildings and cities, which from the.
Connection between energy and frequency and the
connection then between frequency as the inverse
of wavelength we know corresponds to low energies
and low frequencies from long wavelengths.
And as we move up through many orders of magnitude
in wavelength and in photon frequency, we
eventually get into the microwave and then even
after that, the visible spectrum of a few hundred
nanometer wavelengths, both of which pop up at
different points in the materials for for this
week, microwaves in the guise of the cosmic
microwave background, invisible lights as the
wavelengths where the radiation from the sun
reaching the earth is is maximal and then going on
even further to shorter wavelengths at higher
frequencies that correspond to higher energies. We
get past the ultraviolet into X-ray and gamma ray
photons, which. As I should also point out, the
the very bottom aspect of this picture here that.
Those higher energy photons with higher
frequencies and shorter wavelengths are emitted by
objects with higher and higher temperatures. The
visible spectrum corresponding to temperatures
around a few thousand Kelvin like the surface
temperature of of our sun. And getting up into x
rays and gamma rays requires temperatures getting
up into the millions or tens of millions of Kelvin,
which is more like the interior temperature of
stars like the white dwarfs that will appear in
the materials next week.
So one other aspect of photons that. Is mentioned
here in maybe. Interesting to elaborate on is this
overall factor of two. Which not assuming any
physics background and for this material. You
mentioned just came from the fact that any given
energy level for a photon comes in, comes with a
partner or a pair. So for every single energy
related to a quantized frequency in this equation,
ninety nine, there are two degenerate energy
levels with precisely that energy and the.
Specific feature or quantum number that
distinguishes those two energy levels with the
same energy is something known as the polarization
of the photon, which again is easiest to.
Appreciate by picturing photogs as these
propagating waves in the electromagnetic field.
Where? The small little graphic here is showing
precisely that sort of. Propagating waves in an
electromagnetic field. The red portion of the wave
is the electric part, the blue portion is the
magnetic part, and they have to come at this 90
degree angle where we have a photon propagating
along the y axis in this diagram with. The
electric parts oscillating or waving linearly in
the Z direction and the magnetic part oscillating
in the direction. And this is one of the two
possible polarizations for this photon, this
electromagnetic wave with this particular
frequency. In the other colorization comes just
from rotating. This wave by 90 degrees about that
y it's propagating alone, and so in that case, the
the red portion corresponding to the electric
parts of the electromagnetic field would be
oscillating back and forth in the X direction
rather than the Z direction. And the blue magnetic
parts of the wave would be oscillating back and
forth in the Z direction.
So all photons, all the electromagnetic waves can
be split up into those two separate polarizations,
each of which forms a distinct energy level with
the identical energy. And what are the other five
of those is what gets filtered out by polarized
sunglasses to give an everyday connection of this
image, of this concept. So if you were to take two
pairs of polarized sunglasses and hold them up at
90 degrees to each other, the first pair of those
sunglasses would filter out one of these
polarizations of the photons coming in. The second
pair oriented 90 degrees to it would filter out
the other pair and exactly no lights would get
through, which is a nice experiment you can do.
Well, maybe not at home, but maybe in a sunglass
shop, if you will, depending on how many pairs of
sunglasses you have just to.
Confirm that the sunglasses are, in fact,
polarized and see how the polarization of light,
these two degenerate energy levels for every four
started to degenerate energy levels for every
frequency of photon that defines this energy show
up. In.
In our everyday world, so. The big simplification
and the reason that. We focus only on four times
in this week's material is that. Photons,
especially in a large volume, are extremely easy
to create and destroy. There's an enormous flood
of photons coming in right now off of your screen,
out of any lights that you might have on or coming
in through any windows that are also being
absorbed by all of the materials giving those
materials their distinctive color. And what this
amounts to is that the amount of energy being
introduced or removed from the gas of photons that
were swimming in is. Extremely small for any one
of those given photons. And hence the
corresponding chemical potential defined as the
change in energy. Resulting from adding or
removing one photon at a fixed entropy, so any
radically changing the number of photons in the
gas is essentially zero for the photon gas so that
the.
Grand canonical partition function and its
corresponding logarithm, the grand canonical
potential just ends up with no further dependence
on the chemical potential, depending only on the
photon energy, and through that, the photon
frequency. Omega, in all, we could go through
these same sorts of calculation steps for.
More generic ozone's with a non zero chemical
potential, in particular, a negative chemical
potential in order for the number of density of
the ozone gas to remain finite, that adds a. A
significant amount of complication and. Additional
complexity, and so it's something that. I won't
even get into in the synchronous session except
for maybe some generic remarks, if there's
interest, you can just refer you to some of the
additional references at the very start of the
lecture notes, in particular, David Tong's
statistical physics lectures and also the text
book by Dan Schroeder. Both go into these
calculations for.
Massive Lozano's with a non-zero chemical
potential where we need to introduce concepts of
the density of states and actually end up being
able to observe a phase transition in a non
interacting ideal system, which is quite unusual,
that phase transition is going between two
different phases of matter. The the gases that
we're looking at here for photons is one of those
phases. And the other phase is what's called a
Bose Einstein condensate that exists at low
temperatures was predicted theoretically by both
an Einstein, a good 70 years before technology was
sufficiently advanced to create it in the 1990s,
which was very promptly awarded the 2001 Nobel
Prize in physics. So
that's an aside that I will leave for later and
first go through the simpler case of the photon
gas with varnishing chemical potential. Looking
first at.
Some of the.
Recasting of the great economic potential that
we're able to do precisely because large volumes
are easy to come by compared to the wavelengths of
photons, often on those micrometer or even
nanometre scales.
So going through the same sort of trick that we
didn't work for in the case of a classical, non
relativistic ideal, gas you replace the sun is
over discrete momenta with a. Integration over the
corresponding real variables that I decorate with
the hat here. This turns out to be. As we will see,
an excellent approximation, and because the photon
energy only depends on the magnitude. Of this
momentum index by Kohat. We can carry out the
angular portions of these intervals, getting the
positive octet of the three sphere, I think I
merged together two words, both the three and the
sphere, that phrase. So keeping all of the
frequencies positive, we just pick out the. One
eighth of the total angle of the sphere that we're
integrating over a corresponding to positive
frequencies in the X, Y and Z direction, so the
total solid angle is surface area of a sphere for
pi divided by eight. And that gives us just as
integral over. Momenta, which we can then. Relate
back to the photon frequency. To turn into an
integration over the frequencies of these photons.
Recognizing from the factors of all that come in
through that changing variables, the overall
volume. Of the photographs, as well as its
temperature hanging out outside of this integral
over Frequency's Omega.
Quickly check the. People everywhere think that's
just going to hang out for the. Of course, of
today, and just checking to see that there are no
questions yet there, and those of you who are on
synchronously are, of course, free to hop in with
questions out loud or through the chat window. And
I won't bother to wait long for those I'll keep
charging ahead. With the commentary that part of
the reason for casting the Grand Canal as a
potential in the form of this integral over
frequencies has to do with connections to. Physics
experiments, or maybe better to say, physics,
observations of sources of photons, both light and
heat and ultraviolet radiation like radiation,
like gamma rays, where the typical measurements
being done in these.
Observations and experiments consists in measuring
how much energy is being carried by photons of a
particular frequency. So by pulling out this
integration over the frequency, the integrated. Of
the frequency is precisely the information being
measured in those experiments, and I do see that a
question came in to do the boxes on. Page 110 and
111, which. You have to do with carrying out the.
The actual integrals here. So we will get to that,
I think, before the end of today and before
carrying out the integrals, I'm going to. Just say
a few things about the integration itself, what
shows up in the. Integration of frequency and it
is, in fact, useful to hop ahead to that page. 110.
Where? In this box, we actually see the.
Integrated itself.
As computed earlier on, so playing out this
dependence on the frequency or magnitude in the
numerator with an exponential factor in the
denominator, and
in fact, I think the discussion works just as well.
Whichever order we do it in, whether we integrate
first and then look at the
look at the integration or going over or focus on
the integration and then complete the integration.
So let's carry out these integrals and then circle
back around in the lecture notes to comment on
some of the physics connections where what we need
to do.
For. This is a girl here on page 110 is getting
into the form of the integration that we're given
just above it, this fun combination of the game of
function and the remote Zeta function. And we see
that this integral here involves a factor of each
of the power X or as our starting point involves
the exponential factor of Beita times each our
times, amigo, which is the energy divided by
temperature calling the beta is the inverse
temperature. So our X to get these two integrals
into the same form. Needs to be precisely that
beater, each bar Omega, which is the energy of the
photon or a mega divided by temperature, and then
that substitution gives ADX.
Rather should. Express it as the almighty negative
is equal to. Temperature over age four times to X,
so from the. Three powers of Omega in the
numerator and the Omega that is also hanging out
there and see, we're going to pick up four powers
of this factor. T over h bar so that.
Comes along with that constant factor to your
average bar to the fourth.
And. When Omega zero zero and Sable's infinity, we
have precisely executed over E to the X minus one
to X, which is part of the four over 15. So
putting things together, there is a team of the
fourth on top. For factors of high cancel out two
of those in the denominator, so PI squared is left
in the numerator of 15 in the denominator and.
That factor of bar divided by each part of the
force leaves each bar cubed in the denominator and
cubed in that is. As promised, proportional to
this power of tea and to the fourth.
And.
Given that result, it may well be a. Fun exercise
to compute the heat capacity. For this, folks, I
guess maybe I won't.
I won't stop for too long asking that question and
calling that the heat capacity is related to this
energy density, but I'll leave that just up in the
background on people everywhere. It's something to
think about while we look at the similar
calculation for the number of density.
We're now we have. A similar looking integral over
these frequencies that corresponds to a slightly
different combination of. The other functions in
remote Zeta functions and maybe before writing
down this integral, I should.
Swap back and forth and highlight the similarity
between the energy density and the number of
density where we can see if we look closely and
maybe doing that asynchronously in offline would
be the better way to go than trying to fit them
both onto the same screen here. But the integrals
here only differ by the energy density inserting.
A factor of the energy, each bar Omega. Into the
integrated here, so instead of just counting the
number of photons. You're picking up or
integrating over the energy that is carried by
each of those photons. So instead of a. make a
square deal bigger, the integral for the energy is
each four times will make a huge mega.
So we use that trick again with FERME on Gas's
next week, and so it's worth commenting on here,
but doing that same substitution. Of ex. Age for
Omega, you can charge ahead in see that we now
have only three powers of that T over H Bar two
from the Omega squared the numerator and a third
from Jamaica and then the integral. From zero to
infinity of X squared over to the X minus one, the
X, which was our two times Z A three. So plugging
things in is.
We pull it
to zero three T cubed out front.
And everything in the denominator is left over.
Each bar cube cubed in PI squared.
So with that computed, they see that. You know,
there is agreements about the.
Heat capacity for the photon gas. I'll switch
things back to the question about where we've been.
Opportunity for questions to come in for many of
you and just.
Comment that the heat capacity itself.
That constant pressure is that. Derivative in the
energy with respect to the temperature at constant
bullying, with aggressive pressure just now. So
taking the. Temperature derivative of. This t to
the power for just leaves us with our three and
all the rest of the cast of factors that come
along for the ride and.
Yeah. Come in and assume about the gap on page one
of the six is I think our next pretty much our
next stop, because we saw
Biden jumping ahead to that integration. We looked
at a bit of detail at this integration here that
appears in the expression for the total energy
density. And I mentioned earlier before that
digression that it is this. Spectral density, the
thing that is being integrated over that is
actually measured in experimental observations.
With this plot here not actually being those
experimental measurements, but being an
illustration mathematically of how this idealized
Planck spectrum for non interacting photons
behaves as a function of the temperature, which is
the inverse of data or beta is the inverse
temperature, whereas the temperature gets higher
the peak. You see, if I can get both the equation
and the plot on the screen here
in the limit of large wavelengths and the limit of
small wavelengths, the spectrum goes to zero. And
because. Spectrum here is plotted as a function of
wavelength rather than the function of frequency
that we derive starting from the grand canonical
proficient function. It's worth.
Going through the requested box here on page 106
to change variables. And get to get the energy
density expressed as an integral over the
wavelength rather than the frequency. So the. The
straightforward part of this is just substituting
in three powers of that wavelength in three powers
of the frequency turn into three powers. Of
wavelength, so omega, is that too pricey, divided
by the waves like lambda? And. Looking at the. A
derivative of Omega with respect to LAMDA, then we
pull out that power just before things here for.
Use it for being explicit, the derivative of one
over lambda is minus one over lambda squared by C
come along for the ride in a D lambda.
Is. Up in the numerator in the.
One of the ways that's a minus sign could go
astray in this calculation is when converting this
integral from. Frequency to wavelength, we also
have to convert the limits, so as W goes to zero
and the lower limits of the center grow, that
corresponds to Lambda going to infinity and
similarly, W to infinity is the high energy limit
of very low wavelengths. And then we have the
lambda up fronts, but rather. That's minus.
To or the minus comes from only the deal a factor.
This is just positive see Cube with a minus two
plus C from the Omega. And then PI squared C cubed
lambda cubes from the Omega Cube, Lambda squared
from the Omega and then E to the.
Two pi beat each bar, C over lambda, minus one.
The Alanda.
So that is all of the factors that we then. You
have to deal with.
And pulling things out front, I see four factors
of two, which is 16.
There are four factors of pi in the denominator
there and there, and also four factors in the
numerator that will cancel out.
We have.
An issue because I duplicated things and going in
the wrong here, I wrote those PI squared CS in two
different places, so. Let's go back to the blue
and fix the pies, the annoying feature of that, a
racer racing. Everything that comes around.
I put it in both places, so.
Just rewrite this.
Without commentary this time.
And it looks a bit simpler than the cumulonimbus
squared
E two by being the first C over lambda. Minus one
day lamda, so 16 and there are two powers of pi
leftover. There is one factor of C that goes along
with that factor of bar. And then everything else
is this function of lamda where I can absorb that
minus sine. By reversing the order of integration
rather than from infinity to zero, make it zero to
infinity. He has written.
The.
It should have been written earlier in the notes.
Then there is a dilemma for Lambda five and this
exponential factor. Each person related to minus
one and we can check the. Overall, negative signs
by noting that this quantity here. Is just the
Planck spectrum as a function of wavelength, what
is plotted up here, and this is obviously a
positive. So we have the correct overall sign that
is also written there.
Judging now.
In the time that we have left, what would be worth
going through, I think I'll. Talk about the cosmic
microwave background. Bits and.
Wrap up the equation of state on Monday where the.
Having gone through the change of variables.
To get things in terms of the wavelength lamda, we
can now see that.
Suspects that were plotting here has that formed.
One over. Lambed is the fifth time's not enough
space here, so zoom in and narrate this a bit
smaller if it recognizes the eraser.
One over land is the fifth and then an exponential
factor. That goes like each of the one over minus
one.
Where I'm omitting all of the factors of the
factor of beta in there, but ignore HRC in those
other Karlsson's of it in the high temperature
limit relevant for. Classical physics, this e to
the Beethoven land of minus one, we can expand in
terms of the small beta as one plus beta over
lambda, but once cancel and that one over lambda
cancels out the. What are those five factors of
Canada so classically? The spectrum that would be
predicted for.
For later, for electromagnetic radiation is one
over lambdas of the power for which is what's
shown in. This black line here diverging as a
Kordic function as the way of life gets smaller,
but thanks to quantum effects that bring in this
factor of the exponential, as Lambda gets smaller
for any non-zero or any non-zero obeida, any
finite temperature, this exponential factor
becomes exponentially large, exponentially quickly
and.
As it shows up in the denominator, it suppresses
the overall spectrum and sends it crashing back
down to zero after some peak. That depends on the
particular temperature. And this is exactly what
the physicists of one hundred years ago.
Wanted to see since the measurements that they had
been able to do of things like the sun and ovens
at that at that time and showing precisely that
decrease at small wavelengths in the ultraviolet
regime of high energies and the fact that the
classical calculation are named after a rally in
genes to. Two English physicists of the early
nineteen hundreds, one of whom was was from
Ormskirk team Sheens, was a native of Lancashire.
They found that.
Courting divergence in the classical prediction
rather than. The reduction in the ultraviolet,
which became known as the ultraviolet catastrophe
that Max Planck was able to. Cure simply by
hypothesizing the form of the spectrum that now
bears his name, which we were able to. Derive
ourselves from the quantum theory that came along
a couple of decades later.
And, you know.
With a couple of minutes left, maybe the quickest
thing to fit in to that last bit of time is to hop
back to. Some of these boxes on. Pages one, 10 and
11.
And note that.
With these calculations, we're able to get a nice
correlation between the average energy and the
average number of particles where for a non
relativistic case, we had one of our key equations
for the classical ideal gas. And the canonical
example was that the energy was.
Three halves times, indeed, for some reason, the
screen is. But half blank, we get something
similar in this case only with the factor of
roughly two point seven rather than a factor of
three, has that two point seven comes from both
the effect of photons being relativistic particles
as well as the. The role of quantum physics coming
into this realisation of their wavelengths and
actually the sample exam that's posted on the
canvas sites. Asks about these non relativistic
particles or sadistic, so the ultra relativistic
energy in the canonical ensemble where we get even
a. Third, relation between energy and no density.
That is exactly three times the number of
particles, types of temperature. So. The two
effects are. We can disentangle from these three
pieces of influence that go on from a classical,
non relativistic ideal gas to a classical
relativistic ideal, gas doubles the energy density
from three 1/2 to three and then introducing the
quantum effects that cure that ultraviolet
catastrophe. Bring the relation back down again by
almost exactly 10 percent. This is. Quite a
precise and in fact, an exact. Ratio of Gamma
function to Zeta functions in this approximation
of photon gas being completely not interacting.
Which turns out to be a good description of.
Both the sun and the cosmic microwave background
that they talk about on next Monday,
and particularly in the case of the cosmic
microwave background, this really fantastic
agreement between the not interacting, idealized
theoretical prediction and the observed
measurements which provide some of the strongest
evidence for dark matter. So with that, hints
about some of the connections of this module to
broader physics. I'll stop there, check one last
time for any final questions and. If there aren't
any. See you all again next week.