OK, the recording should now be underway, starting
off, as usual, with just an opportunity for those
of you who are able to make it synchronously.
Still to bring up any questions you may have about
the materials for this week or any of the previous
weeks, and that is up and running on the. Usual
pull everywhere, link in the chat window.
Now, gotten through all of the interim assessment
for this course, I need to catch up with marching
off the computer projects and the homework
schedule on Tuesday, there is still time for
submissions or re submissions of those Tuesday
homeworks and then the.
Last landmark remaining for the term is the final
assessment scheduled for Tuesday, the 25th of May.
There are some sample exams and other practice
problems already on the campus sites and some
solutions to those are there as well. And more
will be coming as
time gets freed up from writing the. The written
materials for this. Module, as well as the
internal assessments
in the.
Other main logistical note for today is that
Monday is a holiday in the U.K., which means that
we will not have a secret session. Then we'll meet
again this time next Thursday. And at that time
when we meet, we will be talking about something
significantly different than what we've been doing
through the module so far. So today, if I don't
see any questions coming in on Ziu or everywhere,
so if I hop over to the materials for this week.
And.
As you look at these, you may have seen that these
are the the shortest set of notes and also the set
with the fewest exercises built in four for you to
work through. And the style of an asynchronous
tutorial, and that is largely because this is.
Really wrapping up all that we've been doing
through the module so far, looking at idealizes
systems whose constituents do not interact with
each other, so many of the calculations being done
here, in particular compared to the calculations
done last week for voting yes, guesses of photons
and bosons more generally. See, there are a great
many similarities, especially in the the
relativistic case considered right at the very end,
where really the only change with respect to the
photon gas is the relative negative side in the
integrals for the energy density and particle
density and particle density, which leads to a
slightly different. Numerical factor in the
equation of state that has the usual form. Same as
the ideal gas law, PV is proportional to a.. With
that concept of proportionality, something that.
You can work out by looking up those integrals or
plugging them into a program like. Mathematica or
over on that label, those are not very friendly
integrals to try to do yourself. They do have some
very nice numerical values in terms of Remon Zeta
function, similar to what we saw for photons last
week. So I'll leave that. Just generic. Hole up,
there is another place for you to toss in any
questions that come up again, not only about this
leak, but anything in the module so far. And in
the absence of questions, we'll just go through
the material for this week, trying not to repeat
the content, but build on it in some ways, also
doing a bit of review and consolidation for ideal
Agassiz of fermions in taking the quantum approach
where the partition function, in this case, the
grand canonical partition function. As a function
of temperature and chemical potential is defined
by.
Something over all of the energy levels, which
when we carry through that computation, we found
factories into simply a product over all of those
energy levels, thanks to the non interacting
nature of the particles in this gas. Exactly what
we're going to lose as we move on into the next
topic of molecule, looking at systems of particles
that do interact with each other and no longer
factories in this elegant way.
And what we need to do in order to carry out
concrete calculations with this great economical
production function and its corresponding grant
economical potential related to the Lord of that
partitioned function is specify the energy levels
for the systems of interest where. Whereas last
week we looked at so-called ultra relativistic
gases of photons where four photons that are
massless particles and their energy then does not
depend on the mass of the particles, but only on
its momentum or equivalently its frequency
interpreted as an electromagnetic wave. Here,
we'll start off by looking at. Not a relativistic
fermions, though, going back to exactly the same
form of the energy that we've considered in week
four through a classical canonical approach. Where
the energy is, the momentum squared over twice,
the particle last.
And those moments are quantized by defining the
system in a finite volume. V, which is a cubic
volume factor of L on each side of the cube, and
that takes this energy into an expression that
depends on three integers corresponding to
so-called quantum numbers in each of the three
dimensions of the volume with as for the photon
gas and quantum gases of bosons, the.
Sort of trivial case where all three of or or any
of those moments are zero is forbidden by. Quantum
mechanics, in particular, the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle that we discussed in
previous synchronous session. We also have to take
note of the DeGeneres's for each of these energies,
so how many? Energy levels, there are for any
given value of the energy set by these three.
Integers in this vector K like a Z, and for
typical fermions such as electrons, there are. To
energy levels for each year of the energy, and
this is the same numerical factor that we saw for
photons last week, the origin is slightly
different for photons. We had two polarizations
states, two ways in which the the photons could
oscillate, understood as waves with a wavelength
of frequency and for electrons. What we have is
something known as spin or intrinsic spin, which
is a quantum property of. All while, all particles,
all quantum systems where the particle in question
behaves as though it were spinning about an axis,
even though and this is where things get confusing
and we will go into the full physics
interpretation in this mathematics module,
particles are not actually spinning. They simply
carry a quantized unit of angular momentum as
though as if they were spinning.
And I'm refraining from showing you any of the
sort of illustrations of particle spin that you
can find, say, through a Google image search,
because those all of those I was able to find
showed particles spinning, rotating about an axis,
which is not actually the case. This is an
intrinsic property of a particle, intrinsic
angular momentum rather than something resulting
from the particle doing something or behaving in a
certain way.
But the electrons are typical examples of fermions
where there are two possible spin states, so spin
up and spin down, and mathematically this
corresponds to electrons being so-called spin half
particles where that half is a measure of how much
angular momentum each electron has as an intrinsic
property of its quantum nature. And the the
theorem that was mentioned in passing in the
materials aspect for weeks seven. Known as the
Spin Statistics Theorem. Which is linked at the
start of Section seven point two to that Wikipedia
article.
Is one of the the deep results in quantum physics
from the 20th century. Which established that well
was the place in this set of notes established
that in three spatial dimensions there are only
two possibilities for the behavior of particles,
the bosons and fermions that we've been
considering where. Those boats are they confirm
your statistics are related to the spin of the
particle and the spin statistics theorem where all
the bosons have integer.
Values of spin in this particular basis that
depends on success at each bar and fermions have
half integer values of of the spin and the total
amount of degeneracy. That there is for.
Each of these. Different spins, if so free.
Find that spin to be a quantity called s, the
total degeneracy is two times as. Plus one, so
it's been zero particle with zero has only one
state per energy level, the Higgs boson is a
famous example of that. Since being a half
electrons a few times a half is one plus one or
two of these states. So in going up to speed,
three have speed at four and spend five hands.
Gives us six.
And so, again, a double degeneracy, so even the
three factors in some of the expressions here we
have when we go through the same change are
variables. To convert the grand canonical
potential into a control over these.
The three momentum vectors or the movement of
three vector of the particles in this from Yungas,
even the pre factor comes out the same as the was
on a case last week, just by coincidence, with
that factor of two four spin states versus factor
of two for polarization states. And in the same
spirit as. What we set up for the folks on
integrating were expressing things like the
particle, no density in the energy density as
integrals over the photon frequency, which was
just related to its energy. Will do that same sort
of thing only in this non relativistic case where
we have. These. Momenta key squared related to
that. P squared, divided by twice the critical
mass, you'll integrate a set of over frequency and
over the energies themselves. Which brings in some
factors of a square root when we essentially
inverted the energy moments in relation to express
the momentum as a function of the energy and then
with. The grand canonical potential expressed in
this way, an integral of a particular function
over energies we can.
Investigate that function as to the fundamental
underlying mathematical aspects of the ferry gas
in much the same way that the Planck distribution
was the fundamental underlying quantity for the
photon gas. One thing we'll do differently is keep
the second separate factors separate from the
so-called FERME function.
Which is just a convention that allows. US to
recognize the the ferry function as essentially
the the same thing we saw. A couple of weeks ago
when looking at average occupation numbers where.
The average occupation number that we computed
back in the big seven for fermions. As opposed to
boatswain's. And precisely the form we are looking
at here, the difference being that instead of now
fixing a value of the energy corresponding to the
particular energy level whose occupation number we
were considering back then, we're now looking at
this expression as a function of the energy. And
in particular, integrating over those energies and
expressions for things like the particle, no
density.
As functions of the inverse temperature data and
chemical potential, mbewe, so. For particular
values of temperature and chemical potential, we
want to see how this very function evolves as we
go from one energy level to the next, simplifying
the calculations by making the usual approximation
of the energy levels are sufficiently closely
space that we can integrate over them rather than
having to deal with Plunky Sum's. And we will also
be focusing on the low temperature regime, where,
despite having the same relation between energy
and implementor as the classical ideal gas that we
looked at. I can read the canonical ensemble, the
quantum effects of.
Of these FIRREA, of these quantum fermions will be
most readily apparent at low energies, and in
particular even in the limit where the energy goes
to zero, we will. Simplify things in much the same
way that we simplified the photographs last week
by recognizing that it was best described by a
chemical potential of zero. So here the chemical
potential remains in the calculations.
And it is in particular a positive number, as we
will see shortly, what we're going to be focusing
on is the low temperature limits of teh.
Approaching zero and the behavior of this family
function that appears in the integration of all of
the expressions we're going to be computing for
things like particle no density and energy density
to determine the low temperature equation of state
and.
What's going on in this plot is we are plotting
things on the horizontal axis against a
dimensionless combination of the energy level and
chemical potential. For several different values
of the dimensionless ratio of the temperature to
that chemical potential.
And as.
That ratio of the temperature relative to the
chemical potential decrease is going to lower
temperatures. We can see that.
The ferry function gets closer and closer to a
step function that is that is one for all values
of the energy less than the chemical potential and.
Zero for all values of the energy greater than the
chemical potential. At higher energies, the
evolution from between those two limits, which we
saw as the extremes that fermions could possibly
exhibit, when there can be at most one fermions
her energy level.
At high temperatures, there is on average very few
and approaching zero particles and his energy
level. There are many more energy levels. There
are particles and low density risk for low
energies. It's the opposite situation. There are
relatively large number of particles that are
steadily filling all of the available low energy
or all of the available energy levels with low
energies. So there's qualitatively different
behavior as the temperature decreases, depending
on.
Whether the energy is larger then or smaller than.
The chemical potential. When it's larger, the
family function decreases as the temperature
decreases, going to zero on that side of the step
function and conversely for lower energies. Lower
temperatures produce a larger and increasing value
of the family function approaching that.
The maximum value of one.
And.
The points where the energy equals the chemical
potential is the special point where the primary
function is always a half and it's the point where.
The step function that we can use as an
approximation to the family function transitions
from zero to one, which, as I started to say
earlier, is a change from all the energy levels
being occupied by the single Fermoy on that. That
they allow at low energies to all of those energy
levels being unoccupied at higher energies
and.
Now, this approximation of the step function is
exact in the zero temperature limit, what we're
used to thinking about as absolute zero where?
Previously, we've seen the all energy in motion of
systems coming to a halt at absolute zero. We'll
see that the public exclusion principle that.
Forbids multiple electrons from multiple fermions
from occupying the same energy level will lead to
different behavior.
In the zero temperature limit for these quantum
gases of fermions before we get there.
There are some quick calculations to do which. Of.
Echo, what was.
Done in previous weeks, especially for the folks
on gas computing, the.
Particle, no density where if we plug in the step
function for the family function, what we have is
a one for all energies from zero up to HMU. So all
that's left is the square root of E e and then
that very function is just zero for all higher
energies. So that is the total expression,
constant factor coming along out front. And then
the integral of it is the power, one half is the
power three hands and evaluated that new. And then
zero and divided by that power, so rearranging
things just gives three factors of two. Three
factors and three factors of. You.
Well, with that square root, so to add new to the
three has power and then a three pi square each
bar cube where? The two notable aspects of this
result are. The dependence on Muta, the three
haves, and the independence on the temperature. So
this is both of these we can
justify or anticipate based on sort of simple
arguments going back to even the setup of the
problem, expressing everything as an integral.
Over the energies where those energies are.
Related to the squares of the momenta.
So integrating over the entities is equivalent to
integrating over some portion of the sphere in the
space of these three Momenta K, K, Y and Z. And
the radius of that sphere in this approximation
where the sphere is cut off at this particular
value, where the energy equals the chemical
potential new, we have a hard sphere with a radius
of you sorry, the radius is the square root of you
since we're integrating over energies. And then
the volume coming from that integral is three
factors of that square root of the radius of
square root of MU as the radius.
And the independence of tea is even simpler to
appreciate, just as I said, this very function
becomes exactly the step function in the limit of
absolute zero temperature. And that is essentially
what we are considering here, the. The zero
temperature limit of a Fairbury gas, which can be.
Explicitly corrected by. What's called a
Somerfield expansion, which brings in
systematically higher powers of the temperature
tea in the kind of systematic. Expansion in a
small parameter that you got some practice with on
the homework assignment and to elaborate a little
bit on. What was included in the official
materials for this week is to. Spice up the
synchronous session by supplementing some of the.
Notified asynchronous materials.
If we yeah, a couple of things to say about the
Somerfield expansion, first of all, the integrals
that pop up as we go to higher powers of the
temperature in that expansion are very tricky ones,
which is the main reason we're not trying to to go
through that whole. Calculation in the official
asynchronous materials, it would be really as much
material as we've had on quantum gases of both
those sounds and fermions all over again. One
thing we can do
a bit quickly, just by. The sort of physicist's
style argument based on. How this ferry function
approaches its. The step function limit in the. In
the limit of zero temperatures, we can do a
qualitative argument that can provide at least the
functional form of the the first. Correction in
the summer field expansion to. These quantities,
like the particle, no density and energy density
and therefore the heat capacity.
Where?
We can recognize that if we start in the zero
temperature limit, that is exactly a step function.
We can use that black line as a decent
approximation to that, then when the temperature
is turned on just a little bit and we have a small
value of the temperature, we still have all of the
states or all of the energy levels below this
chemical potential new being filled. But the
temperature is providing some extra energy to the
particles that can increase their probability to
occupy a an energy level with a higher energy. We
looked at that in some detail in the canonical
example in week three. Now, seeing that excited
states are exponentially suppressed in the
temperature and in the energy gap, and in this
context, the first excited states that can be
filled and are not filled already are those. Down
here, just where the energy is just above that
chemical potential, the ratio of Ammu is just
larger than. They one. And the the particles that
are most likely to be able to.
Take advantage of the extra energy from the
non-zero temperature to make the leap from a field
energy level at lower temperature up into that
unoccupied, that open energy level and a higher
energy are those that are already at the energy
levels, just below the chemical potentials of
values of the ovum. You just smaller than one. And
the. So the story that you can take away in the
physicist's, qualitative or conceptual argument is
that the.
The distance in energy that these particles are
going to be.
These particles, energy is going to be increasing
as they move from the filled energy levels just
below UV equals one to the unoccupied energy
levels just above UV equals one, that extra energy
is going to be proportional to the temperature. So
the higher the temperature gets, the greater the
probability is for.
Energy levels to be occupied at higher energies
above this cutoff and at the same time, the number
of fermions that are going to be in a position to
move to higher energies and occupy those higher
energy for those energy levels with higher
energies are precisely the relatively few that are
hanging out just below the cutoff of the step
function.
In this region of colored in here, which also is a
number of particles that is going to grow
proportional to any growth in the temperature, so
as the temperature increases from zero, we have
two factors of the temperature showing up in.
In the energy that the system is going to have one
coming from the. Change in the energy levels with.
Or the accessible energy levels with a non
negligible probability of being occupied in the
second from the number of particles that are
available to occupy those energy levels. So if we
go back to where we were. Which was computing the.
Average energy density
following on almost the same calculation as the
the number of density, all that has changed is.
Adding a factor of the energy to the integration,
so integrating the energy over this probability
distribution.
We can skip rewriting the integral with its cut
off from zero to Mew for putting in the step
function. And jump straight to what is.
A very similar result is just. Five have a of new
and divided by that power. Which can rearrange as
that same. Factor of two and the three has now
divided by five. I swear it started with one hour
of HMU left over. And because these are the same
factors and they're high in each bar, we can just.
Replace them with the particle no density computed
above. And. Converting the one third in the
particle, no density to the one 5th that shows up
in the energy density.
So this is the zero temperature leading result of
this summer felt expansion for the energy density
and if you were able to grind through. The
calculation there to close.
Which is done in. Schroeder's textbook, at least,
and possibly David Tauxe lecture notes some of the
references at the start of the materials for this
course, we do indeed find that the next connection
or next correction to. The.
Energy density from Somerfield expansion is
proportional to T squared, as promised and is a
factor of new. Coming in the denominator to get
the units to work out correctly and then. We're
we're to the fourth is the next correction in that
series.
So.
I'm looking at the time and realizing that, as
usual, the supplemental discussion about Zemmour
failed expansion and the complications that arise
took took longer than. I expected also just
quickly mention that some of this results here.
If the screen behaves itself and underlines, it is.
Where we can determine the huge capacity of the
firm Yungas. That low energy of.
Derivative of the energy with respect to
temperature at fixed volume. So the first term
that we had here. Would have just predicted a a
completely vanishing heat capacity, which we saw
earlier in the course of this evening, the
homework is the very unusual situation that we
generally only have in the limit of zero
temperature or infinite temperature. And it is the.
Correction coming from the term in the Somerfield
expansion. That gives.
The. True heat capacity of the low temperature
firmly on gas is taking a derivative. Of T squared,
bringing down a factor of two.
And actually, there's no V there, because he
capacity is the derivative of the energy rather
than the energy density, and the energy itself is
one of those extensive quantities that scales with
the total volume.
And the pressure is at this point, just as easy to
compute as the heat capacity, again in this zero
temperature limit where the entropy. Is is zero
and brings in that same sort of there is a zero
field expansion for the entropy at non-zero
temperatures. So this equation of state that we
have here. Expressed in sort of three different
ways. That the pressure is. Related to the
chemical potential times, the number of destiny or
currently the energy density, or if we. Substitute
in this chemical potential, we end up with the
five thirds power of the particle, no density
and divided by the volume. This is really the zero
temperature result, which, in contrast to both the
boson, the quantum boson gas equation of state and
the classical equation of state, the ideal gas law,
the equals a.. This pressure does not vanish at.
Had zero temperature.
And. I think I. Glossed over one thing up here,
which is the the definition of the family energy,
just as this zero temperature chemical potential
of.
This is that relation between the zero temperature,
chemical potential and particle no density that
goes into the pressure to give that functional
dependence the power of the five thirds power.
Where if we invert this equation and again,
consider. Corrections coming. To it from. The.
There's no field expansion we have. The feminine
energy, just as the zero temperature limit of the
chemical potential where those higher. Order
corrections in the temperature vanish.
And this is a plot of.
The.
The pressure of the family gas compared to the
temperature, which we can contrast to the ideal
gas law for classical particles, which is just PV,
equals A..
Where he is in a river times tea, which is the
density road we define, so that corresponds to
just a straight line with slope ro. That the
Fermoy gas approaches at high temperatures we have
seen. But the non-zero value in the the
temperature limits and even at low temperatures
before the classical physics becomes a good
approximation.
Is really a remarkable mathematical prediction
that is borne out again in real physical systems
in the universe, including.
Some of the. Densest stars in the universe, which
which are the setting for a particular type of
supernova known as Type 1A for. Obscure historical
reasons. And what goes on in this setting is that
these stars, either neutron stars or white dwarf
stars, tend to be.
Quite old. They've been around since the early
days of the universe billions of years ago, and
they are.
Because they are so old, they have actually burned
through nuclear fusion, all of the light elements,
all of the fuel that is generating heat and lights
in the stars that we can see in the sky, including
our own sun. The the white dwarfs no longer have
that nuclear fusion process, giving them lots of
heat, lots of energy and lots of the corresponding
radiation pressure that we derived last week. The
only thing keeping them from collapsing into a
black hole under the weight of all the matter they
contain.
Which is roughly as much mass as our son. In
something like 100000 or 100000 times smaller
volume than the sun.
What that. The only thing a. Stabilizing the white
at that volume, roughly the volume of the Earth,
one hundred thousand times smaller than the sun is
precisely the degeneracy pressure of there of the
electrons in this white dwarf star understood as
an approximately zero temperature Fairbury gas,
even though the temperature of 10 million Kelvin
is not zero by every day standards, but still very
small compared to the chemical potential, the
Fermi energy that is so large due to the very
large particle density. So something like.
Failure of row. In round numbers is ten to the
power. Thirty six particles per cubic meter, which.
We can compare to sort of everyday substances like
metals that have densities of around 10 of the
eight particles per cubic meter, which is
corresponds to. That free energy of about 24
Kelvin, just to the plugging in the massive
electron and converting units appropriately to get
Kelvin.
And the connection to the supernovas comes when
these white dwarf stars being supported by their
Fermi degeneracy pressure are in a binary system
as pictured in this illustration from the European
Space Agency and the white dwarf star.
Is able to pull in or severely accretes matter and
energy from its companion star that is still
burning, still undergoing nuclear fusion and
emitting a steady stream. Of of matter that it's
caught in the gravitational attraction of the
white dwarf star, so there's a steady accumulation
of mass in the way to Earth being balanced by its
approximately zero temperature.
Fermi pressure. And as more and more mass piles up,
there's more and more gravitational attraction.
Within the white Forestar itself, leading to
higher and higher densities. And eventually
reaching through a complicated calculation, a
limiting value where the density is large enough
for new types of fusion to start occurring
involving heavier elements, carbon and oxygen,
rather than hydrogen and helium. Which take off in
a runaway chain reaction and in the space of just
a few seconds, basically fuse all of the carbon
atoms in the star. So about as much matter as our
own sun. An amount of energy released from those
fusion reactions, that's about five billion times
brighter than what our sun is putting out.
And we looked a bit at the relativistic ideal from
your guess at the start today. So I'll just
mention.
Just to wrap up, because we are at at the time,
the end of time. The connection to a relatively
recent Nobel Prize for 10 years ago, what did rely
on this process and on the the fair refresher in
these systems of Whitemoor of stars producing Type
1A supernovas? And that is because of this steady
accumulation of mass that the Fermi pressure
allows to occur, which means that these Type 1A
supernovas are all very irregular, no matter what
the white dwarfs are started out with in its its
past life before it finished burning all of its
fuel. What what amount of mass and what chemical
composition it had.
It will only reach the chandrasekar limit and
undergo this type of a supernova when it has
accumulated precisely enough matter from its
companion star to reach that limit. So the Type 1A
supernova is very regular, both in its brightness,
how much energy it puts out and also its
temperature, the temperature that goes into the
Planck distribution of the light from that
explosion that we can observe. And from the that
distribution is possible to infer both how far
away the supernova was and also from the shift in
the Planck distribution, how quickly the white
dwarf star was moving away from us at the time of
its supernova. So because the universe is
expanding, all galaxies are moving away from each
other in the speed at which they move away from
each other is governed by the speed of the
universe's expansion. So by carefully
investigating Type 1A supernovas, where we could
tell both how quickly the galaxy containing the
supernova was moving away from us and also how far
away it was based on the brightness of the
supernova. We were able to establish that the
universe is actually expanding more and more
rapidly as time goes on, which is a phenomenal
they got named a dark energy. Which is. The
question will name, because it's not really dark
and it's not really energy, it's a universe
expanding faster and faster over time for as yet
completely unknown reasons. So sorry to to run
over time to tell that story and that connection
to a recent physics breakthrough. I realized as I
want to take any questions and be back in. Five or
so minutes for the office hours. That's it for me
for today.
Thank you.