OK, recording should be under way for the first
few minutes, at least, we will hopefully see some
more folks trickling in, but. In the meantime, can
get set up with the usual opening bid, checking to
see if there are. Any questions from you about
anything that has come up in the module so far
and. Leave. This question, this poll up and
running for a few minutes while. More people come
on in and in the meantime, I can give a few
comments on. Logistical matters now that we have
the end of the term in sight, so the computer
project, obviously, you all know, was due about 36
hours ago, and I suspect that some of you all were
focused on that to the extent that you're too
tired to have to come in for the synchronous
session today. But keeping things moving, the the
very final piece of continuous assessment, the
last homework assignment is up and available. And
it has three questions. One corresponding to a
week for an ideal gas's, looking at what happens
when two ideal devices are mixed in a in the same
container. The question on the week five material
with thermodynamic cycles going through
calculations for that and then question on the
green canonical ensemble for week six. And as I
suspect you all know well, it's worthwhile to just
take a quick read through those problems right
away, have them percolating in the back of your
mind. Over the next few days, even before you get
around to having the time and inclination to
really work on that final assignment, its due end
of Tuesday, the 27th, that'll be the end of
continuous assessment for this module insight and.
You can see in the meantime or next week, rather,
if questions about it come up, they can go onto
canvas sites or
be brought up at synchronous sessions over the
next 10 days. Also, I have taken care of the issue
that came up Monday that the last year's exam was
not in the repository, just turned out to be due
to an oversight following from the strange
situation last year that should now be corrected.
And both that exam and a sample exam are also
uploaded to the candidate site with more sample
problems to come now that the assessed assignments
are running their course.
And I.
Did I realize on Monday that for some reason there
was a question that came in through people
everywhere, that whatever reason did not appear on
my screen until after the end of the synchronous
session? Just a quick clarification about that
computer project that was cleared up in the
subsequent office hours on trying to make sure
that this was something similar does not happen
this time around, making sure that there are
opportunities or any questions that come in
through all everywhere. I see. Before moving on.
And if I do move on too quickly, as always, feel
free to wonder yourself and speak up, grab my
attention or puts a comment in the chat window
just to make sure that I don't overlook anything
accidentally before moving on.
But having. Taken some due diligence to try to
avoid that issue this time around, we can
dive back into to where we were or where we got to
on Monday after reviewing the skeleton of the
molecule that that we saw up to the break, the
three different kinds of ensembles we were looking
at quantum statistics and the. Distinction between
quantum statistics and classical statistics in
reviewing the concept of quantized energy levels,
which we saw all the way back in Chapter four per
week for material on the classical ideal gas, we
had to propose that energy levels were quantized
in order to have a well-defined, partitioned
function, something over a countable, if infinite
number of microstates.
And. That is a necessary but not sufficient
ingredient to really define quantum statistics in
contrast to the classical statistics. The key
distinction is shown on the screen here, the
shaded box in the asynchronous materials for this
week, which is providing or making a conceptual
point that may be subtle and may be worth
illustrating with some examples and exercises.
Where in the classical approach. We consider. Each
individual particle in our system, which may be
fixed in the canonical ensemble and may be
fluctuating from microstates to microstates in the
grand canonical ensemble, but for each of those
particles in the total number, we sum over all of
the possible energies that we can have and then
correct for any overcounting in the case of
indistinguishable particles, that is relevant for
quantum mechanics. And again, you don't need to
know anything about quantum mechanics as a
scientific discipline. This is all just
conjectures or assumptions that we are making to
provide interesting systems to study that we can
connect to real world phenomena. And that approach
turns out to breakdown if there are. Or if there
is a non-negative a non negligible probability
that multiple particles may be occupying the same
energy level and in that case, which defines the
quantum regime, we have to take a different
approach looking at quantum statistics where
instead of sending over the particles and then
their energies, we sum over the possible energy
levels and all of the possible occupation numbers
that each of those energy levels could have. So
just to what I have planned for some activities
today is checking in quickly with a couple of the
big gaps in the notes just to make sure we're all
on the same page with those and then do something
a bit more interesting, extending that example or
that illustration just to make sure that the
procedure we followed in these notes is clear to
everyone. So let's move on to the first of those
quick check ins, which is touching on the Gap on
page ninety four, where we look at a extremely
simple example where this contrast between
classical and quantum statistics is.
Easy to see is is obvious, possibly too simplified,
it becomes maybe a bit too obvious to have its
full importance clear. But the idea is
we consider a canonical system with just two
particles, each of which can occupy any of five
energy levels. And we want to sum over all of the
microstates in this system where in the in the
classical approach that defines the two particle
canonical partition function for the case where
the particles are distinguishable with some over
both of those particles and just add up all of the
possible energy levels that they could be in. And
that gives a prediction here for the number of
microstates which we have gone through some
manipulations to make equal to the total canonical
partition function in this case,
which is. What's running in the poll here, two
particles filling. In year five, energy levels
define some level, some number of microstates that
have to be sold over to determine the partition
function.
And given the small crowd today, I won't wait too
long for responses if they don't come. In a minute
or two, they may not be coming at all, but
hopefully we'll be able to check in and confirm
that at least the material material and the
written notes that you've had to look at this week
is sufficiently straightforward to answer this
question. And if it is not? You feel free to to
say so, and we can. Go through it in L.A. rather
than on page.
So I'll make a last call for any further responses
in. Go on to see. We have in. The. Results here
where?
There's unanimous agreement that. There are five
possible energy levels for each of two particles
gives five squared or 25 microstates where going
back to the notes then.
We see that in the indistinguishable case,
appropriate for. Quantum particles, this classical
approach tells us that.
We should expect to count, you know.
That distinguishable canonical partition function,
twenty five over two is twelve point five
microstates, which is nonsense because the micro
the micro states that we are sitting over are by
definition, integers. So that is the simplest
possible example of what goes wrong with. The
classical approach to.
Two statistics, when there is a nonsexual
probability of having multiple particles in the
same energy level and if we explicitly go through
and count all of these twenty five.
Possible microstates that show up in that
distinguished distinguishable
particle, a canonical partition function. We see
that. Only those states where. All of the
particles are in different energy levels are
double counted, so once we. Switch from
distinguishable to indistinguishable particles.
This red and blue are both the same simple factor
of one count of the number of particles, and these
two states, those two microstates are identical
and overcounted in this approach. But this one
with both particles in a particular energy level
is not overcounted and should not be divided by
two, so it's only those 20.
That are divided by two in the indiscernible case
and the five where.
There are multiple particles in the same energy
level, do not pick up that overcounting factor, so.
In principle.
You can adapt classical statistics to try to keep
track of all of these different possible
overcounting factors, depending on.
Nice, just a note about your network.
Well, when we move on to the next project, I will,
yeah, read out the options and you can put them in
the chat window. We'll do what we can with the
network available to us.
As I was saying, well, it's possible to. Try to
keep track of all of the different possible
overcounting factors that could arise from
different multiplicities of particles in the same
energy states, really the quantum approach
mentioned earlier of counting occupation numbers.
Like these in each energy level, so each of the
numbers in these five, two lives is one of those
five energy levels. There are a maximum of two
particles total and just counting over all the
possible ways these particles can be distributed
into the energy levels. That's just counting.
Indistinguishable balls being placed in boxes and
immediately gives us these these 15.
The one other quick check in to do before diving
into something perhaps more interesting and
certainly more substantial. Is considering the two
possibilities for. The occupation numbers that
particles can have in quantum physics due to a.
Particular feature of quantum mechanics that we
won't go into in detail unless there is a request
for it. I guess this is your synchronous session,
so you should feel free to guide or directed to
your interests if those interests lie in the
direction of quantum mechanics. In nature, there
are all particles fall into these two distinct
classes called bosons and fermions are named after
a pair of 20th century physicists, those and
Fairmead that differ by the possible occupation
numbers that they can have in a given energy level.
In the case of those answers, maybe the familiar
one, because you can have any non-negative number
of particles in your energy level, just as we
would expect from every day. You can put as many
balls into a box as is fit in there. For me, the
Fermín case or the case of Ferme Dirac's
assistants is maybe less familiar. And for those
particles, it is possible to have at most a single
particle in each energy level, so the possible
occupation numbers are only zero and one as
opposed to all non-negative integers or bosons.
And this leads to. Different counting of those
occupation numbers and hence. Going over the some
over microstates in the quantum approach to
partition functions, we end up with different
statistics. Where the quick the second quick check
in today here is filling in this box on page
ninety six.
Counting that out of those micro states for the
two particle, five local example we were looking
at a few minutes ago, how many of them? Are valid
for fermions as opposed to the bosun's or or the
classical particles that.
Do not. Feel the effect of quantum mechanics. And.
If the options are still loading that equation,
you can just number them at A equals five
microstates, B is 10 microstates C is 15 and B is
twenty five. In that response can just come in the
chat window either directly to me or publicly to
to everyone.
And in the spirit of a quick check in, this is the
last call for your responses, and there's that
link again, in case those of you who joined since
it was last posted in the chat window.
I just see that.
Going back and opening up the.
Appropriate response. There is again. Unanimity
that looks like no problems with.
Those two quick check ins going back up to the
comprehensive list that we had here,
these are the 15 microstates for boatswain's and.
We're fermions we cannot have.
The the five with that definitely occupy the
energy level, only the 10. Remain with singly
occupy energy levels. In the case of fermions.
So.
Still a little. Bit longer. Calculation, just to
make sure that.
Make sure that this example was not. Too trivial
to to reveal the mathematics that's going on and
that things can be.
Reid arrived in. New cases. So do that same sort
of exercise, but instead of. Two particles with
access to. Five energy levels.
It's everywhere responds to.
There it is, things are updated, so a bit longer
calculation they'll give you we'll check in after
five minutes to work on this on your own. You'll
go through a bit of setup just now. We'll crank up
the number of energy levels and crank up the
number of particles. So. Consider three particles
and seven energy levels to a generalization of the
calculation. You've had a week to look at and the
question is how many microstates are there for
fermions and for bosun's in this case? This is
again, a small enough system. That's the classical
accounting is is clearly wrong, sending over each
of those three particles, looking at the seven
states that could be in and multiplying all of
those together to get a seven cubed and then
dividing by that three factorial overcounting
factor again gives a non integer number of
microstates. In the correct quantum approach of
sending over energy levels and occupation numbers
is required in order to. Correctly count the
microstates being some day over to determine the
partition function. And from there, all of the
properties of the system.
And that will also differ. For the case of those
vs. fermions, due to the difference, possible
occupation numbers that they can have.
So I'll give you several minutes to. Work through
that calculation and keep an eye on responses as
they come in and feel free to.
Ask any questions. Out loud in writing, as you
prefer, if you get stuck or don't know where to to
start with this. Calculation.
And I see responses coming in. So. Me. Ask if
anyone is still working and wants more time.
If I don't.
S..
The hand over here response and will start to.
Transition to.
Taking a look at what we have.
And. And there's not quite unanimity, so perhaps
it's worth.
Is reviewing.
Reviewing quickly how the calculation would
proceed for First-Floor Fermions and then for
boatswain's, and here is a bit of like space in
the margin where I can try to draw.
Seven boxes.
And we can think about.
The way is that three particles can be placed in
here first in the case of fermions, where you can
have at most a single particle in each box, so
there are seven options to choose from for that
location of that first particle, vector seven. But
now no more fermions can go in. That, first of all,
there are only six possibilities for the location
of the second Permian and similarly five for the
location of the third, and since each of these.
Particle's is in a different energy level. We
still do have that full overcounting factor of
three. Factorial, which equals six, and we end up
with seven times five, is thirty five.
Whereas for. The case of bosoms, we still have
those 35 contributions where each of the particles
is in a different energy level, but now there is.
The option of having to particle's.
In the same energy level.
Like so.
So seven places where those two particles could be
put in then.
Six possibilities for the third particle divided
by that overcounting factor of two factorial. It
seven times three is twenty one, and then finally
the. Third option is where? All three particles
are in.
That same energy level for the Bozena case. And
that is a final. Factor of seven.
So.
The fermions are fully described by the 35 to the
left for those we have to sum over. All three of
these positive contributions, twenty five plus
thirty five plus twenty eight is fifty sixty three.
It is written down here, 60 to.
Of. Just so that I don't have to do the addition
in my head, and that is the way that these sorts
of calculations have to go when we are in the
canonical ensemble where. The.
Or the number of particles is fixed and there is
then a constraint over how many total particles we
can have maximum in order to add up to the fixed
number of particles in the canonical ensemble.
This example also illustrates why. It is a bit
easier to to work in the green canonical example,
in the case of quantum statistics, which is the.
Exercise that. Or the the poll that is should now
be up and running.
Where? By going through this exercise, we can see
that just from the options, the. The combinatorics,
the mathematics of counting possible microstates
is. Significantly simplified when the number of
particles is allowed to fluctuate in the grand
canonical approach rather than being fixed in the
canonical approach. So that is motivation for.
Tackling these quantum systems over the next
couple of weeks in the grand canonical ensemble,
it will simplify the mathematics and I'll just
give you a minute or two to respond to this,
hopefully having gone through the more complicated
canonical calculation for the same system with
seven energy levels.
Keeping an eye on how quickly the responses come
in and move on once we reach a critical mass.
Looking at these.
Responses, I may have made a mistake setting
things up, see?
Indeed, I did. So let's well, let me have. You can
see the answer looking at. Me correcting the tape
and I put in here, which was a copy paste. Being
too quick with the copying and pasting that again,
we want to.
Some over now, all of these. Possible energy
levels for any number of particles zooming in on
the thermionic case. And hopefully getting the
ability to wake up and respond.
Not sure why the screen share here is getting a
bit. Slakey.
We can have microstates with no particle's. We're
up one particle in each of these boxes for the
Fermoy on a case.
So we have two options for each of seven boxes.
So in total, there should be. Those two options
for each of the seven boxes is what is that, two
four eight 16, 32, sixty four one twenty eight,
which I mistakenly entered as the the opposite
order, seven squared. I will correct that live and
apologize for the added.
Apologize for the typo and the corresponding
confusion that we've now seen the answer, where
were the.
The Bozak case, everyone did say that there are
possibly infinite number of. Of those islands that
we can have. So. I think you all are.
We are demonstrating the solid grasp of both the
quantum physics concept of something over these
energy levels, as well as the distinction between
bosons and fermions. And in the grand economic
approach that. That we are now taking for the next
few weeks these. Sums over the microstates, giving
us the grand canonical partition function take
particularly simple forms, and that is largely
thanks to the fact that we are still.
Considering these not interacting systems where
each of the particles
does not interact with any of the other particles,
and even though we are something over occupation
numbers of particle levels rather than a single
particle, energy states this. Ideal, not
attracting nature of the systems is still showing
up in the way that the calculations break apart
into.
Multiple identical factors. Essentially one for
each of these not interacting particles, so.
Going through both the. The Bose Einstein
statistics for biosolids of the family, direct
statistics for fermions, we are able to get
results that. End up in the form of this product
over many identical factors, one for each energy
level,
and that is a.
An example of behavior known as factorization,
which is also something we saw in week four
material on the classical ideal gas, where the
particle canonical partition function was just
personal to Ann Powers of the single particle
partition function. Here in the case of quantum
statistics, we have a product over energy levels
rather than a product of a single particle
petition functions. But in both cases there is
this factorization into multiple identical terms
that differ only by the relevant energy
corresponding to the energy level. And I mentioned
this because in a few weeks we are going to set
aside that assumption of non interacting. Ideal
behavior in these classes and start to see the
effects of interactions which are going to make
things much more complicated in a similar way to.
What we saw in the two parts of the computer
project where in the first part we had a simple
case where the Central Limit Theorem gave us all
of the answers right up front. But in the in the
second parts, when the central limit theorem was
not applicable. We had to do a great deal more
work and had to rely on numerical calculations to
get answers for the behavior of anomalous
diffusion. There will be a similar story for
interacting systems where they are so much more
complicated than the ideal Das's of not
interacting particles that this sort of
factorization. Will not be possible, and numerical
approaches will.
We'll be necessary in order to get exact solutions
and are very widely used in. Any realistic study
of of systems that. Systems of particles that
interact with each other. In a non negotiable way.
And just in the last few minutes for today, I
won't pull up any more troops or polls, but just
comment on the second possibly subtle conceptual
issue showing up in the the material for this week,
which is
the. The high temperature limit in which these
quantum physics should reproduce, the classical
behavior that we are familiar with from everyday
experience. Bringing in knowledge that quantum
physics governs the microscopic world on the
atomic scale. We know that somehow these quantum
effects should not be visible in the larger scales
that we can directly see every day. And by looking
back to our earlier work, we can appreciate that
it's high temperatures in these statistical
partition functions that correspond to the
classical limit of quantum statistics, and that is
behavior. Illustrated in. This figure here where
the high temperature limit is off to the right
side of this flight.
Where both the. Classical Maxwell Bowsman
statistics and the quantum Bose Einstein
statistics of Muslims attribute Iraq's statistics
of fermions or.
Agree so well that it. Took us until. The 19th
century to to really realize that. There were any
subtleties coming from quantum behavior at lower
energies, lower temperatures, really, and the
subtlety here is that. Looking at the quantity.
Plotted on the horizontal axis of this plot. It is
not immediately obvious that large temperatures
correspond to large values of this ratio energy
minus chemical potential divided by temperature.
As the temperature gets large, that naively seems
to get small. But the key subtle issue is that in
order to retain a finite number of particles,
which is what is plotted on the vertical axis of
this thought, we need to take the chemical
potential view off to negative infinity. As. The
temperature goes off to infinity to look at the
high temperature classical limit. So that this
ratio of minus you over to. Is much greater than
one, which is exactly the ratio here when those
energies are negligible and by much greater than
one, we see that already a factor of a few
suffices to reproduce classical expectations from
quantum systems.
So. Depending on requests, we may revisit that
result and the calculations leading up to it in
more detail on Monday, you may just dive straight
into more detail the considerations of quantum
gases of bosons. We'll see how we all feel in that
synchronous session about how confident we are
with the subtleties of the kind of statistics that
have been introduced this week. And of course, if
you have immediate questions now, this is your
last chance to ask them during the second session.
I'll be back in 10 minutes or so for office hours
once I shut down, zoom and extract that recording.
So that is all that I'm going to to say for today.