OK, the recording should now be under way, and
we'll see if any more folks come in in the next
few minutes. And in the meantime, you can just get
set up with some of the usual.
Logistical, organizational matters, and in
particular, giving those of you who are here the
opportunity to. But again, any questions you may
have either for yourself, for. For the future use
of those watching the recording.
In the.
Few logistical notes today are that the next and
final homework assignment is due tomorrow. Some
have already come in, though there's still time to
resubmit them if you see any changes or
improvements you'd like to make. And after that,
the only remaining piece of assessment will be the
final exam, which has been scheduled for a month
from yesterday, the Tuesday, the twenty fifth of
May. So as we wrap up with the interim assessment,
there'll be some more. Practice problems and other
simple materials uploaded in preparation. For that.
One other piece of logistics is that next Monday
is a holiday in the U.K.. So you may have seen.
From the somewhat flaky calendar on canvas that.
There is no synchronous session scheduled that day,
though, I expect still to be around for all of
this hours.
Just taking a quick look to see whether there are
any immediate questions about the homework or the
asynchronous materials for the module up till now.
I don't see any. Coming in so far so they can jump
over to those materials and just keep going
through them steadily ramping up the. Quantum gas
is a bosun's that was the material for last week
and then getting into the quantum gases of
fermions. And that we will deal with for the
remainder of this week leading up to the bank
holiday. Next Monday and where we left off with.
Last week saw our discussion last Thursday about
one of the assets of those islands was applying
the idealized calculations that we were doing for
a photon gas. The. Not an intern or a guess of not
interacting particles that obey the relativistic.
Energy momentum relation.
That the energy. The photon is just the speed of
light at times as momentum p, which is equivalent
to a Planck's constant four times the photon
frequency omega. We saw that
that simple.
Approximation, which is known as the. The black
body model and I can. Elaborate briefly on where
that name comes from. For the curious, a bit
simple, a curve of the plate distribution show
here as a function of wavelength, which is.
The inverse of the frequency, two factors of two
pi in the speed of light provides a. Pretty good
approximation to the light that is emitted by the
sun.
Which is shown to these colored bands here ready
for what we would measure at the surface of the
earth around sea level, and then yellow is coming
from measurements carried out by high altitude
observations, either climbing up mountains or
initially measured from high flying balloons. And
more recently, measured even on satellites, but.
These sorts of measurements predate the satellite
age and. Were some of the input observations that
that led Planck to develop the distribution that
now bears his name, this black line here that
matches the. Observed light from the sun to pretty
good precision, taking into account the fact that.
Interactions are not negligible in the sun, and we
can see they also interactions between photons and
these sorts of gases that exist in the sun, in the
space between the earth and the sun and also in
the earth's atmosphere. Can absorb a lot of these
photons that are easy to create and destroy,
corresponding to a vanishing chemical potential,
which leads to some of the different shape or the
different measurements you would get at high, high,
higher. Altitude or high position in the
atmosphere compared to sea level. And the black
body term, that was. In vogue at that time, it has
stayed around for that historical reason, just
comes from the idea that these objects being
considered that are radiating lights or the whole
spectrum of electromagnetic radiation from high
energy ultraviolet radiation down to low energy
infrared and thermal radiation, all of which
corresponds to photons with different frequencies
in different wavelengths. The black body is an
object that emits that sort of light or that sort
of electromagnetic radiation without having to
worry about it, reflecting any. Any radiation that
is in the environment, which there always is, if
there's like to see these bodies or a non-zero
temperature that is being carried by the
electromagnetic radiation, the ambient environment,
the idea is a black body simply absorbs all of
that external radiation and emits its own
radiation with no influence, no reflection coming
from all of that other stuff. So it's a
simplification that, like the simplification of a
non interacting gas, turns out to describe not
only the sun, but also things like ovens and light
bulbs and all other sources of electromagnetic
radiation very well. And another extreme that we
can look at, where the BlackBerry curve for the
blank distribution matches up even better with the
observed spectrum of electromagnetic radiation is
something known as the cosmic microwave background.
Which is illustrated in in this picture here,
which is a.
Famous image. Or one of the classic famous images
that is showing a picture of the entire visible
sky with all of the stars and galaxies and other.
Known sources of heat and light subtracted away
and removed from it and what is left? Is what we
would consider empty space and what is being done
in this picture is that the temperature of that
empty space? With no contributions from galaxies
and stars is being colored depending on whether
the temperature is a little higher than average or
a little lower than average. So the the colors
here are illustrations of fluctuations around the
average temperature of the entire sky, the entire
observable universe. That average temperature has
been measured very precisely to be about two point
seventy five Kelvin. And that average is attracted
away from each points in this picture. And what is
left are hotter regions colored in red or orange
or reddish colors like that area over on the right
of the figure that are just a few. Millions of a
Kelvyn higher than average, I think the actual
number is one part in. 10000. And then the blue
colored regions are similarly about a part in
10000 cooler than average. And what this? Is is a
Gafsa photon, so a.
The gas of electromagnetic radiation that is
filling. The entirety of the empty space in the
observable universe, within and between galaxies,
that dates back to the early stages of the
universe's evolution. If.
We pull up a. Illustration of. The universe's
evolution here.
From measurements of this cosmic microwave
background that we were just looking at, along
with other.
Other observable facets of cosmology and the
observable universe.
We've been able to measure and this is a.
This picture is being shown on a program that
doesn't let me scribble on it, so we'll just have
to to look at it. Without the benefit of any
drawing, so we know that the age of the universe
from the early stages of what's called the Big
Bang, when the universe was a very hot and then
state has been about thirteen point eight billion
years. In the cosmic microwave background that
pervades all of the universe is essentially.
An imprint of the universe in its early days,
about three hundred eighty thousand years after.
It was formed after that big bang, and that was
the point where the universe had expanded and
cooled enough. That. Electrons and atomic nuclei
were able to bind to form neutral atoms, which
allowed the light that we can see in the sky to
propagate freely rather than being absorbed and
created by those electrons and charged atomic
nuclei. So that was the point shown here, about
three hundred eighty thousand years after the Big
Bang where. The light that we are now observing in
the cosmic microwave background was released and
allowed to travel freely again thirteen point
eight billion years ago, the three hundred eighty
thousand years is a rounding error in that overall
age of the universe.
And that light that has been traveling for
thirteen point eight billion years is what is
being observed to indicate the temperature
fluctuations shown in.
Joining this figure, which we can get back to, and
there's in addition to the scientific value of the
cosmic microwave background, which we'll get into
in just a minute, there was a famous story about
its discovery back in in nineteen sixty five and.
This is by Arnold Penzias and Robert Wilson, two
astronomers who were trying to set up a telescope
to measure. Long wavelength on low frequency radio
waves.
As a probe of astronomy and astrophysics, and
while they were setting up this telescope and
trying to to tune it to get rid of background
noise from terrestrial sources, radio broadcasts,
the sun and other nearby stars they kept.
Noticing this persistent hissing coming at low
frequency. Electromagnetic radiation, low
frequency photons coming almost uniformly from all
directions in the sky, that. With a bit of work,
they were able to identify as precisely this, this
cosmic relic of the early stages of the universe.
So the cosmic microwave background, although it
had been predicted by some folks in the decades
before the 1960s, it was discovered accidentally
rather than by actually looking for it. And it was
only that accidental discovery which got a Nobel
Prize in the 70s that really. Helped to solidify
that big bang picture of the universe that we now
have and really lend credence to the predictions
that there would be this cosmic microwave
background. Pervading all of the empty space
between stars and galaxies.
Now.
I mentioned when looking at. This drawing here
that the average temperature being subtracted away
is about two point seventy five Kelvin, which I
every day standards, is quite low, one hundred
times lower than room temperature, roughly, and. I
also mentioned that. The the life here dates from
the very early stages of the universe when it was
just a fraction of a million years old, when the
universe itself was in a Honeyman state in
particular, so hot that
atoms had just started to to recombine. The
temperature was such that there was nearly enough
heat energy to ionized all of the atoms in the
universe, which is you can also see from this
figure was hundreds of millions of years before
the formation of dense structures like stars.
The universe was a more or less uniform plasma at
a temperature of thousands of Kelvin, which is the
scale needed in order to keep all of those atoms
ionized of the electrons separate from the protons
and other other atomic nuclei.
And.
What that tells us is that.
Now, as the universe has expanded over the past
thirteen point eight billion years, the
temperature of this cosmic microwave background,
the. The leftover lights from the big bang that's
filling all points in the universe, its
temperature has gradually cooled. By much more
than 99 percent of its initial value.
Leaving us with just that few Kelvin temperature
left over and.
While. It is sort of intuitive to think that over
time, hot objects, can they be expected to to cool
down the fact that. The cosmic microwave
background is really part of the universe, rather
than an object sitting within the universe and
able to radiate energy in the form of heat or
light really means that its change in temperature
is a bit more subtle than just an object sitting
in some space cooling down by radiating thermal
electromagnetic radiation. This cosmic microwave
background really is that radiation and the real
reason it has cooled is in fact precisely due to
the expansion of the universe over the thirteen
point eight billion years since the cosmic
microwave background was formed. What what has
happened is that. The as the universe expands, the
wavelength of this background, light in the
universe is also being expanded in the same way,
which is we talked about last week corresponds to
lower energies and the correspondingly lower
temperatures coming from those longer wavelengths
moving towards the. Infrared. And in particular.
The peak wavelength of the cosmic microwave
background these days is around the scale of
millimeters as opposed to the hundreds of
nanometres, that is the main wavelength of the
visible light from the sun that we are able to see.
Which is. As might be expected from the name The
Microwave. Region of the electromagnetic radiation,
longer wavelengths moving into the infrared and
thermal frequencies and wavelength of a few
millimeters, which I believe is. The next. Figure
in.
In the quantum gases of bosun's notes where. This
millimeter scale is. Just about the central
frequency on the x axis of of this plot, which is
shown here in. Frequency of a particular.
Cyclical frequency rather than angular frequency,
so omega is two pi times. This F on the horizontal
axis here plotted in readers of Inver seconds,
which are also known as Herts.
And a frequency of several times, 10 to the 11
cycles per second. Corresponds to lights traveling
at the speed of light with a wavelength of about a
millimeter, let's see, 10 to the 11 would be a
hundred billion cycles per second. So this is the
overall.
Um.
Power density of the cosmic microwave background
averaged over all of the the sky is no longer
looking at the temperature fluctuations, focusing
on the overall measurements that can be carried
out quite precisely to the point that the. The
size of the squares in this figure showing the the
data are.
Generous estimates of the overall uncertainties in
these observational measurements of the power
coming from the cosmic microwave background, all
of the stars and galaxies subtracted away as a
function of that frequency. Which is then fit to
the salad line is our plank distribution.
And. In particular, we can see that there's really
an excellent agreement between all of these
data points and.
The overall Planck distribution, with its
particular value of the temperature as as that
only free parameter, so it's to. Remind ourselves
of what this election is. Which I can write either
in terms of that angular frequency Omega or the
frequency F, which is.
Let me go over to pie. I prefer to work in terms
of the angular frequency omega just to. Keep the
factors of supply under control.
We have.
Plant distribution, given in terms of Omega cubed
over E to the each of our Omega over to. Minus one
in that fit to the single parameter of the
temperature. To these data then. Gives the.
Bellevue, that was.
Published along with this plot from all the way
back in 1990, this was one of the first
measurements of the temperature of the cosmic
microwave background radiation. Which.
Measured it to. Just a few percent precision, so
two point seventy four plus minus zero point zero
six Kelvin. And in the 30 years since those
measurements were carried out, they've become much
more precise by many orders of magnitude, which in
turn allows a check of the age of the universe
simply by figuring out how long it. Needs to have
been in order for the cosmic microwave background,
initially formed at a high temperature of
thousands of Kelvin to have decreased to the two
point seventy five Kelvin that we observe in the
present day.
Applause Just to check if any questions have come
in while you've been going through that. Bit about
the cosmic microwave background, because there's
one. Final thing I want to say about the cosmic
microwave background as a bit of a further
supplement that is mentioned in the notes without
going into detail, which is that the cosmic
microwave background is.
One of the strongest sources for. Our strongest
sources of evidence that we have for the existence
and other properties of dark matter.
And this is the figure we want to take look at in
the context of dark matter, because the evidence
for dark matter from the cosmic microwave
background is coming. Through a bit more involved
calculations than we're doing in this module, and
in particular, we have to take into account the
interactions between dark matter and. This the the
plasma of photons, light radiation and all the
other particles in existence in the early stages
of the universe on the cosmic microwave background
was formed. And carrying out those sorts of
calculations. Allows. Allows us to predict.
Not only the. Energy profile following the Planck
distribution that we were able to get from the
simple, not interacting photon gas, but also the
overall patterns of the fluctuations in the
temperature for the effective temperature shown
here, where. I should have mentioned when we were
looking at this figure that we can do these sorts
of fits of data to the plate distribution for
individual points in the empty sky show.
In this picture here and use those facts to
determine the temperature of the cosmic microwave
background coming precisely from that point in the
sky. So that's how the temperature. And in
particular, the fluctuations being shown here is
determined.
And what we would be able to predict from
computing the interactions between photons and in
a matter of ordinary matter that interacts
directly with light in the way that we are used to
in every day, as well as dark matter, which is
transparent and invisible to heat and lights and.
And the other. Experimental tools that we have
available in our laboratories on Earth carrying
out those calculations of those interactions leads
to predictions for how these regions of. Higher
and lower temperature photons and the cosmic
microwave background are distributed around the
sky and. The usual way of presenting that sort of
data about.
The characteristics of. How likely we are if we
are in some hot patch of the sky to find another
hot patch as opposed to a cold patch, some
particular distance away in the sky. So because.
This is a three dimensional spherical shell
projected onto a two dimensional page, the
distance between. Those two passes is a measure of
an angular separation in the sky and the
measurement of. How much the temperature in one
place in the sky is correlated with another place,
a certain angle away. Is the usual way that all of
the information in these measurements of the
cosmic microwave background can be reduced to just
a simple plot like this, which is. A relatively
old one from 2006, so the data have become much
more precise since then.
But this plot is nice because it illustrates how
the. The quantity being plotted vertically, which,
again, this program is not, let me draw on it, how
that is being shown as a function of an angular
scale labeled on the upper horizontal axis of this
plotts.
Flooded in particular logarithmically. Though the
vertical axis is an ordinary. Ordinary scale, so
this is a similar logarithmic plot and what is
shown on. The bottom horizontal axis is the
conversion of those angular scales in what's
called a a multiple expansion where. If we go back
to. This figure. Here is a simple dipole or.
What these polls correspond to is essentially.
Dividing up the the overall sky into some number
of. Of pieces or sectors that we can start with,
say, a dipole, which is just looking at dividing
the sky into two pieces. Which can freely take any
orientation in this representation of the data and
seeing just how much how strongly those two pieces
are correlated with each other. And similarly for
Waterfall's dividing the sky into four pieces,
octopods dividing it into eight and so on, with
any possible orientation that leads to looking at
smaller scale fluctuations between those different
regions. So that's the connection shown here
between this so-called multiple moment and angular
scale where they see being plotted on the vertical
axis is a measure of that correlation between the
high and low temperature fluctuations at those
corresponding scales. And the data points are the
measurements that can be. Taken and extracted from.
Data going into those temperature fluctuation
pictures that we were that are in the notes and
we're flipping back and forth between. In the sort
of British curve that is overlaid on top of them
is the prediction of the much more complicated
calculation with something like six parameters of.
Exactly what sort of temperature fluctuations we
would expect on any given scale, following from
that calculation of how the photons of the cosmic
microwave background are. Interacting with all of
the the matter in the universe, both. Visible,
luminous matter like atoms. And all of the
materials that we're familiar with, as well as
these potentially dark matter. And in particular,
where dark matter comes into this calculation,
though, sorry that I can't draw. Drawn onto. On
this picture, but the amount of dark matter is
most clearly seen in the relative heights of the
second and third peaks around this multiple moment,
five hundred and eight hundred, respectively,
angular scales of point four degrees versus about
point to five degrees where?
The the dark matter is the main reason that that
third. Peek in this plot is as large or as high
vertically as the second piece, which is easier to
see in a slightly more recent
figure here. I can zoom in just a bit. So this is
putting a little bit more recent data from two
thousand nine rather than two thousand six.
Slightly different scales, but still that same
correlation between the temperature fluctuations
of the cosmic microwave background at different
angular scales in the sky. And here that data is
being fit to two different predictions in two
different calculations shown by a dotted line and
a solid line. Where the cell phone line is what
would be predicted if there were no dark matter in
the universe. And the dotted line is the
prediction if if there is dark matter and. We can
take away from this plot is that the data really
demand the existence of dark matter in a
particular, we can see that in that third peak,
around 800 or L equals eight hundred and eight
hundred multiple moments on the horizontal axis,
which is where the difference between the dotted
and solid curves is most significant and easiest
to see. There is a much better description of the
data being provided by the hypothesis of dark
matter, which is just one piece of evidence
establishing the existence of dark matter, though
possibly the the most solid piece of evidence and
the evidence that is. Most difficult to to get
around by supposing that gravity might behave
differently than than we observe, which is an
argument that was carried out in the 80s and 90s
when the existence of dark matter was first being
established. So that is.
The connection of the cosmic microwave background
and of and the work we are doing on quantum gases
of photons to. Some hot topics in modern physics,
like the. Existence of dark matter. Pause again
briefly just to check if any questions have come
in, what we've gone through, that which does get
us through.
All of the. Photon gas material from the from week
eight in the module.
And.
Since let's see, I'm looking at the time and not
seeing questions, and I think there is time that
we can.
If you just get into a bit about fermions, the end
of today and even before that, there's one last
topic that I was tempted to include in the
materials for for the module, but left out because
it is, again, a. A more complicated calculation,
though, possibly a more interesting one than the
photon gas, which is what happens if we have. Non
relativistic gases of those zones, and in
particular at low temperatures where those non
relativistic gases would differ from their
behavior, would differ from the classical case
that we considered back in in week four before the
break. And.
There's really a fascinating phenomenon that
occurs in. Non relativistic losen gases at low
temperature at the cost of a much more complicated
calculation, when we are not able to approximate
the chemical potential as varnishing and have to
carry out the full calculation of inaugural's
mustard gas with a a non-zero chemical potential.
This is this phenomenon is known as those Einstein
carbonisation, as the name suggests. It follows
from those Einstein statistics and was first
predicted by Einstein building on the work of
those in the 1920s. And it took a good 70 years
for technology to advance sufficiently to get
temperatures low enough that both Einstein
condensation could be observed. Experimentally in
a an atomic physics lab.
And that was very promptly rewarded with the Nobel
Prize in 2001. And this video that I will try to.
Broadcast over Zoome will see.
How it's picked up and transmitted, but that video
is. Illustration of what's going on with those and
condensation. Just lasting about a minute and
showing.
Both the quantize energy levels and their
occupation numbers as or for a gas of those arms
and how those occupation numbers tend to depend on
the temperature when we have a non relativistic.
Relation between the energy and momentum of these
particles. And as the temperature lowers,
gradually, the energy levels that the bosons are
able to populate become a lower and lower and
eventually at very low temperatures. All of this
goes on to form a new state of matter, all
populating that lowest energy level and behaving.
As a single collective quantum wave, as
illustrated here.
So sorry to add, there is the link where that full
video can be found, and hopefully it wasn't too
distracting for me to talk over the subtitles that
it was showing from the. And so how to get out of
that full screen? And back to another window.
So what are the so those kind of candidates have
many remarkable features. I'll just highlight. To
one of which being that. That transition from the
gas of not interacting particles, the sort of
ideal gas that we've been considering through this
module, that makes all the calculations especially
simple when that gas of separate nondrinking
particles changes to a. Single collective
wavefunction that really is what's known as a
phase transition, a change in the state of matter
of those particles, sort of similar to water
changing into ice. And this is reflected by.
Discontinuities and non Atlantis's in quantities
like the heat capacity, which is shown here in so
is David Tonguç lecture notes that go through the
more complicated calculation of the density of
states that has to be carried out.
In order to predict this sort of behavior, but the.
The cusp of the peak that is shown in the heat
capacity at this critical temperature, T.C., is
the characteristic feature of a phase transition,
which we're going to get into on this week. But
next week after the bank holiday and usually phase
transitions require interactions between. The
particles in the system, those are some
condensation being really one of the unique
systems in which a non interacting theory is able
to show with this sort of phase transition. I can
also point out that at high temperatures in this
plot, as we go off to the right, which can't draw
on.
This window either see that the heat capacity
approaches, that three halves end, we computed for
the.
The classical unrealistic gas in week for.
And yet the last thing to say about those I
conversation is that while it was a real.
Technological breakthrough in in the mid 90s very
quickly became a routine experimental setup to
create a Bose Einstein condensate and use it for
all sorts of other purposes as a tool in ultra low
temperature physics labs, and in particular, a lot
of the applications of those those Einstein
concepts that are being created now in hundreds of
labs around the world is to serve as the basis for
for quantum computers or quantum simulating
machines, where those Einstein concept is created
and then it's quantum properties are manipulated
in order to do calculations and simulations.
So I guess, as usual, that discussion will
supplement on both our side conversation went on
longer than. I expected so I'm going to to wrap up
there and Thursday will be quantum is a fermions
from the start. And this is the last call for
questions today.
And if there aren't any of the next ministers who
will shut down the zoo meeting, extract that
recording and come back in about 10 minutes for
today's office hours.