OK, I've got the recording underway and may spend.
A couple of minutes going over some of the usual
logistical issues, while perhaps more folks will
be able to to sign in on this bright Monday
morning in Liverpool and.
We start off with the usual link to people
everywhere, which I think I will experiment with
using in a different way for at least the next few
days, depending on. How the number of folks were
able to make it to these secret sessions continues
to evolve. As the numbers decrease, it becomes a
bit more. Of a burden on each individual
participant to go back and forth between. Polls
and discussions, so I may just leave the the basic.
Pull open, giving you the opportunity to ask any
questions and guide the course of what we
discussed today. And I will try to keep an eye on
both those results and zoom simultaneously. And
also invite you just to speak up in Zoome, if you
miss a written comment or you just want to ask a
question out loud.
And so with a reduced role of polls and quizzes
and those sorts of activities, what I think we can
spend some time profitably doing both for those of
you here who can direct the course of what we
discuss and for the folks checking out the
recording after the fact, just go through the
materials for for this weekend and last week. And
chat about some of the key conceptual issues that
are highlighted there, see if there are any
questions or confusions about those. And I may
also elaborate on some of the. Background or some
of the information that is not assumed as
background, but is being brought in as ANZAAS or
an assumption with regards to quantum physics,
photons, the nature of light and that sort of
thing.
So with that prelude, all pause for a minute or
two to see if there are any immediate questions
about those materials, not only for this week and
last, but any point throughout the the module. Any
questions about the computer project due last week
or the final homework that is due next week, a
week from tomorrow?
It helps, of course, if I remember to turn on the
screen, share where I am actually sharing.
Matt.
People everywhere question.
So not seeing or hearing. Any immediate questions
can pull up the materials going back to last week,
the topic of quantum statistics that this week
we're digging into a bit more in a more detailed
investigation of photon gases as the simplest
realization of a quantum statistical system of
Bosnich particles to be followed next week by
quantum statistical systems of thermionic
particles in the. Synchronous sessions last week,
we discussed pretty thoroughly not only the
background and previous parts of the module
leading up to the term break, but one of the two
main conceptual issues that comes in when we bring
in quantum statistics. Again, without assuming
familiarity with quantum mechanics, the issue we
discussed pretty thoroughly is the need to.
Revise or change how we define. The sum over
microstates that gives us the.
Partition function or grand canonical partition
function from which. Essentially, all aspects of
our statistical system can be derived in that is
always defined as the sum over microstates of the
Celsi, distinguishing between classical and
quantum statistics is how the individual
microstates are defined and distinguished from
each other, with the classical case involving
considering each particle in the system in turn in
something over all of the possible energies that
it could have. And then in the indistinguishable
case that is relevant for quantum particles, we
have to correct possible overcounting or fairly
ubiquitous overcounting in order to get the proper
number of microstates. And that works perfectly
well in a high temperature classical regime where
there is. A huge number of microstates available
compared to the number of particles in the system,
so there is a negligible probability for multiple
particles to simultaneously occupy the same energy
level. And the quantum regime where classical
statistical physics breaks down is distinguished
by the opposite behavior when there are relatively
few energy levels compared to the number of
particles occupying them. And there are then
subtleties in the overcounting coming from the
need to treat differently. Particles that are in
different energy levels or in the same energy
level, and we illustrated how that works with a
very simple example of the quantum system of two
particles that can be any in any one of five
energy levels where the mathematics is the same as
counting the number of ways that two balls can be
placed in any of five boxes. And the results of
the classical approach I described are going over
each ball, figuring out the number of boxes that
they could go in, the number of possibilities, and
then correcting for overcounting naively gives a
non integer number of possible microstates,
possible ways of distributing
these particles into the energy levels. And the
quantum correction to that is instead of.
Something over each particle and then all possible
energies, we sum over the possible energy levels
and then how many particles can be in each one,
the so-called occupation number? Which is the
concept we encountered when developing the
canonical and grand Kilmichael ensemble's. You
threw the the replica trick nonsense for the large
thermal reservoir and particle reservoir that
fixed the temperature and chemical potential in
these canonical and canonical approaches and with
the partition function.
Defined in this way as a sum over microstates. So
right up here. Then there is no further
overcounting to worry about, and we can just
proceed in a simple and straightforward way. So
that is the quick review of the longer discussions
and exercises and activities we went through last
week. And the. So before moving on to the other
key conceptual issue of Sevenoaks, of course, to
see if there are. Questions or comments about.
That issue of the quantum statistical approach.
So moving on, I will actually not jump straight to
the.
The key conceptual issue of the classical limits,
how quantum statistics and classical statistics.
Reproduce each other in the appropriate regime, so
that's classical physics familiar from Newton's
time and even before it can provide excellent
approximations to the natural world that is in a
more fundamental underlying level described by
quantum mechanics. Two things to. Highlights in
the intermediate sections comparing bosons and
fermions, the two types of quantum particles that
are distinguished by the possible occupation
numbers that they could have.
And.
I want to emphasize something that comes up a
little later on, which is that in all of the work
up through this week and even into next week, that
one guest is a fermions. We are still considering
idealized system so called ideal Das's, where the
individual particles are not interacting at all
with each other. If they come and approach each
other instead of colliding and bouncing off each
other, they simply pass straight through, have no
influence on each other, which provides enormous
simplifications which will come to appreciate more
when we. Drop that. Assumption or that
approximation in week ten and look at interacting
systems where things immediately become enormously
more complicated
one. Aspect of these non interacting particles
that might sound mysterious without having seen
the concepts of those kinds of fermions before, is
the issue of exactly how fermions as quantum
particles are set up so that at most a single
formation can occupy any given energy level? So
the intuitive but incorrect way of thinking about
this. Is to picture fermions as repelling each
other so that once one has claimed its energy
level, it forces out any other formula that might
try to come in there, just kicks it way off to the
curb so that it cannot join the. For the current
four million occupying the energy level in the way
that those zones are able to, but that would be
inconsistent with an approximation that the
particles we're working with are not interacting
and do not exert any forces on each other in in
any circumstances.
And the.
The real reason that criminals behave as they do
has to do with a feature of quantum mechanics that
is briefly summarized in the material but is
somewhat tangential to the course itself. And
there's no need to worry about or think about this
topic in order to extract the key information and
applications of statistical physics. But
essentially. For those who are curious, can spend
be synchronous sessions, elaborating a bit on some
aspects of this background that come into play and
connects to statistical physics, tying all of
modern physics and mathematics together into a
coherent description of the universe. And in
quantum mechanics, particles and in microwaves of
many particles are described by wave, what are
called wave functions, which are essentially the
square roots of probabilities defined at all
points in space and time. And those wave functions
are the technical term. For. What I call the
system in this paragraph, giving a bit of
supplementary background, so if we consider.
A system of two particles in my system here, I
mean, wavefunction that is conventionally written
as the uppercase Greek letter PSI, and we think
about parametrized in that way function in terms
of the positions of those two particles, X1 and X2.
And we ask what would happen if we took those two?
Identical, indistinguishable particles that
position X one index to. And just swap them the
particle at X one, moving to X to position X, to
particle X to moving to position X one.
And in three spatial dimensions.
Which is.
I think a footnote on the previous page here.
Where more interesting behavior is possible in
different set ups, for example, if we have
particles confined to the two dimensional surface
of the table, they can exhibit more exotic
behavior. But in three dimensions. The familiar
case that we operate in on the day to day basis,
there are only two possibilities for what happens
when we exchange these two identical particles
that are related to what I said earlier about the
wavefunction essentially being thought of as a
square root of a probability distribution because
the particles are identical. The the probability
for this set up is unchanged by swapping them, so
the probability is one and if we take the square
root, there are two possibilities, plus one and
minus one, both of which square to that
probability, one. So we can have. If the pen
writes, instead of changing the zoom of the page,
that procedure can lead to either that same.
System, that same wavefunction with a positive
sign, which is.
Behavior of those items or you can pick up that
negative sign that still squares to the same
probability distribution, which is the behavior of
fermions,
what we saw last week and earlier in these notes
that when the particles are occupying. That same
energy level, so this final column of the
possibilities that we considered in the simple
example case of two particles with five energy
levels, there really is only one energy level and
interchanging multiple particles in that energy
level. Introduces no change to the system or to
its wavefunction. So that is the system or that is
set up that would correspond to multiple fermions
in the same energy level where we would have that
same system equal to its negative or that same
wavefunction equal to as negative and therefore
vanishing. So no possibility of having fermions in
the same energy level, not due to any force or
interaction, but due to.
The.
Underlying fundamental description of quantum
particles, so that is a bit of elaboration on the
background there, how we can still be working with.
Not interacting particles that still are not able
to. Share a share the same energy level.
And.
As I move on to the final section. Take a quick
check to look for questions or requests for topics
to discuss. I will note. In passing a statement
made in.
This derivation of the grand canonical partition
function for Bosnich particles having to do with
the convergence of the geometric series that
requires the exponential factor to be less than
one or equivalently, its arguments to be negative,
less than zero, which means that each individual
factor with a positive temperature and that
overall negative sign has to be greater than zero.
And I mentioned here that generically. We have the
lowest energy level set equal to zero, and in fact,
it is possible to shift all energy levels by a
constant factor without changing any expectation
values coming out of the statistical probability
space, which is a a derivation we can go through
or you can work out on your own. In that case, we
require a strictly negative chemical potential,
which those of you who have had a chance to look
at the materials for this week, even at 9:00 a.m.
on the Monday morning, will see that in the
photographs where we look at the simplest case of
an exactly vanishing chemical potential, which we
are able to do by stepping back to the. Basic
underlying condition that the difference between
energy and chemical potential has to be positive
and for the photon gas at a finite volume. The.
Formulation of quantum mechanics of financially as
opposed to classical physics does forbid that zero
energy state, which is how we can get away with
that state, that simplification of a vanishing
chemical potential for photons.
And how that is consistent with this discussion
here, in case that might have caused any confusion
or might cause confusion in the future as you. Dig
into to the material for this week and compare it
with the derivation left from last week that we're
still discussing.
So hopping ahead past the.
Derivation of the Bose, Einstein and pheromone
Dirac Green canonical partition functions that
define quantum statistics for those two classes of
quantum particles.
You made the statements and looked at the plot
briefly last week that high temperatures are aware
classical physics should be a good approximation
to the underlying quantum behavior of the natural
world. And we demonstrated that by putting all
three of these statistical systems next to each
other. From the page here where we can already see
from these three equations. Where they are.
We're going to be. Reproducing each other is
actually maybe even easier to see when we take the
logarithm of the three to define the corresponding
grand canonical potentials. The usual way that we
manipulate and work with the partition function in
practical calculations. I can see that in the
limits where this exponential factor into the wind
speed of times, the energy of the energy level
minus the chemical potential, is much less than
one. We can expand these logarithms to linear
order in that factor. And all that remains is
precisely that factor. So the logarithm reduces to
the exponential factor, which is what we get in
the so-called Maxwell Boltzmann calculation
corresponding to the classical statistical
approach of sending over particles and then over
all their possible energies, then correcting for
overcounting and similarly, in the Byzantine
Einstein case, expanding that logarithm to linear
order in a small exponential would bring out the
negative side. In addition to the exponential in
all three of these.
Canonical potentials end up. Agreeing as we
checked out visually on the the figure on the last
page of the section there is. Some calculation to
do the work to do to reach down to.
To that figure in that results on a quantitative
rather than conceptual level, which. Were you
about halfway through the day? There's time to
quickly run through. These three calculations,
which are going to start to become routine and
quite familiar as we practice going through.
Through them one after the next, and just to
simplify some of the notation here, they may
rewrite things. In terms of. Just to each the
minus X, some L, the L was labeling each energy
level of our system. Now we are. Something over in
the quantum case and.
Rewriting the classical result in terms of so that.
Excel is the inverse temperature beat of times,
the energy of the energy level minus the chemical
potential and.
The derivative, well, I should have really changed
variables in the derivative itself that we can see
that it brings down a factor of Beita with a plus
sign from the two negative sides overall.
So we have a T and EBITA that cancel as their
inverses and then just the same exponential factor,
you the minus Extel, which we want to identify as.
A sum over the energy levels of the average
occupation number for each energy level in the
next Fogelson case.
The derivative is.
Just a bit. More work in the other two cases, but.
Proceeds in the same sort of way that. Now, in
addition to that factor of data here with three
negative signs coming. Along with it, so it's
minus T in the minus beta, and it needs of the
minus X comes along, the derivative of the log is
one divided by its arguments in the sun over
energy levels out front, which again, those are
cancelling and we end up with.
If some of your average occupation numbers for the
Bose Einstein quantum statistical distribution
appropriate for bosun's, where the occupation
numbers that we sum over for each energy level can
take any non negative value zero, one, two, three
and off to infinity, depending on the total number
of particles in the micro state. That's the reason
we're working with the grand canonical ensemble to
keep things simple and straightforward and
something over the possible fluctuations in the
number of particles with a fixed chemical
potential. And. Very similar calculation in the
very direct case, with the only difference here
being how many negative signs there are and with
an even number of negative signs changing compared
to the those Einstein case, the results. Ends up
the same each the minus beta times. Exponential of
exponential minus data times energy minus chemical
potential. So the average occupation number for
that very direct distribution appropriate for
fermions, they can have only zero or one particle
per energy level. This is the only possible
occupation numbers. And what we just wrote down
match the results given here after dividing
through by the exponential factor e to the data
times differences in energy and chemical potential.
And we can obviously see the non conversions of
that, but as I sign distribution in the limit,
when the exponential factor here becomes E to the
zero, if the energy were ever equal to the
chemical potential, we have one divided by each of
the zero minus one, which diverges, as was also
shown in the figure we looked at fairly briefly.
Last week that if I add this is zero here where
that horizontal axis is precisely the.
Difference between energy and chemical potential.
So if that ever reaches zero and the Bose Einstein
distribution heads off to infinity before it gets
there, in contrast to the classical Maxwell
Boltzmann case. That diverges exponentially.
Where that X is the.
Horizontal axis. Down there and the very direct
case saturates the maximum possible occupation,
number four, and energy level with fermions where
the average occupation number is one, that means
that we always have a fermoy on in. In this energy
level, every every energy level is occupied, and
as the lower lying energy levels become occupied,
the fermions are forced by the exclusion principle
to seek out higher and higher energy levels that
remain unoccupied and therefore available to them,
which is.
The fundamental reason why atoms have electronic
structure because electrons are fermions and
rather than all filling up, all the electrons
orbiting an atomic nucleus could opt for Yori just
hanging out in the ground. States have every atom
behave the same with no such thing as chemistry,
but that Pauli exclusion principle is what
prevents that situation. Forces electrons to keep
filling out higher and higher energy levels in
atoms, which is what allows those atoms to form
molecules and. Eventually form us. So the
exclusion principle is quite useful for us to
exist.
So at this point, I will. Pause one last time
before diving into the deeper analysis of the.
Quantum statistics of gas's of those arms, the
more familiar case where. We could have as many
bosun's as we want in any given energy level, if
there are questions about. What has come up so far
today?
Write it down or speak them up, raise your hand
and zoom. You know.
If you just a few seconds for that before hopping
over. To recreate.
Not seeing or. Hearing anything on any screen?
We can dive into week eight again with a bit of.
Supplementary background or elaboration on the the
module material. And in fact, I preview this a bit
earlier today when we were talking about the. The
chemical potential and the appearance of the
diversions in the.
Those Einstein distribution when the exponential
factor. Equals one when his argument vanishes.
They have that energy level equal to the chemical
potential. I can see that divergence both here in.
Dividing by one over a factor approaching zero one
minus one or taking the logarithm of factor one
minus a number, that approaches one. As its
argument goes to zero, but.
Not surprisingly, since the real world is not
divergent, everything is finite. We do not
encounter. That issue in. Real systems, in part
because the rules of quantum mechanics require
that the energy levels in a finite volume are
non-zero. The momentum in particular do not take a
exactly varnishing zero value and. Again, at the
level of this molecule that can be taken as input,
but if you are curious about where exactly it's
coming from, there is it can be appreciated from.
A fairly famous result of quantum physics called
the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle, which.
States that. Well, what is called the uncertainty
or.
What we can really recognize, having gone through
some of the work of this module as this version of
a particle's position and of that particular
momentum in quantum mechanics
has some minimum value, that that product there,
you can find factors of two in different
dimensions for this cell, but a little squiggly
sign in that inequality. But there is a factor of
each bar on the right hand side.
And there's also a AL-JABRI, a connection to this
that the. Position and momentum are. Don, can you
take operators in the language of of algebra's la
algebra's of the groups for those of you who have
encountered those concepts in previous modules?
And how far is the.
Is there commutator the level to which they do not
compete with each other, but that may be getting
too technical, even for supplementary?
Addition to to the material, what happens if we
had a momentum of exactly zero leading to an
energy of exactly zero is that the uncertainty of
the dispersion in the momentum itself would be
exactly zero. And then we would need an infinite
divergence, dispersion in the position in order
for this inequality to be satisfied. And that is
something that we cannot have in a finite volume,
such as the observable universe. So we have
non-zero energies, which is what allows us to have
the. Vanishing chemical potential.
Discussed at the end of this first section of the
is on gas, and that is.
Another significant simplification, not quite as
significant as the factorization that comes from
Don, attracting ideal particles, which is what?
Allows the overall grand canonical potential to be
written as a simple sum over all the possible
energy levels of the system. But it is still a
very useful and very significant simplification,
which we can see where we would see if we tried to
duck back to the.
Non relativistic or.
I should say massive exotic particles that we
considered back in in week four, we had classical
particles inaudible gas in the container with
their energy of P squared. Overthe place, their
mass, which in that finite volume, the
quantization of the moment, simply leads to this
expression for the energy that we've seen before
as an overall factor, depending on the volume and
depending on Planck's constant each for. With just
numerical factors of.
None. Well, in the classical case, not negative,
but here in quantum mechanics, strictly positive
integers k ranging from one to up to infinity to
finding our energy levels and their degeneracy is.
And I did. Mentioned in that discussion just now,
I realize talking about relativistic and non
relativistic particles, maybe I'll wrap up the
last few minutes today by
just filling in some discussion of that. A
reminder for those of you who have encountered
special relativity in the past and maybe a bit of,
again, interesting supplemental information for
those of you who. Or maybe seeing this for the
first time, you have some blank space at the top
of the page here where I can write down really the
most general expression for the energy of a
particle as a function of its momentum in special
relativity, which is the square root of that
momentum squared times, the speed of light squared,
plus the mass of the particle again squared times
the speed of light to the power. Four, to get the
universe to work out correctly. We're also
something we certainly saw in before, but I'll
remind you of here is that this undecorated P
squared for the momenta is the scalar product of
the momentum vectors.
That you have components of momentum in each
possible spatial direction, left and right,
forward and backward, up and down. So writing
things out in terms of those components, this
overall P squared that appears in the energy
momentum relation. Is just the sum of squares of
those individual momentum components in the X, Y
and Z directions. And if we consider the case of a
particle with vanishing momentum and see
immediately that its energy is the mass times, the
speed of light squared equals MC squared being the
one of the most famous equations in the bottle in
modern physics and also in pretty modern physics.
This describes the so-called reste energy. Of a
particle with mass M that is not moving, it has
lamented zero. And. If we take the.
Consider the opposite extreme of a particle with
mass, much less than its momentum rather than much
greater than its momentum, than the mass drops out
of this equation. And we just have the energy
equal to P the moment, sometimes the speed of
light operating effectively as a unit conversion
factor, changing from units of momentum to units
of energy. So choosing appropriate units leaves
that speed of light just equal to to one, though
we will carry it around in.
In the materials for this module.
Just to keep track of it and as a check on some of
these familiar equations like equals EMC squared.
And if we look at, say, intermediate regimes,
where. Say both the momentum and mass are non-zero
zero, but the the mass is relatively large
compared to the momentum. Then we can pull. That
factor, EMC squared out in front of that square
root and. Changing the order of the terms would
end up with just one plus A P squared over M
squared times, C squared. From pulling out four
factors of sea out of the two that are already
multiplying the momentum under the square roots
and expanding this to linear order in that ratio
of P divided by it, that should call this and see.
We get the rest energy, EMC squared plus EMC
squared times. Pia, authorities squared plus order.
Peter, the four. Over M three, C two, which. Like,
where can I fit this in?
That is EMC squared, the rest energy will let me
do this, pull out just that latter term we have.
What is called the kinetic energy or energy of
motion, energy of momentum, factor of P squared,
we have M over M squared is an M i. Forgot about a
factor of a half from the expansion of the square
root as a one half power, and there is to any and
all factors of sea cancel out, and that should be.
Exactly what we wrote down a few weeks ago. So
that is the distinction that we have between non
relativistic particles considered previously and
the relativistic particles with. Energy of
momentum, time, speed of light, which is the case
for photons that we're focusing on this week, and
an easy way to remember this whole setup is to
picture a triangle with the energy on the
hypotenuse, a right triangle with.
EMC squared on one of the legs of the triangle in
P, C on the other, which.
Doesn't have any real physical meaning as a
triangle, but it's a visual, dramatic way to
remember the. Overall relation between mass energy
and momentum in special relativity. So.
That takes us to the end of time and I will stop
there and dig into the actual results of the week,
eight notes on Thursday called. You're free to ask
any immediate questions that you have right now,
but. If I don't hear those next few seconds, I
will shut down, zoom and sort of back up again
after saving the recording for the office hours
and then call again Thursday afternoon.