No. Hi, folks, and welcome back. And after the
term break.
Expecting or hoping that a few more people will
sign in over the next few minutes so they'll get
the recording started at the screen shared and
just start off with the usual pull for whether
there are any. Questions or issues that you would
like to. Bring up focus on discuss during this
secretive session before charging into some of the
logistics coming up and the. The new material on
quantum statistics and perhaps before getting into
the new stuff, it might be worthwhile to do a
recap or review of what came before the break
since it was a few weeks ago. Now that that break.
Kicked in some of the. Details may have slipped
away in the meantime, the. The.
Usual screening share set up and running.
Which should now be.
Visible and. Maybe the most timely matter is the
second parts of the computer project that is due
tomorrow. I have well, I've seen that some of you
have already submitted this over the past 10 days
or so, though there is still time for submissions,
if you see anything that.
Maybe suspicious or you would like to revise and
of course, there are many of you still working on
it and I have received questions about it from.
From a few of you and any further questions about
both about the assignment for the second part of
Self as well as for the solutions to the first
part that provide something of a template, a
similar exercise in the case where we had the
central limit theorem at hand to to provide an
analytic check of the numerical solutions, that is
all fair game for today is synchronous session.
And while I.
Wait to see if any. Questions of that sort come in.
Through that usual poll everywhere, a link in the
chat window. There it is again. For those of you
who have joined since it was first posted, I can
provide some general comments on. The first
homework assignments that got graded during the
break, so you all should have gotten the feedback
and solutions to that. So I can.
Show off in this screen.
And to begin with, maybe I will highlight the very
last part of the third question is the one that
was
most consistently confusing for for several of you,
which was asking what are the conditions under
which?
This generic. Each capacity. Um.
Why you are not drawing, I don't know.
Something. Going on with the tablet there that now
seems to be resolved. So when is that heat
capacity and which takes the generic form of
energy fluctuations around the expectation value
of the energy, the conditions under which that can
equal zero and. The.
Common response that came into that question was
to say that, you know, we started off with the
heat capacity.
Equal to the derivative of that energy expectation
value with respect to the temperature. So it was
tempting to set that to zero and then. Say that E
had to be.
The constant in order for the capacity to vanish
in that is certainly a sufficient condition, but
it is not, in fact necessary. And this is a much
too severe a a condition to impose in order to get
the capacity to manage what we saw, just to review
the solutions. If you haven't looked at them
recently, all we have to do is recall the
definition of an expectation value as the sum over
microstates of the argument of that expectation
value in the annual brackets. And in this case,
that sum over microstates becomes the sum of a
strictly non-negative quantity, some quantity
squared. Multiplied by the probability that is
also not negative and we can take to be strictly
positive by saying that the sun is over, the
accessible micro states that have a non-zero
probability of actually appearing in the system.
So what we have is. A sum of strictly positive
squares with positive coefficients and the only
way that some can vanish is if each individual
term vanishes individually, which gives us the
constraints on the energy for each individual
micro state. That has to be exactly equal to that
expectation value.
In other words, there are no possible fluctuations
of the energy around this particular value that
turns out then to be the expectation value is the
only possibility. So.
We can actually see this in action back. All the
way back in week three, actually, when we were
looking at a system of indistinguishable spins. So
spins in the solid that can wake up or down.
And pick up some energy from.
Their interactions with external magnetic field. H.
Which. Age oriented in that direction, and we
computed. Back in those days before the break that.
The of the resulting energy for the system and
spins coming from that Helmholtz free energy was.
Minus beta, eight times the hyperbolic tangent.
A better age is the strength of the magnetic field,
beta is the inverse temperature. And therefore,
the heat capacity.
Resulting from this.
Is.
Try to remember the beta squared.
Debate The Times, this minus B, the age.
And then the.
Metabolic Vangent.
And if I can. Do this in my head or remember the
answer. Had the negative sides cancelling out and
then the two terms gave a.
Beta H squared over the hyperbolic cosine squared.
Of being age, which in the limit of. So we can do
the usual exercise of looking at the high and low
temperature limits of this function. At low
temperatures, so t going to zero. Are going to
infinity, the hyperbolic cosine diverges much more
quickly than Bureij squared, so that is one limit
in which the heat capacity goes to zero. Whereas
in the limit of infinite temperature where beta
goes to zero, hyperbolic, cosine goes to one, the
numerator also goes to zero in the way that in
that synchronous session we went through and
plotted here, this is I can't draw. On this screen,
but the vertical axis here is the heat capacity
for that system of indistinguishable spins and the
horizontal axis is Beda, the inverse temperature
so that.
The high temperature limit corresponds to the
small data where. Nobody goes to zero zero zero,
the capacity also goes to zero in the limit of low
temperatures or infinite beta. So this is a simple
but not trivial example where the heat capacity is
not always zero. But we still have limits in which
it equals zero when the well, we can check that in
those limits. We want. The energy of each
microstates to equal the expectation value with no
fluctuations. So that is perhaps the takeaway
message that we should have looked at before
switching back here so we can recall that when we
have. Very low temperatures, the probability for
the system to be in any micro state other than its
ground state is exponentially suppressed. It
vanishes exponentially quickly. In the in terms of
the energy gap. Which for these things is.
To. Age, the change in the energy that we get when
we flip one of these spins from oriented with the
magnetic field of giving a low energy to oriented
against, it's giving a high energy. So as the
temperature goes to zero, essentially only a
single microstates remains with non-negative
probability. And that is the ground state where
all the spins are aligned with the magnetic field
and it's its micro state. Energy is then so
trivially equal to the expectation value. The high
temperature limit with beta varnishing is a bit
more subtle because that's the case when every
possible microstates is equally likely just
because their energies are negligible compared to
the energy scale set by the temperature. So we're
free to.
Sample every single one of those microstates with.
What appear to be different energies and the way
that we end up with the high capacity going to
zero in that limit is that all of those energies
are so small compared to the temperature that they
are effectively zero. And with no fluctuations,
then around that zero, the expectation value, so
that is the physical picture behind the
mathematics we're looking at here and an example
showing how we don't need this constraint, that
the high capacity always vanishes in order to have
that function vanish under some particular
conditions on the micro state energies.
I haven't seen. Questions come in about the
computer projects, homework solutions or other
asynchronous materials so far, so I'll pause for a
few breaths to see if there are follow up
questions about that, that last part of question
three.
And I can remember while waiting for those that. I
did make another notes about generic feedback on
the assignment, which was that the vast majority
of the marks that were lost were were lost for
parts of problems that were skipped, not not
answered, rather than doing things incorrectly. So
on the one hand, that's encouraging that when
solutions were presented, they tended to be
correct. And then the.
The question is whether the the absence of an
attempt was just due to a lack of time and too
many things going on, or if there were questions
about even where to get started, which. You are
always free to ask me. And. I'll figure out what
what answer I'm able to give for these sort of
assessed these sort of assessments.
So now they're seeing or hearing any questions, I
will raise one other quick topic, which only. Seem
to be an issue on on a few submissions, which
noted in the very first part of the first problem
that the.
The most likely step size in this random question
was identical to its in the expectation value of
one. And there were some comments to the effect
that this should always be expected as a general
principle, so.
I think I would want to.
Pull. Those of you here, see?
What you all think about the conditions under
which the mean of a probability distribution is
this most likely value.
Where we saw in the in the homework problem that
that both of those were AMURO equals one was
trouble with value, X equals one. See if that is
something generic or only results from particular
conditions.
So I'll pause for a minute or two. To give you a
chance to think about and respond to that, and I
see.
Questions in the chat on.
Yeah, so while we while you are thinking about the
question, I can just correct one statement in the
chat that the mean scores were actually not so bad
on the assignment's. The mean for the first part
of the computer project was sixty five, which is
toward the upper end of the interval, I'm told I'm
supposed to target in the UK system in the mean
for the homework assignment was fifty five, which
as at the the lower end of that bracket, both,
both pretty much right on target for. For the for
the module and in the U.K. system, so. I don't
think there's any reason to panic, and of course,
there were some scores much better than than those
averages, as I said, the most of the marks were
lost from.
From emitting answers to two questions, skipping
those rather than doing things incorrectly, so.
I think for the most part, we are in good shape to
to meet all the learning outcomes and of course,
if you are having any difficulties, that's what
I'm here for during the office hours and
asynchronous communication.
The issue with canvas is I think there are several
students who are still registered on the canvas
sites but have either withdrawn from this
particular module or from cities as a whole. One
of them is just a test student. So there are
multiple non submissions that canvas is
incorrectly averaging over, I think, in the
numbers that you are looking at. So that is always
going to to pull things down.
And let's see.
We have some responses coming in to. The question
here.
In a way, just another minute to see if any more
consideration is needed for those of you still.
Thinking about. This.
This question.
Taking a look at the. Responses, if I can get to
them. There is an even split between saying that
we need to compute things on a case by case basis
and the. Choice that there is.
Only agreement between the mean, the most likely
value when the distribution is symmetric. And. I
put in that that response be thinking in advance,
that's. It would be a tempting option, but it's
true that the mean is is not always the most
likely value. We actually saw an example of that
in the computer project demonstration, which.
Which I won't bother to bring up since nobody.
Selected either either of a or or response, see
where in the in the demo for the computer project,
we looked at a monotonic distribution where the
mean and the most likely value were not the same.
And if I hop over to a whiteboard here quickly, I
want to show off a counterexample for a
probability distribution that.
Has a.
Is the following form where I won't bother to
compute the constant that comes out over overall,
but I will say that the probability distribution
is the sine squared of X for X from minus Pi to Pi
in zero otherwise. So that if we. You know, that
probability distribution, that the constant factor
C can come from.
With a smaller line width that can be fixed by
requiring that. The integral over the probability
distribution equals one across this, its whole
range and.
Plotting this distribution, we know that the.
The sign of high and minus pi is zero. There's
been a maximum of sine squared at both plus and
minus PI over two and the sine I don't know why it
spontaneously zoomed out like that as I tried to
draw things, but. Plot four P of X vs. X from
minus Pi to Pi then takes the form. Of that,
which we can see has. You mean value, so that's X,
the integral from minus play pie of.
X times square root of X X, which is an odd
function over an even range around zero, so that
mean value is right at zero there. So that's the
the mean, whereas there are actually two
degenerate most likely values which come when. The
derivative of the probability distribution is set
to zero and check to be a maximum rather than a
minimum. And those most likely values are at plus
and minus pi over two rather than. That's me value
zero, even though the probability distribution is
symmetric around zero and around, it's me. So the.
The ultimate answer to this poll is that both the
mean and the most likely value would have to be
computed and compared on a case by case basis, one
of them corresponds to that integral over the
probability distribution of of X, whereas the
other corresponds to setting the derivative of the
probability distribution to zero and then checking
to see whether we have a maximum or a minimum.
So that is all that I was going to.
Talk about in terms of the assessment and
assignments of the computer project due tomorrow
and the D homework solutions here where the
feedback came back over break. Well, maybe one
last thing I can mention quickly was in the
High-temperature expansion for the last problem,
there were at least some difficulties. Converting
between.
The.
These two forms of. Asymptotic expansion's in
terms of expanding a function in the denominator
of a ratio and getting that into the the standard
form for an asthmatic expansion, where this these
higher powers of the small expansion parameter
show up as additive factors rather than appearing.
Underneath or in the in the denominator of Horatio?
And there are one example here, which is a
standard
expansion that you can look up in in tables of of
series or through Mathematica or programs like
that. Where in order to.
Expand this ratio in the usual geometric series
approach, we have to get it into the form of one
over one minus something small and then expanding
those that something small in the geometric series
allows us to rearrange things in terms of. The
powers of the. The expansion parameter X that
appear, and perhaps the key here is that the
manipulation is necessary in order to get things
into the geometric series form, bring out this
overall factor of one over X that comes along for
the ride. And affects. What what order has to be
retained within the geometric series expansion? So
that once is once the powers of the exchange
operator are knocked down by this overall factor,
we end up with the given asymptotic behavior. So
what we have at the end in this case is a series
rather than a Taylor series with negative powers
of the expansion Parameter X appearing as well as
positive powers. Apart from that, it's a matter of.
Keeping track of the terms that appear in these
expressions and organizing them. In terms of the
small expansion parameter X, which has been a
times here. And. Looking now at the.
The secret is material for.
The coming week will one last check to see if
there are questions about assessment or the
computer project.
And feel free to interrupt as. I go on, I think it
would be. Useful due to the break over the past
few weeks, just to. Take a quick look back at what
we did before that break in terms of introducing
and defining and developing the three statistical
ensembles that that formed the.
This is the spine or the skeleton, the core of
this module, where over the next few weeks we will
be applying the last of those grand canonical
ensemble in the.
Context of quantum gases that we will develop
later this week so that there are some solid
concepts there, which we may get to today, may
save until Thursday.
In the meantime, we will.
Take a few minutes for review to put those three
ensembles right next to each other in.
In a row here, starting with.
The MicroCon conical ensemble and the canonical
ensemble and finally the. Grand economical
ensemble. So in all three cases we have.
In mind that a physical system is evolving in time
and as it evolves.
It is probabilistically sampling all of the
possible states that are accessible to it's
subject to certain constraints, and in the micro
canonical case, those constraints are the very
direct physical laws that energy and particle
number need to be conserved. So if we draw our
system and zoom back in,
we draw our system as. Some box we can even
imagine, that box has a bowling and V in which we
have.
Whatever. Particles for other constituents, we are
interested in
the energy. In particle number are fixed, which
means that this system we're describing with the
micro conical ensemble has to be completely
isolated from all the rest of the universe. So
there is some Hardwell around it through which no
particles to pass and through which, in fact, no
energy can pass in order to ensure that both
energy and particle number remain fixed. So this
is sort of
a straightforward application of the sort of
conservation laws that play an important role in
physics, but it is something that's hard to to set
up in practice developing. A an experimental setup
or or a situation where some system is completely
isolated from everything around it and that
difficulty motivates. The consideration of the
economical ensemble.
Where we still have our system. In some boxes
flying V.. With that same fixed number of
particles. Or whatever other constituents are in
there, but now we allow the energy to fluctuate.
By. Exchange of energy with. Some external system
that. We. Imagine to be significantly larger than
than the system of interest in this takes the form.
Of a thermal reservoir.
That has enough degrees of freedom. That it can
fix the the temperature through. Contact them
through exchange of energy. Between the system of
interest in its selling container, fixing the
particle number and the overall thermal energy, I
perhaps should have mentioned the micro canonical
context that the temperature was a derived
quantity as a function of entropy, as a function
of energy. The interview is always a derived
quantity and all of these cases. And now when we
go to the canonical ensemble. Where the NRC is
allowed to fluctuate the. Expectation value of
that energy. Becomes a derived quantity that is a
function now of the fixed temperature being fixed
by that thermal reservoir.
In the final case that. Was introduced in the week
before break and will be our subject going forward
is.
The so-called grand canonical ensemble where
the pattern set by. The. Evolution from
microeconomics is economical to continues now
instead of fixing either E or N, we allow both the
energy and particle number to fluctuate. So I'll
draw a
container here that does not look so solid and
allows both energy and particle number or energy
and particles to flow freely into and out of the
system. And again, the temperature is fixed
through energy exchange with a large external
reservoir. And now we also fix the chemical
potential move through through that exchange of
particles with that large external reservoir.
Which is now. Not merely a thermal reservoir, but
also a. Critical reservoir.
And it is possible for both energy. And particles
to be interchanged between the system and its
surroundings, making now the expectation value for
the particle. No, he derived quantity. That
depends both on the temperature and on that
chemical potential. So here are.
Those three cases all next to each other, showing
the sort of systematic variation in terms of what
quantities are kept fixed and how.
So that is the the context for. Week seven and the
following few weeks about the application of the
grand canonical ensemble in the context of quantum
statistics. Where?
The starting point now, well, the other ingredient,
in addition to the definition of the great
Kilmichael ensemble that we got before the break
is what exactly are.
Our quantum statistics and how do they differ from
the classical or non quantum statistics that we
have been looking at?
You know, the context picture again, is there.
And you know, this is being recorded, so it will.
Show up on on that recording.
And I'll leave it up as I may be introduced to the
last little Cole, I will. Bring up today, which I
can introduce.
Perhaps speaking out loud for a few minutes before
writing anything that someone said we'll see with
quantum statistics, is that.
The quantization of the energies of the particles
in the system is a necessary but not sufficient
condition to. To get to quantum statistics, to
have a system that is described by by quantum
physics and to reiterate, you don't need to know
anything about quantum physics coming into this
module and there won't be any instruction or
information in quantum mechanics coming out of it.
So this is basically just developing a set of
conjectures to introduce interesting statistical
systems that we can analyze with the tools that we
have available. One of which we we actually looked
at back in week, for which I will cut back to now
and be in the material we.
When we were considering an ideal gas, we saw that
we had to quantize the momentum of the gas
particles and therefore their energies that that
depend on those momentum in order to get a
well-defined canonical partition function as a sum
over accountable number of microstates. So there
was a quick computation that. With these. Quantize
energy with these quantize momenta. The overall
energies were some. Constant, every factor that
depends on.
The the length or the the volume that we assume
are particles are in. And then the moments are
just.
Integer.
Just to sum over integer value, K, X, Y and. OK, Z,
take values zero, one, two, and so on, with every
factor taking those pure numbers caved into
physical momentum, mental units of. Mass times
velocity and. Looking at. Those energies we saw
that the lowest energy levels. Were.
Or I should say the lowest energies and.
The form of that concept, refactored times, either
zero or one or two, which.
Should be able to look at in the next fall that
I'll activate.
And, you know, there's a typo there that the.
There's a typo in what I did before earlier, sorry
that I left out the two times m factor in the
energies that I can.
Quickly restore, that is why I write these things
down ahead of time, and the question here is has
to do with the terminology introduced at the.
Start of the written material for this week, which
distinguishes between energy levels and the actual
value of the energy that any given energy level
has. And in particular, there's a possibly
confusing aspect of that terminology, that it is
possible to have multiple distinct energy levels
that all have the identical value of the energy
which. Is actually something we saw back in the
case of the classical ideal gas and before.
And. Question here is a quick reminder of our
discussion from back then asking what were the
agenda races for the.
The three lowest energy, so how many different
energy levels are there at all have the same value
of the energy?
There's just a few minutes left in.
In the meeting today, so.
I will give you those few minutes to. To think
about and recall, that's a derivation from week
four that I just reviewed and. I can bring that
back up rather than showing the the question that
you can look at yourselves.
Is pausing the final couple of minutes to.
To see what you find for.
For the DeGeneres's corresponding to these
entities.
And in the interests of of time and running out of
time, this will be the last call for
four responses.
And.
And since I see disagreements in those. Responses,
an even split between two of the options. I'll
just go through and. Quickly sketch out the the
answer to that which we did look at in some
previous meeting that is recorded somewhere, but
you all for responses noted that there was only a
single way to get zero energy out of this
expression, which was that all of X, Y and Z had
to equal.
Zero. In order for the energy to vanish, for the
energy e one, they have a single unit of that
prefecture. We just need one of those. Case to be
won while the others are zero, there are three
ways of managing that.
And similarly for.
To get two units of energy, we need to case to be
one while the last one is zero. And there are
again three ways of. Setting that up.
So.
The point of this exercise is just to serve as a
reminder, something we saw earlier, that there are.
Multiple possible distinct states in typical
systems that can all have the same energy. And
that is the justification and motivation for the.
Terminology or the syntax that is introduced here,
where the energy levels are labeled by these
calligraphic ès and those are what are actually
being counted and just revised or quantized in the
case of quantum statistics, and the actual value
of the energy for each energy level may well be
the same for multiple distinct energy levels,
which is the case in the example that we already
saw before the break. So I will stop there. I'll
stick around for just a couple of minutes in case
there are quick last minute questions. Then I'll
I'll need to shut down the meeting to extract the
recording.
And.
I see one question came in after I shut down the
office hours will start at the top of the hour.
There will definitely be past exam papers. The one
from last year should already be up. I will
investigate why it is not. And then a second one
will come up over the next couple of weeks. So
sorry for that oversight, I thought. The 20/20
sample exam was already available, and it will get
up as soon as possible. So thanks for pointing
that out and all of you take care with the the
rest of your day and the resumption of term.