OK, I'll get the recording underway for today.
A small crowd early in Liverpool on a rather bright
Monday morning to keep that shade closed or rather
I should probably just share the screen to hop
over to
getting started with some
quick logistical topics, and unless more people
show up in the next few minutes, we'll probably
just leave the usual input for. Questions or other
feedback from those of you who are on here
synchronously?
Rather than going through a lot of polls, the same
number of folks, you can just feel free to speak
up instead through. Zoom out of the chat window or
out loud and to give you a few minutes for any
initial immediate questions about. Things that are
on your mind or have come up before in the past
meetings mentioned that there have been some not
necessarily logistical updates, but logistical
elaborations since our last meeting where there is.
Posted now there are posted, detailed instructions
for the final exam, which should also now be on
the calendar for.
Or on the module through canvas, so no need to go
through those. Now you can read them offline, but.
You get in touch, if anything seems problematic in
terms of the scheduling or other aspects of those
instructions, which I imagine are pretty standard
for all of your molecule's.
And a quick check is. Not showing any immediate
questions, so we can pick up where we. Left off
last week, and I think with today and Thursday,
you might be mixing together a bit of the material
from week 10 and 11. But starting with looking at
some of the.
The reason that the easy model has been so widely
used and so successful as a model for everything
from neural networks to feral magnetism, and that
has to do with the.
The phase transition that it exhibits as a
consequence of having these interactions between
nearest neighbor spins on this type cubic lattice
that defines that some over an interstate repair.
So you went through all of that last week? I won't
reiterate it unless there are questions about it.
But instead, just point out the door to limits
where we can make some reasonable approximations
and analytic pen and paper solutions to this
partition function that's in full generality
involves the sum over all possible microstates in
this case, all possible configurations of these
spin's pointing either up or down where there's
set in the external magnetic field, two to zero.
For the time being, there will be no distinction
between up and down in a symmetry between those
two directions. And generally that sum with a tiny
system here of about a thousand spins, we have
about ten to the power. Three hundred ten terms
counting all of the terms in the exponential as
well as all the exponential in the sum over spin
configurations, which is not something that can be
solved in full generality, at least in more than
two dimensions. What we can do is consider a
simplified limit. Of either high or low
temperature, which is exactly what we did back in
week reality, that was looking at the. Entropy and
internal energy for systems of distinguishable
spins like we have here in the latter, as well as
indistinguishable spins in a gas where the
individual spins, can't be. Distinguished from
each other and saw that. In both the low and high
temperature limits in the not on track, in case we
had an exact expression that we were able to
expand in a tower series in some small quantity,
but for looking at just the phases of the system,
the qualitatively different ways that these
collections of degrees of freedom can behave
depending on the control parameter of the
temperature with no magnetic field, we can just
focus our attention on the the very leading term,
the some limit for the partition function, which
when we have infinite temperature, that equals
zero. That partition function just becomes the sum
over all of those spin configurations of the two
Beita times, something finite. Which would be
desirable is just going to be to the zero, so a
factor of one seemed over to to the end times. So
as mentioned here, this is exactly what we had, I
think, in week two for this system, in the micro
canonical setting with energy equals to zero.
Every spin configuration appears with an equal
probability if it has to be won over the total
number of microstates in order for all of those
probabilities to add up to one condition on.
What it means to be a probability.
And.
Here, where it seems as though the energy is now
invisible compared to the very high temperatures
that we have, that's motivation to introduce
another way of describing and categorizing these
systems to the magnetization, which is just the
difference between the number of appointing spins,
minus the number of downvoting spins. Divided by
the renormalize by the total number of spins to
get some equality between zero and one, and the
reason for the absolute value sign here is to.
Distinguish between. Cases where. We might have a
large number of. Know when we are doing the
ensemble average, looking at the expectation value,
because there is that symmetry between appointing
spins and down to that expense with that vanishing
magnetic field. The. If if we did not have an
absolute value that ensemble average defining the
expectation value would sum over equal
contributions from, say, all of the spins pointing
up or all of the spins pointing down. And that
would give obviously equal and opposite
manifestations without that absolute value sign,
which in the expectation value that some with an
equal probability would simply. Vanish. So, you
know, we'll see. That's the expectation value is
necessary in order for this quantity to.
Very concretely distinguish between the two phases
in the first phase that we're looking at here, the
high temperature of things is distinguished by an
equal probability for every microbe state that we
just arrived and. The expectation values then are
going to be controlled by the multiplicity of any
given any given macro state and given the
distribution of spins into these upward pointing
or downward pointing sets that give different
contributions to that magnetization. So if all the
microstates are equally weighted, then.
The probability of landing in any of those
microstates is just given, by the way, the
probability of picking up a particular number of
upward pointing or down reporting spins is just
the number of possibilities out of out of the
total number and of the systems that we choose,
say, and plus of them to be pointing up, which is
just the usual binomial factor that's been popping
up all term and for large numbers of spins, even
for. You tiny systems of tens or hundreds of spins.
This binomial factor is. Dominantly peaks right
around the sort of midpoints where we are choosing
roughly half of the spin's to be pointing up and
half of them to be pointing down, there's a
factorial preference for that setting, which when?
The number of upward in now reporting spins is
approximately equal, we end up with a
magnetization from their difference that is
approximately zero and in fact goes to zero in the
limit of an infinite number of spins. That's
called the thermodynamic limit, where all the
approximations that we would be making for a
finite number of spins becomes become formally
exact. When we have that infinite number, it no
longer becomes. A. An approximate equality between
upward in our brain spins, but actually the exact
equivalents in that sort of damage limit.
So the magnetization is going to zero in debt
limit of high temperatures. And not surprisingly,
it does something difference in the limit of low
temperatures. Which is.
I'm just debating whether or not to make this a
poll, so we have probably not enough people to.
It's really make that worthwhile. You want to.
Consider or see how the.
Low temperature. Limit behaves for the easy model.
And in this case, we have.
Low temperatures, correspondence, large penis, so
that the.
Partition function, which I. Have right here an
equation one 19, the negative signs in the energy
cancel out. So as beta gets larger, the
exponential factors in this partition function are
themselves becoming exponentially large so that
only the the lowest possible energies coming from
these nearest neighbor payers on our simplistic
lattice are going to dominate the system in this
low temperature limit.
And I suppose I will.
You know.
Do a quick check in with what is this ground state
energy on the page that we are currently looking
at, page one twenty.
Seeing that. The.
The probabilities now are no longer equal for all
microstates, but depend on the energy we have to
determine the the ground set energy policy and
that it will really dominate over the the first
excited state in this limit of of low temperatures.
And from that.
We'll be able to. Reach a conclusion or
approximation about the behavior of the
magnetization and the characteristics of this
phase.
And.
Like.
Had some issues with getting this whole activated
or deactivated, but it should now be running and I
see at least one response so far away, just a. A
little bit longer for.
Any further responses since it is still a small
crowd today?
And it's probably. Time just to quickly check out
what we have for that ground state energy.
When there's some disagreement between. The two
options are both involve the dimensionality, these
times, the number of sites and in the.
Way to.
Resolve that that balance would be to.
Note that.
The. The minimum energy is coming when.
All of these products have nearest neighbor spins
are they are either plus or minus one, depending
on whether those spins are aligned with each other
or a. a line in the aligned case. They're both
plus one and square the positive one where they're
both minus one square positive one. Whereas in the
Anticline case, one is positive, one is negative
in the overall product is negative. So with the
negative sign out front, you want all of these
nearest neighbor appears to be aligned and all
contributing a. Plus one in the sun, that becomes
a negative one with an overall negative sign. And
then gives us that smallest or most negative
possible value of that energy. In particular sum
over all those nearest neighbor pairs of plus or
minus one square. Which is then just counting the
number of nearest neighbor pairs that we. Figured
out last week was the number of sites, times D,
the dimensionality where that simple cubic lattice
every site has. Our nearest neighbours, both
forward and backward in each of the dimensions. So
the groups already switched back to that open.
Input for any questions that you want to send in
anonymously rather than through Tsou. These times
and is the the lowest energy corresponding to that
ground state that we define. You know, I believe
week three and then. You need to consider both the
first extended to energy as well as the number of.
Micro states that all have the.
The degenerate energy level corresponding either
to the underground state or the first excited
state, so the ground that there are two. And he
generously of two, four of.
The different ways that all of the spins can be
aligned, either all pointing up or all pointing
down.
In the.
First, excited state corresponds to taking one of
the and spins in our system and flipping it so
that the.
Ground state energy that we had now is increased
by all of the links that.
Are connected to the site that was just flipped or
perhaps a more.
Thorough or direct way of going about this would
be to recognize that we're getting that same
contribution of a negative one from all of the
spin pairs that continue to be aligned, which is
all of those deeds and sites except for the. To do
links that are connected to the site that was
flipped and those Tuti links instead are
contributing with a positive sign to the energy.
So just rearranging the slightly the first excited
state energy. Is.
These times in dimensionality.
Minus four times the dimensionality, the. Which is
indeed a less negative energy than the.
The ground states by. That factor of four times
the dimensionality.
So. As the temperature. Becomes small. This energy
does not depend on the temperature and there will
be there for a constant exponential factor arising
from precisely that, for the difference between
the energy gap that we find earlier between the
ground, say, the first excited state there at the
same time be impossible spins that can be Flip's.
There will be two and microstates that all have
that first. Excited state energy level.
In the magnetization for each of those microstates
is. Very nearly the maximum magnetization, one
coming from the ground states with just this one
over and correction. So two competing effects of
end, both more micro states that can pull the
magnetization away from its maximum. But at the
same time, each of those microstates is pulling
only a one over and factor further away. So the
conclusion then is that as this bita. Is
sufficiently large. In the low temperature limit,
so just looking at the TotEx rather than the the
correction terms in a in an expansion in a small
parameter. The ground state will always dominate
the magnetization and we end up with that
expectation value approximately one and
approaching one in the thermodynamic limit of a
large number of.
Of Spin's.
And.
Another way of appreciating this is just to rather
than doing detailed mathematics, just to look at
pictures of.
Of how these. Source of microstates and the
different phases can. Can be distinguished from
each other and look different from each other.
Let's see if I'm able to draw in in this program
where. These pictures are all coming from one of
the textbooks in that list of references at the
start of the larger material, Dan Schroder's
introduction to thermal physics. This is the
representation of. Microstates of the easing model
in two dimensions, so just on a two dimensional
square. Where, say, the upward pointing spins are
being colored white down front spins are being
colored black and in each of these. Different
squares in this nine by nine grid, we're looking
at a.
Representative microstates from one of the
numerical calculations that was described in the
in the week 11 notes or kind of jumping around and
looking at numerical simulation of the using model
at the same time as we discuss the high and low
temperature limits where there are analytic
approximations that we can make. And. The top left
picture here, what's called the initial state,
which is where. These simulations are being
started because that is completely random, it
corresponds to selecting one of the microstates
with an equal probability for all the microstates.
So this is what we would get in that limit of T.
Going to infinitely high temperature. And it's
looking across that whole that whole first row
where the temperature is relatively large.
We see that I there's not too. Much difference,
not very different behavior in the sort of
microstates that that we are seeing if we jump
ahead to the bottom row. Where the temperature is
one one and a half or two relatively small can see
that in this case. Most of the spin's want to be
aligned with each other. Exactly the order phase
that we were talking about just now, where the
ground state of all of the is being aligned
becomes exponentially more likely as this
temperature T goes to zero. So at the bottom
center plot. There is.
The microchip there, which has only two spins,
pointing in in one of the two directions to light
colored spins and almost all of the spins colored
black awning in a single direction is pretty close
to the the ground state that we were getting.
Analytically, as an approximation, I should have
said at the start that these systems are, if you
count them, they're 20 by 20 lattices in two
dimensions, only four hundred sites. And. At the
very lowest temperature case shown here, t equals
one might look a bit surprising at first sight.
And what's really happened there is that the
temperature is so low that.
The.
It's an artifact of the Metropolis Rosenblatt's
teller algorithm that was used to produce these
these pictures where starting from a random
initial state, it can become exponentially slow to
reach the ground state if the temperature gets too
low. And that is because in order, what we see in
this lowest temperature flat is a roughly equal
balance between the number of upper 20 expands,
the number of downward spins all in separate
blocks with periodic boundary conditions sort of
wrapping around the top to the bottom. So there's
only a single light colored block. There and also
wrapping around each of the sides, creating that
tourists, so each of those white and black regions
is just a single region. And in order for one of
the to degenerate ground states to be chosen.
It would have to be one by one, the algorithm
would have to flip each of these.
Say WACHT spins to make them black, which becomes
exponentially hard when you have that one isolated.
Leks been up there, there's a very large
probability that that Laxton will want to be
flipped back to whites so that essentially we have
to separate Gladys's, each of them aligned. In.
Their own direction and the interface between them
can no longer change through this important
sampling algorithm just because the probability of
flipping a spin on the boundary is exponentially
suppressed.
So we can. Get even. A. A more detailed view of
what's going on here by. Looking at live some of
the sorts of simulations that you know of which
these are snapshots, maybe before I switch to that,
I'll just.
Say a little bit about the intermediate
temperatures, say this time around, two point five
in the center right. Figure here, something
interesting is going on on that while there is
still lots of domains of. White and in black since
and see the compared to the very high temperature
microstates shown above it, the domains where all
the spins are aligned are steadily growing. And
there's actually at the critical temperature,
which is where this four by 400 micro state
picture was taken and actually turn out to be
domain's of spin's, of all different sizes with
equal probability, lots of phenomenon that's
called percolation, where we can see if we look in
here and.
Turn on the Pentagon, there are small domain's of
black, just a few spins there, larger domain's and
obviously this big large I here that is mostly
black
is the sort of intermediate behavior that we get
in between the high-temperature with it where
there are. Very rapid fluctuations between up and
down pointing stands and the low temperature limit,
where there are few, if any, changes in the. In
the spin orientation.
Now, the.
I was doing the prelude for some of these videos,
which hopefully will come through in Zoome where?
These are this putting together a stream of the
snapshots at a fixed temperature.
Starting from one particular orientation now using
the colors, yellow and blue rather than black and
white, but showing in this case, this is for a
high temperature, how as we. Go through the system
with the Petropolis results, tell our algorithm
and propose. Spin flips with some probability that
a lot of those continue to happen, and I should
also say that this calculation or the simulation
is being done in a non-zero background field, that.
I believe is oriented in the in the yellow
direction, so that. At very high temperatures that
are there's a high temperature compared to that
exterminated field, you would not be able to.
To see how much effect of the electromagnetic
field, but if we look at. Low temperatures. Then
you're starting even from that all blue
microstates.
Even with the magnetic field encouraging alignment
in the yellow direction, it is hard for. Spins to
be flipped to that yellow direction, there's an
exponential penalty coming from the interaction
term with that low temperature. But eventually, a
few domains are able to form and start growing and
inside those domains.
There is. Contribution or the preferred
contribution to the energy from both having the
spins aligned, as well as having the alignment
with that yellow pointing external magnetic field
so that as.
The domain's slowly spread in the course of this
simulation. They are able to grow faster and
faster until they dominate everything and it
becomes exponentially unlikely for any spins to be
flipped backward to. So the blue orientation.
So I think in just a few more seconds, this last
two blue domains will be swallowed by the low
temperature order to phase that.
Is the the only ground state in the presence of
this external magnetic field and.
The try wasn't. Toward the end.
Where we can see what the order face looks like,
looks like in. Contrast to the disordered phase. A
shot of the very high temperatures with it at
intermediate temperatures, we see that
intermediate behavior with. Larger domains that
still aren't able to. Spread all the way across
this Latisse. But are distinct from both that
ordered phase of the low temperature limit as well
as the. High-temperature phase where there are
more random fluctuations from site to site.
And as this just continues to run for its final
few seconds,
I'll just make the point that comes up in the week
11 notes that.
Even in. The you know, these small systems, I
think the number of lattice points here is only
something like three thousand.
Points, but there would be far more microstates
than could possibly be. Computed in the in the age
of the universe. So what we have to do is. Sample
with some sarcastic randomness, the way that was
done on the computer project with with the random
walks.
Use pseudo random numbers to sample a very
vanishingly small subset of the possible
microstates with the
selection of the microstates. Organized in such a
way that the important microstates are captured
and. Reliable, robust. Measurements for the
expectation value with controlled uncertainties
can be obtained.
And.
See, there are two topics we could go into at this
point, the
field approximation or more about numerical
simulations. You're welcome to. And whatever we
don't do today, we can save for Thursday. We can
also do a bit of. Overview of the entire module.
If that would be useful,
maybe something
fun to do in. The. The last bit here. Would be to
just look at the even simpler. Montecarlo
calculation that comes up in this week, letter
notes. Where?
I link to. A little python code now is already
open in this window. Just about
ten lines of code or so. That. Can be used to.
Compute some approximation to PI by. Randomly
sampling with an equal probability. All of the
points in this two by two integration domain,
counting the fraction that fall within the unit
disk.
Where the fraction is just proportional to the
areas of the disc.
Compared to the area. The square, which is.
Tires squared with that are is one.
Here it is, divided by two, by two is four. So
that. Multiplying that fraction by four gives
estimates for pie on line 18 here, that will
become more and more accurate as the number of
samples increases. So let me see if I can. Try to
run this quickly.
In a python read executed Prince Loopt. Um.
And already in the first couple of seconds, we
have tests of up one hundred, up to a million
samples, which is able to compute PI to a few
decimal points, three point one four and. Yeah,
even on.
Even running on my laptop, which is much faster
than going over the cloud here, the the billion
samples takes about. Ten minutes to run, so it's
going to
zoom in on the results there.
Not going to finish properly running. On the cloud
like this, I should say that the updated version
of the the Python code that is in the repository
leaked from the notes.
Does a bit of a trick breaking up these in
different samples into someone to get back to the
current version rather than.
That older. Copy break up that these a number of
samples into 20 different sets and use the the
standard deviation.
Of estimates from each of those 20 cents to.
Determine the statistical uncertainty that is
coming from this finite number of samples. So if I
copy this slightly larger and more elaborate code
that's now 20 lines rather than 10.
And zoom back out.
Paste that in there and see.
That we need. Another library imported.
There's a warning there that would come up on my
laptop, but
see that in addition to.
The same estimates that we were getting, three
point one for a change, we have some. Estimate for
the uncertainty coming from the finite number of
samples, which leaves all of these results
consistent with the answer that we know three
point one four one five nine two six five, four
and so on,
but gradually shrinks as the number of samples
increases. And in particular, we can confirm here
the square root.
Conversions that I believe is is mentioned in the
lecture notes.
Where I believe that just as an empirical
observation at this level, I can see that going
from.
Say the thousand samples or the uncertainty was
point to you, three up to 100000 samples, the
uncertainty, so the total number of samples
increased by a factor of one hundred. The
uncertainty decreased by a factor of the square
root of 100, which is ten. It is now point zero to
six at another factor of one hundred more samples,
up to ten million lives. Another factor of ten
reduction in the uncertainty to zero zero to four.
And. I guess on the one hand, that is nice, that
it's systematically improvable and controllable
uncertainties appearing in these. Monte Carlo
Calculation's.
On the other hand, it's. Now, the square root
convergence is relatively slow, and it means that
for every. Extra decimal place in PI that we want
to determine in this way, we would have to
increase the the scale of the calculation by
another factor of a hundred and so on. The cloud
here, it's already taking two minutes just to do
one hundred million samples, giving now three
significant figures after the decimal point three
point one four one. And. I guess that makes it
clear is the illustration, this is not the way
that you actually compute pi to to many decimal
places. So.
And takes us pretty much to the end, it's the last
call for any questions coming in through Zoome or.
For people everywhere and we have been. The easy
model phase transition to look into in more detail
on Thursday, along with any final module review
that may be requested. I will just wrap up with
that today.
In one question did come through before I stopped
recording the structure of the exam, so it's the.
Should be. The same sort of structure that came up
in the first term exams in January, I do believe
it's a one hour time on task, there will be
several problems for you to complete. I think it's
not giving anything away to say that it will be
one of those exams where all of the the problems
are to be attempted
and they will all count toward the the ultimate
mark. So when our time on task with another hour
after that, to make sure that any issues coming
from uploading or submitting the exam can be dealt
with and. A great deal more information about
those sorts of logistics in these instructions, so
if that was not the information that you wanted me
to. To comment on let me know.
Otherwise, I will.
Wrap up the recording for today.