OK, the recording should be under way. Let's get going
with the final stretch for statistical physics now
that we are in May and diving into the the last
significant topic for the module, which is
interacting systems, but before I before we get
into that, let me pull up the usual
invitation for any questions that any of you may
have about. The material so far in the. In the
module either this week or previous weeks.
And.
As well, any.
Questions about other aspects of the module.
There's not too much logistics to deal with
anymore. The exam is coming up in about three
weeks on catching up with the marking that'll get
back to you
all next week, hopefully. Definitely has to be, do,
will be or definitely has to be done well before
the exam happens. And then it is just.
You know, going through exam preparation with some
additional sample questions and solutions being
provided in the last couple of weeks worth of
material on interacting statistical systems and
their broader applications.
And I'm just pausing for a moment to see if there
are any questions at the outset, which at any time
be free to. And they're hoping that poll or. Just
bring up. And zoom out loud or in the chat window.
Not seeing any so far, I will. Charge ahead with
the. The week 10 material, which is.
Taking what's really a significant step, that kind
of setting up. All of our work for.
Broader applications in the ways that this could
be built on in many directions where, as I've said
before, during the the bulk of the module, the
previous nine weeks, we've been making one
particular simplification in all of our work that
has been very significant. And that has been the
assumption that when we deal with these
statistical systems that consist of a large number
of underlying constituents, we have made the
assumption or the approximation that those
constituents do not interact with each other in
any significant way. And this is
this is the ideal part of the ideal gas that we
introduced all the way back in week four and was
also the future of, say, spin systems considered
even prior to that, where what this has allowed us
to do in both the classical and quantum context is
basically break up the overall calculation of
these 10 to the power of twenty three or however
many particles into just a single calculation for
a single particle to start interacting with the
others. And then we just essentially raise that to
the ten to the twenty three power. What I just
described is classical approach, but we saw that a
similar sort of factorization also occurs for the
quantum approach of considering energy levels and
occupation numbers rather than individual
particles, where in non interacting settings we
just end up with either a sum or a product over
those possible energy levels, depending on whether
we're considering the partition function or its
logarithm, the free energy.
And while we were able to do a lot of things with
monitoring systems ranging from heat engines to
the spectrum of heat and light from the sun and
from the cosmic microwave background, as well as
the Fairbury pressure that keeps. All stars from
collapsing in on themselves, there are. At least
some things that do require the kinds of
interactions that we encounter in. In our everyday
life where we don't simply pass through. All of
the materials that are able to touch them and
interact with them and the the class of examples
that is focused on. In. In this week and in this
module, the general is the phenomenon of phase
transitions where statistical systems that are
built up of exactly the same constituents. Behave
and qualitatively different ways, depending on.
How those constituents are interacting with each
other or the control parameters that we can adjust
in these in the system are an experiment to.
To verify or to to control the behavior of these
constituents, and the classic example is the
behavior of of water, which can exist in the
phases of the gas, a steam, just liquid water and
various sorts of solid ice. There are if you dig
into the details, there are many different phases
of of water, of H2O molecules that depend on
control parameters like the the temperature and
the pressure, things that. That can be controlled
in experiments or in just everyday settings. But,
of course, that that's the familiar example, but
these transitions are really. All around it, if
you if you start to look for them from the
earliest microseconds of the universe where. The
elementary particles that existed in a confined
plasma shortly after the Big Bang underwent a
phase transition to form the so-called confined
neutrons and protons that we are built out of in
the modern day, as well as all sorts of
solid-state or magnetic systems where the typical
transition is between insulating and conducting
phases that.
Determine whether or not the electrons in these
materials are able to.
To propagate freely or if they are bound and tied
to particular atoms or molecules. The example
mentioned in the notes here is that a transition
to a superconducting phase where not only can the
electrons propagate, they actually propagate
without any resistance or without friction. They
don't lose any energy to heat. And this occurs in
many sorts of so-called superconducting materials
at low temperature. The one pictured here is two
layers of graphene that are stacked on top of each
other and misaligned by a small angle theta where?
Through some sort of remarkable effects, all
related to the interactions between the particles
in the system, superconductivity only sets in when
this angle theta takes a particular magic value.
About about one degree. So.
I should say, just as a brief supplement, that
there is.
At least one case in which you can't have a phase
transition without interactions between the
constituents of a statistical system, and that is
in the context of both sides on conversation that
we talked about maybe 10 days ago, wrapping up the
week, eight materials where.
The the gas of those islands that. Or the ideal
gas, I should specify, of not attracting bosun's,
the sort of thing that would be considered in the
special case of fermions necessary in such a case
of photons, zero mass ultra relativistic particles.
That is a particular phase. Of a collection of
boatswain's, and as the temperature decreases, we
looked at just the video illustration without
doing the mathematics, seeing that there is a
transition to a new phase of matter, the Bose
Einstein condensate. Where? There is still no
interaction between the the individual, those
islands in the SCAS, but due to quantum effects
and the competition between those quantum effects
and the thermal effects of the temperature, even
these not interact, those can undergo a phase
transition from that ideal gas to that quantum
Bose Einstein condensate phase. But in general, as
a rule, these transitions and many other sorts of
interesting behavior depend on the interactions
between the particles in our our systems and to do
things mathematically and concretely. This week we
will look at the two state spin systems that we
introduced all the way back in week two and three
in the non interacting setting, where in that case
the energy was just given by how these individual
spins as coupled to an external magnetic field of
strength h which I believe should be drawn. On the
next page here and in week three, we went through.
Some of the different setups that we can have,
even in the simple system, whether the spins are
fixed into a a solid framework or whether they're
allowed to to move about freely is a gas.
And seeing the effect that the corresponding
information we had had on the thermodynamics or
the statistical predictions for those two
different cases where the spins were able to move
freely as a gas, we could not distinguish between
them and had less information. About the the
system and therefore of observe to different
behavior in its derived quantities, the entropy,
in the internal energy. Or the interacting system
will focus just on the case of distinguishable
spins that are distinguished by having a fixed
position in some regular grid, that.
I'm going to call a Allardice
and. Basically, what allowed us is at the broadest
level. Is a way of. Positioning or spacing, the.
The particles that the degrees of freedom more
generally that make up the. The statistical system
in question. I'm trying to be as general as
possible here without specifying too many things,
which we will go on to specialize too. We have
some.
Regular grid of locations in space where those
degrees of freedom are located in that have an
effect on how those degrees of freedom interact
with each other. So to start now specializing in
becoming more specific and more concrete for
actual calculations, say that will work only with
simple cubic lattices, possibly in an arbitrary
number of dimensions where the the system of spins
placed in a line. Was precisely the the
distinguishable case that we considered all the
way back in week three in the not interacting
setting to. To look at the entropy and energy and
the effects of information on those systems. So
what's pictured here is a. You two dimensional
lattice with. For spins in one direction, in four
spins in another, so overall, a four by four site
Latisse or Inequal 16, the individual spins
labeled by their location in each of those two
dimensions. And take values, depending on their
orientation, aligned with or aligned against this
extraordinary field H.
And.
The place to start to make things concrete and
mathematical is to more formally define. What
exactly is meant by.
By an interaction or by a non interacting system.
Which we can do by considering what happens to.
The internal energy. When we change, when we pick
out some degree of freedom and change it. So in a
not in tracking system where that degree of
freedom is not interacting with any of the other
degrees of freedom and should therefore know
nothing about them, we would expect the resulting
change in the total energy of the system from
changing that degree of freedom to label by. I
expect that change to be independent of every
other degree of freedom labeled by K. That is not
equal to I. And it's easy to see for the the not
interacting spin system that we looked at before
if we break up. The sum over all of the spins that
couples to the external magnetic field to pick out
whatever spin, whatever degree of freedom we are
changing, there's only one possible change we can
make in a two state spin system, which is simply
reversing the orientation of that spin with
respect to the magnetic field or in other words,
changing inside. And when they do that, the sign
of that speed changes. All of the other spins are
unaffected, and if we take the difference between
the the final energy and the starting energy, we
end up with those summations over all the other
spins cancelling out. And all that's left is a
simple function that depends. Only on the spin
that was changed, so. The
formal definition of a not a tracking system
checks out in a straightforward way for that case,
and now we can change the set up of the spin
system by introducing a. A new term in the energy,
so in this equation, when 18, the second term is
exactly what we had before back in weeks, two and
three each spin coupling to that external magnetic
field. And to that we add.
This initial term, which has a product of two
spins and Jane in a funny label at the bottom of
the station sign. This is in parentheses labeling
those two spins that appear in this quadratic
product. And what this notation means is that. We
are considering.
Indices I enjoy that run over all of the the
nearest neighbors in the simple cubicle, a
structure that we have defined. So if we hop back
up to this two dimensional case and consider some
particular spin, say that one that I just circled,
its nearest neighbors are in this case, the the
four things that are a constant distance away from
it, both to the left and right, as well as up and
down. In this two dimensional lattice, so the.
For this. Particular spin circled in blue, that
first term in the new energy equation 118 is
something over the. The four products of. This
term with all of its four nearest neighbors and
then doing the same for all of the other students
in the lattice without any double counting. So if
we hop over to consider the Spinto the rights of
the one that we circled, we've already accounted
for its interaction with its nearest neighbor to
the left. So that is that term in this sum is
accounted for
and.
See, since there is. A smaller crowd, I'll skip
the the polls everywhere and just stop.
Go through the the confirmation that this new term
in the energy does indeed produce an interacting
system.
Just by doing the same sort of procedure is for
the non in case in this box.
Where we can start by writing down. The energy
with the particular lights then pulled out and
isolated, so just changed the notation to some
over the nearest neighbor, here's J and K
specifying that those are only the pairs that do
not contain that spin, ie that has been changed.
Thus the product S.J České. There is an.
The term with the external magnetic field, as
usual, Sunday over. All the spins, except. The
spin I and then we have the contributions from
that spin I, we have the terms over all of its
nearest neighbors. So those sites, they were by
KABE. We're case in the set of nearest neighbors,
I think. So this is all of the terms that were not
included in that first summation.
So all of the nearest neighbor payers have now
been accounted for and all that's left is the
coupling of spin eye to that external magnetic
field. And when we negate the spin. The first two
terms don't involve spin any longer, they are
unchanged.
And in the. Last two terms.
The sign.
Is simply. Loopt. So as K and minus. HCI, so the
difference is.
A factor of two. This sum over. All of the nearest
neighbors of the site that we have changed.
And then the same coupling to the external
magnetic field that we had an unattractive case
and because these české are different than they
are, the nearest neighbors are the. That was
changed as opposed to. Being that that site.
We see that.
This indicates we are indeed dealing with an
interacting system. Is desire.
Maybe a. Simpler way to keep track of things.
Equivalent to talking about all of those nearest
neighbors and the nearest neighbor, Pear's, is to.
Introduce a bit more terminology for these simple
Kubic Gladys's in any number of dimensions where
we can sort of introduce elementary one and two
and three dimensional.
Unit objects that the the overall lattice system
itself is or can be considered as being built out
of.
So rather than drawing up and down, pointing
arrows to to represent the spin degrees of freedom
in these systems. It's conventional just to to
denote the locations of those spins by some black
dot. Where the figure on the right here, the the
shading of the data is being used to indicate the
the third dimension.
The idea that the the lighter the dogs get, the
farther into the page, the third dimension has
progressed, it's. About as best as you can do,
representing three dimensions in. The two
dimensional page that we're looking at here. And.
In addition to those dots at which the the spins
or the more general degrees of freedom are are
going to want to live in V dimensions, we can
connect the nearest neighbors and only the nearest
neighbors by drawing lines between them that
become known as or have become known as links. And
these are sort of the elementary objects that
appear in that first term of the energy we were
looking at.
This first term of the box here is really a sum
over the links, whereas the second term that we
had before is the sum over the individual sites.
So the links are essentially representing the
interaction between these nearest neighbor pairs.
In the interacting system we have set up and, you
know, going further three dimensions is sort of
the most that we can have in the world that we
live in. But mathematically, we can define
lattices in any number of dimensions, because you
mentioned that the two dimensional system, we
could experimentally realized by doing experiments
with a thin film of degrees of freedom. On the top
of some table and even reduce that to a one
dimensional lattice, a simple chain of spins. But
as we go into higher dimensions, there are
analogous elementary unit objects known as
Phuket's and cubes, one of which is drawn here
with the cat being the elementary unit of surface
area and the cube being an elementary unit of
volume once we hit three dimensions.
And one of the wrinkle that. You might have to
worry about in these latter systems is what
happens if we reach the edge of the lattice and
there's no longer. Any more sites for. For our
spins to.
To share a link with or to have a have an
interaction with. There are various options, one
of which is the formal mathematical level, just to
consider an infinite lattice that goes off forever
in every direction.
And we can also just say that the lattice ends, we
can chop off any of the links that go out from the
edge of that lattice, but the mathematically most
convenient way to handle this sort of thing is to
impose. What are called boundary conditions in a
particular imposing periodic boundary conditions
where we identify the in this case, the leftmost
site in the lattice as the the nearest neighbor.
Link of the nearest neighbor site of the rightmost
site so that the link connecting them.
Is just another standard link, like any other link
in the Latisse, so there's a constant distance
between. The. The sites here at the. Right, edge
of the lattice that. Circles around to talk to the
side at the left edge, it's just as far away as it
is from the. The other nearest neighbor in the
other direction, and at least in one dimension,
this is easy to to represents by
bending this chain of sites around into a circle
where. We can see that or see the reason this
periodic boundary condition set up is convenient,
because now every single spin or every single site
is on. On the same footing with the same number of
nearest neighbors, you don't have to worry about
where exactly it is located in the lattice or to
put this in a more mathematical freezing. There is
a discrete translation cemetery where, well, in
the case of writing the drawing, the ladies in the
circle, that translation would be called the
rotation of the sites going around here. Where? If
we would rotate the circle by an angle of two pi
over and over and is the number of sites that we
have, then the resulting lattice would be exactly
the same as the starting points. Which is what I
mean when I say there's a symmetry and we can so
it is harder to visualize this sort of.
Bending around in higher dimensions, but
mathematically what it corresponds to is. Placing
this simple cubic lattice with a constant fixed
distance between every point and all of its
nearest neighbors in all the dimensions that that
setup gets placed on a dimensional Taurus. So. The
two dimensional Taurus is probably what you think
of when you hear the word Taurus. I neglected to.
Pull up a picture of that.
I'm sure you've seen it before, it is essentially
the doughnut shape and in higher dimensions, you
simply have dimensional territory or hyper Tauri
that share the same property of being
typologically flat spaces with no curvature. So
that there's no complication with having this
simple Kubic Latisse living in this toroidal
structure that allows it to to wrap around
periodically.
And then the. The calculation of how many nearest
neighbors there are in the interacting energy that
we have to dealing with becomes a very simple and
very regular calculation.
Where no independence of the number of dimensions
we can see based on the pictures we've been
looking at in the general discussions around it,
that every site in every dimension. He has a link
connecting it to its nearest neighbor, both in the
forward orientation, in that dimension and the
backward orientation, so.
For every site, there are two times the number of
dimensions. Links connected to it are coming out
of it. So in this one dimensional case, we just
have the two links that connect to that site
circled in blue.
And. Similarly, if we had other dimensions in
which we could move, we would have the four
backward left, right up, down pairs of legs for
each of those,
but each of these links that are attached to each
site are also attached to another site. So.
Every link is essentially shared. Between.
To. Different sites, so to avoid overcounting. We
have to combine both of those facts to consider
that the total number of links is that two D for
each site and then that counts each link twice
from each of the sites that it connects to. So
correcting for that gives just these times and
links in these dimensions. And I'll try to
remember to put little dots in the in the middle
of that sort of expression just so it doesn't look
like a differential factor. But an actual product
between the number of dimensions and the number of
sites, so that is how many terms there are in this
sum over the nearest thing, repairs that we've
been able to recast as a sum over links in the
system. Is known as the the easy model, these
dimension's. Which has.
Now, really a fascinating history that. I've said
a bit about in in the text here, but.
It really, especially over the past half century
or so, it's become one of the foundational. Tools
in. No, not merely statistical physics, but. Very
many branches of mathematical sciences and even
fields of research beyond the physical sciences
like sociology and in biology. As a an extremely
simple system that due to. It's interactive nature.
Exhibits and can be used to model a very a vast
array of of different behaviors. So the where the
model was invented not by this easy fellow, but by
the guy named Lence, who was actually using his
PhD supervisor and Lence.
Came up with this model of. Of spins that can have
only two orientations and interact only with their
nearest neighbors and some regular Latisse
motivated by trying to explain the phenomenon of
feral magnetism. Which is one of those phase
transitions that I got mentioned earlier towards
the start of today, where?
As temperatures decrease for certain metals, they
pick up a an overall magnetization.
In the. No one had in mind with this model was
that the the spin's he was considering were the.
The individual magnetization of each individual
atom or molecule that composed this particular
ferromagnetic material,
iron being, I guess, the paradigmatic example,
which is what the Fero Charlamagne magnetism means,
I'm curious materials involving iron ore from
Latin. And the idea was that.
In one phase of these. Atoms in this lattice.
They're a. They're magnetization their spins would
all align in the same direction, adding up to the
overall large scale magnetization that had been
observed experimentally, whereas there may be some
other phase. Where? The the spins were pointing
all in different directions.
Leading to an overall cancellation of their
contributions to the magnetization Rich. Was
testing whether that was the case, was the project
that he assigned to students using whose solution
to the one dimensional system rather than the
three dimensions that that lens was originally
interested in, define that one dimensional using
model. And has turned out to be enormously
difficult to. To generalize to higher numbers of
dimensions.
And.
So what easing did was come up with an exact
expression, reclose for expression, for the
canonical position function of this simple model
with that energy from equation 118 in one
dimension.
And the two dimensional. A case. In the special
case for that, external magnetic field was exactly
vanishing, was not solved for another 20 years
until. This fellow named Morrisson Singer and
eventual Nobel laureate carried out a. Famously
difficult calculation that. You know, it really is
one of the most famous calculations of 20th
century mathematical physics and sort of up there
on the scale of the equals and C squared in the.
In the physics community, if not in popular
consciousness, it was a remarkable achievement to
exactly solve. Even this very simple two
dimensional model, which is maybe the key points
to.
To wrap up with today, maybe will make things a
bit short today and pick up next week with.
Looking at the phases of the easing phase,
transition between them, where the sorts of
numerical simulations that will be included in the
week 11 material can play a useful role. But in
terms of. Of mathematically or analytically
solving this interacting spin system, the easy
model.
We can see that. Now that we no longer have the
ability to consider each individual spent in
isolation, not interacting with any of the others.
We can no longer factories or break up the
calculation into just repeating that simple one
spin calculation over and over and over again, we
have to keep track of all in spins at once. And
the precision function then depends on every
possible microstates that is defined by every
possible orientation of all of those and spins,
each of which can be either up or down. So a total
of to the end terms. In this.
There's some overlapping configurations that
defines the partition function, which grows
exponentially quickly. So if we. If we back off
from our goal of thinking about ten to the power
funny three particles that are in everyday
materials and think about just say No. Thousand
twenty three spin's. In this song that is is
written here on this page, there are something
like 10 to the. 310 power. Terms where I'm
breaking up these summations in the exponential to
count the total number of terms that would have to
be computed in order to really evaluate this
function, either mathematically or analytically or
by a numerical calculation. And those numerical
calculations. They turn out to be.
Of great utility in more than two dimensions where
there is no known exact solution to the U.S. model
in three or any larger number of dimensions,
except for the infinite dimensional limit, which
is somewhat of a mathematical curiosity. What were
you even mean by an infinite number of dimensions?
But there is. Yeah, as we will see next week, an
enormous amount of work using all sorts of tools
at the cutting edge of water research even to
evaluate interaction systems like the using model,
let alone the more complicated variants that we
could consider describing or consider defining,
say, by allowing the ideal gasses that we've
worked with to have particles that interact with
each other or by generalizing these things to
degrees of freedom that can take continuously
value or continuous values, maybe having a
continuous length or continuous orientation rather
than being simply plus one for an opposing spin or
minus one for a down 20 spin. So I'll wrap up with
maybe that key point that interactive systems are
enormously difficult to handle mathematically and
there are whole fields of of mathematics that.
Worked on just this question and now we'll see
next week wrapping up the module, how the
statistical tools, the statistical ensembles, the
partition function, the free energy canonical
degree and canonical micro canonical ensembles can
all be brought to bear even in these more
complicated settings of interactive systems.
So the one last call for immediate questions,
we've asked for office hours later on today after
saving this recording and shutting down the
meeting. This is the good place to stop, I think,
for today.