OK, that recording should be under way and we'll
get set up with the usual logistical notes and
the chance in the chat window to
Have any input on the direction that those of you
who are here live, want this last session to go.
So if there are a couple of. Directions that we
could go today, one being. Circling back to the
weekend stuff on the Medfield approximation that
sort of skipped over on Monday in favor of talking
about numerical Montecarlo calculations, the other
main thrust would be an overall review of. Of the
past 11 weeks, the volatile material with an eye
toward the final assessment coming up. And I think
if there are no strong preference is expressed
through Zob or that way everywhere, I would
probably go through them in that order. Touching
on the bean field approximation as the last major
components of the.
The material that has not really been discussed in
much depth in previous synchronous sessions while.
You have that opportunity to. Make your feelings
felt, can you give a few more logistical notes,
first of which being that the second part of the
computer project is now finally graded and that
should have gotten back to you about 10 hours ago.
And as always, no guarantee that I've done that
working perfectly. So feel free to get in touch
with me if you think I've. Made any mistakes by
going through it, either in your submission was
marked or the general solutions, I think in
general folks had a much easier time with this
parts than with the first part, probably
benefiting from the experience and model of how
that that first thought went. So there were not
really any very widespread and significant issues
that I noticed while going through things. The
solutions are up on the canvass sites and in the
usual place. So let me know if you have any
trouble finding those as well. The second homework
assignment is now what's being marked and that
should go more quickly without having to hop back
and forth between PDF submissions and code files
that should be wrapped up over the weekend and.
I guess there will be no more synchronous sessions
after that to provide general feedback if there
are big issues on the record and upload a little
supplementary video. But I will say that at the
end of the regular term schedule, at the end of
this week, I won't be doing office hours at the
usual time, the hour after each of these
synchronous sessions, but will be available by
appointment and asynchronously throughout the
assessment period. If there are questions about
that upcoming homework assignment being returned
or anything else in the module as a whole.
And, you know, just for the sake of recording a
couple of the. Questions and answers that came up
at the end of the previous session after I believe
the recording had already stopped the. Question
was that whether the final assessment would cover
the entire module or just the the portion of it
that.
It was not covered by those previous work
assignments, and the answer is that the entire
module is fair game to show up on that final
assessment. There are few enough questions that
not every aspect of it can be covered, but what is
covered can be drawn from any week in the term.
That said, there will not be any programming
component to the final assessment that all got
wrapped up just about a month ago with the end of
the computer project.
And not seeing or hearing any. Strong demands for.
What to to look at today? Just keep that. Pull up
and running in the background and check in on it
on occasion, and as always, you're welcome to
unmuted what questions and comments in the chat
window I will hop over to. Actually, the the last
bit of the week, 10 material that got skipped over
on Monday in favor of numerical methods, looking
at the Manfield approximation and also the.
Related issue that I think. Also got a little bit
shortchanged for lack of time, which is what?
Really rigorously and mathematically defines a
phase transition as opposed to just some
difference between the behavior of the system in
different regions of its control parameters. So we
did see previously that looking at the using model
as the simplest possible interacting theory in the
high and low temperature limits that we could
solve the very leading order, asymptotic behavior
with analytic approximations. Or we could carry
out numerical calculations, both of which
distinguish between two distinct types of behavior,
two different phases analogous to, say, the liquid
phase of water in the solid phase of ice. Both may
not have the same substance, but behaving
qualitatively differently in the easy model are a
parameter, just like the melting or freezing of
water is the temperature of the system or the
inverse temperature data. And at high temperatures,
we saw that the system is disordered and. Roughly
half of the spin's are pointing in each of the two
directions that they can point out in the absence
of an external magnetic field and there's sort of
no pattern or no large scale organization between
determining which direction spins or pointing it
is randomly decided for each thing. And we have. I
guess just as a quick reminder,
can pull up. This again, and look at the high
temperature limit where.
Each square here corresponds to a spin color,
black or white, for pointing up or down and at
high temperatures.
It's not the one that I want.
Circle this high temperature limit. Here, where
there's no large scale pattern in the orientation
of the stands, which is a disordered array of of
up and down 40 degrees of freedom and in low
temperatures, things are. Qualitatively different.
With all of the spins preferring to. Align in an
ordered rather than a disordered phase where these
two faces are distinguished. By the magnetization,
the difference between the number of appointing
and down appointing spins, which vanishes in the
disordered phase and is non-zero and it approaches
its maximum one in that order phase. So this
magnetization here is playing the role of a
parameter that tells us whether the system is
ordered or disordered, and because that sort of
order disorder behavior is fairly generic in a
large number of statistical systems, this
magnetization can be generalized or it serves as
an example of a more general concept of order
parameter, which, as it says on the tin, is a
parameter that tells us whether the system is
ordered or disordered in a phase transition is.
Formally defined by the presence of a
discontinuity. In this order parameter or.
Any of its derivatives? And this is. A. A way of
categorizing and defining these transitions as
opposed to a gradual, continuous crossover's. That
was developed around the mid 20th century by.
Two Russian physicist Lev Landow and Ginzberg
think the first name is Vitaly Ginzberg, but can't
quite recall. But it's the Ginzberg paradigm where
there is an order parameter that distinguishes
between these phases in a phase, transition is
present. If that were a parameter or its
derivatives have a discontinuity. And the the
points in the case of the easy model, the
temperature at which the discontinuity occurs, is
known as the critical points or more specifically,
the critical temperature. We can imagine systems
where there are multiple different control
parameters that we could have to play with, we
could adjust the pressure of the volume, the
external magnetic field, and in that
multidimensional parameter space, there could well
be one or more different points where our order
parameter exhibits this sort of discontinuity,
transitioning between different phases. So the
critical point is a more general concept that
specializes to the critical temperature in the
zero field easing model in the classification or
categorization that was developed by Orlando. And
Ginsburg was to say that when the order parameter
itself has a a finite jump, a discontinuity at
that critical point which is drawn in this right
hand plot in the form of the dotted line, we call
that a first order phase transition or a
discontinuous phase transition where the order
parameter OPIS
jumps all of a sudden from its non-zero value in
the ordered phase to zero value in the disordered
phase, which of course implies. Similar
divergences in discontinuities in the derivatives
of this this sort of parameter, but it's also
possible for the order parameter to be continuous
at the phase transition, but to transition from
having a non-zero value to having a zero value
going from one place to another with a kink
where the first derivative exhibits a divergence.
And.
Not to spoil things, I think we already looked at
this last time that this so-called second order or
continuous phase transition is what the using
model exhibits in. Two or more dimensions where?
And in the two dimensional case, the make the
order parameter, which is the.
The magnetization that we've been talking about is
proportional to. The square root of the distance
away from that critical temperature. Whereas if
you take the first derivative, so obviously that
square roots is, in fact what is drawn in this
plot, it is a continuous function.
At that critical temperature where it goes from
that square independence to just being zero. But
if we look at the first derivative instead of the
square root, we end up with one over that square
root, which diverges as the quantity in
parentheses goes to zero as he approaches TCE from
below. And. We can get a grip on. These
transitions by. Trying to simplify these
interactive theories in some way, so we saw that
there were simplifications very far from that
phase transition.
Once we get to temperatures that are very much
larger than the critical temperature, we're very
much smaller than the critical temperature and we
are solidly we can identify that we are solidly in
one or the other of those phases and extract some
of the leading asymptotic behavior, neglecting
higher order terms and some small parameter.
Both of those expansions are going to break down
around the phase transitions to something a bit
more clever has to be done to look at the phase
transition dynamics in themselves. And this
Medfield approximation that.
Was what we skipped over last time is. Another
fairly generically applicable method that can be
applied not only to the easy model, but to all
sorts of interacting systems of which the using
model is a or the simplest possible example. And
the way this proceeds is to sort of reorganise the.
The energy that defines the U.S. model and its
interaction, so we're still defining everything on
this simple cubic lattice in these dimensions and
just by adding and subtracting a expectation value
for the magnetization which. We've done a quick
derivation here to relate that to the average
spend. Which as a.
As a sum over all of the microstates in in the
definition of the expectation value, this
expectation value of the magnetization is
independent of any particular spin or spin
configuration. It is simply a function of the
control parameters, beta and H. Which we turn back
on to a non-zero. External fuel strength.
For the purpose of this exercise, so by adding and
subtracting that constant value for a particular.
Value of these control parameters, we can express
the overall energy of the U.S. model with a slight
change of design conventions to get things to line
up with the previous sections. Sorry for that
inconsistency or that a change in convention
midstream, but we are able to organize things in
terms of the fluctuations of spins about that,
every expectation value of the average
standardization.
Now.
Obviously, for the easy model where these spins
can take only the values plus or minus one.
Any individual term here, even expressed in this
way is going to be fluctuating in some way or it's
going to be exhibiting large fluctuations, no
matter what the mechanization is, it cannot be
close to both plus one and minus one
simultaneously. However, on average, when we
insert this quantity into the sum over all the
nearest neighbor pairs that are represented by the
links in the simple cubic model, the average
fluctuations we can conjecture are. A relatively
small it could be neglected in the specific
context of that, some of our nearest neighbor
repairs, and that leads to this minefield
approximation to the energy which. Is not or has
not yet been justified. This is simply a. I guess
sort of conjecture that this sort of.
Approximation is valid and applicable that the
fluctuations are small on average then. What we
end up with is a system with a constant value, a
constant contribution to the energy coming from
that expectation, value of the magnetization
squared minus just the sum of our spins coupled to
a a modified external field. That depends on the
speed value of the spin. So this terminology of
Medfield approximation is something that arose
historically and can be.
Uses a mnemonic to remember that that's going on,
that an external field has been defined now
depending on that mean value of the average STED.
And.
There's a little box here to go through the
exercise of. Checking whether or not this Medfield
approximation is.
Is giving us an interacting or not a tracking
system, and just by noting that we have a constant
independent of the spin configuration and then the
same energy that we started off with, just with a
different or efficient and effective magnetic
field rather than the. The very magnetic field, we
can just reuse our result from the first
little gap in this week's material and immediately
write down that the change in energy upon changing
the degree of freedom in this case is just going
to be two times now, that effective magnetic field.
Rather than the bare magnetic field that we
started off with, so the only change is swapping
in an effective field rather than. The original
field, this is.
Independent of all spin's.
Apart from. The the one that got changed, which is
our definition of a non interacting system, so
this is sort of the. Magic of the Medfield
approximation, it is taking us from the
interacting system that is extremely difficult to.
And analytically, since a no longer factor rises
and all of the exponentially many terms in his
partition function have to be considered in in
full detail, the mean field approximation is able
to take us from that situation back to a non
interacting system that still know something about
the the dynamics that are due to that interaction.
By virtue of incorporating the.
Resulting magnetization in the effective. Magnetic
field that each of the spins are independently
coupling to. So that I probably should have put in
this material as one of those shaded boxes at the
Medfield approximation is taking us from an
interactive system back to the non interacting
case. But with. Some cleverness built in in that
definition of the non attraction theory to back up
some of the effects of these interactions that
were not able to handle explicitly.
So. Going through and. And plugging in. The the
Medfield approximation of the energy into that
partition function, we again, as we should expect
for a non interacting theory, benefit from the
factorization. That we had just like back in.
In week two or three or four of the previous parts
of the of the module for introducing.
InterAction's and.
By relating the.
The magnetization of the order parameter to. The
resulting Medfield approximation of the petition
function. We can end up with or derive the self
consistency condition.
That basically pulls out the dependence on the
marginalization that has been built into the not
interacting structure of this theory, so I'll
quickly go through how that works rather than
setting it up as a helpful question, given the
size of the audience today, but by identifying
this overall magnetization.
In the partition function, we can. See that the.
Derivative of the Helmholtz free energy, this
minus whatever, Ryvita. Derivative with respect to
the external magnetic field strength. Of the log
of the petition function.
Is. As usual, for the derivative of a log, we pull
out whatever Z expand the partition function in
some overlapping configurations.
And then just have. Derivative of. Better times
that attracting. Term.
Nearest neighbor appears as CSJ. And Peter HSM.
So derivative with respect to H is pulling down
both a beater and an M, so the batter comes out
and cancels that one over batter out front. So
we're just left with that. Whatever, Z.
Some over the span configurations, which are the
microstates. Of the system. That magnetization of
each of those skin configurations and then the
exponential of the same factor as above, which is
just the negative expectation value of that
overall magnetization.
Which is the number of spin's times the man, the
normalized magnetization person, that is our
quarter parameter, which. We're looking at two of
the terms in this equation, we can.
Identify. That's expectation value as this one
over and data that the derivative of the Lord of
the partition function, which is. Just what we had
down there and plugging in that fact arised
Medfield partition function. Gives us the.
Synch overcaution with the factor of. Tuti in plus
H coming from the argument of the of the Coche.
Which depends on. On both the left and right hand
sides of this equation, one twenty four, there is
dependence on the expectation value of the
magnetization on both sides of that equation,
which. Becomes
annoying to solve know, expecting when a cash is
equal to one piece of its argument, but can be.
Analyzed
by considering it a self consistency condition and
simply plotting the the two sides of this equation
as two separate functions and looking for their
intersections, which is equivalent to to looking
for the roots of the difference between those two
factors.
So that's what's exactly what's done over the next
few pages. Just starting off with a reminder of of
what the tension looks like at the at the baseline
where the tension of zero is zero and
asymptotically in. The limit of. It's argument
going to.
Plus or minus infinity, the change approaches plus
or minus one.
In the you know, the horizontal axis here is just
that expectation value of the magnetization. Which.
You might recall that in the easy model, this this
is bounded to be between minus one. And one, when
all of the spins are aligned in either of the two
orientations that they can have. And this is
consistent with the self-consistent condition that
the easing model in this Manfield approximation is
only consistently described when this solid green
curve of the Tange and the straight dotted line of
itself. So Y equals X when those intersect is the
only possible solution, possible description of
the easy model in this Manfield approximation,
which in this case the only intersection is right
here at the origin to the point zero zero. The
things become more interesting when. An external
magnetic field is turned on that simply shifts the
argument of this hyperbolic tangent. The magnetic
field is positive, the attention gets shifted to
the left. When it's negative, it gets shifted to
the right. And we now see that the there is, again,
only one possible self-consistent description of
the using model in this Medfield approximation in
each of these cases. One is the intersection up
here with the positive value. Of the the
magnetization.
The other is the intersection down here with.
Negative value. Of the magnetization and in both
cases, because the tension is bounded by plus or
minus one a vertically and this dotted line is
just. The lion, the lion X equals Y, we know that
this point here. Is MS equals one?
The mechanization equal to its maximum value, and
we can see that. In both of these cases, the only
consistent result is correctly within the.
Allowable domain of values for the magnetization,
which is not a proof that the Medfield
approximation is is actually working for the
system, but at least a
place where it could have failed and could have
given a nonsensical result, but instead it
remained consistent with the constraints that are
built into the structure of the system.
But, of course, when we looked at the at the faces
of using model. We saw that they depended on the
temperature rather than this external magnetic
field, that for simplicity when doing the high and
low temperature approximations, we turned off the
magnetic field to not have to worry about it. So
moving on, we need to look at what happens when
when the temperature varies in the self-consistent,
the condition that we're looking at by. By
flooding these curbs and finding their their
intersections. So this here this spot here is the
same as the one above just with a lower
temperature and.
We double check. You know what exactly the change
was, so the temperature up above was. For in order
to get the know convenient argument of the
hyperbolic tangent here, we have have this and
reduced it down to two, still keeping the nonzero
external magnetic field. And now the the
intersections have shifted much closer to those
maximum values, plus or minus one.
They the plot up here, I mentioned in the notes
that. This magnetization, was it plus or minus
point eight eight, so it's approaching the the
asymptotic low temperature limit where the the
magnetization of one is set by. There was to
degenerate ground states out of the two to the
power nd now possibly 10 to the power, three
hundred or ten of the power of three hundred
million possible states as the temperature gets
lower. Because the tension gets steeper, it
approaches. That ordered limit of. More and more
quickly.
Now confirming that.
The Medfield approximation at low temperatures is
giving us a system in its ordered phase, so that's
another good sanity check of this approximation,
that it is doing something reasonable and
identifying at least
at least the asymptotic phases know we saw at the
intersection at at zero when that external field
was set to zero. We always have the hyperbolic
Tange going through zero and intersecting with the
dotted line at that point. And. Now, for these two
cases of the temperature of four and eight.
With zero external field that.
Disordered. Phase solution. So in. Equals zero
corresponding to the disordered phase. Becomes the
only possibility at those high temperatures, the
the dance becomes for the slope of the dance
around zero becomes so low that it takes hands too
long to approach and Salsinha take value of one.
By the time it gets up there, it's no longer in
the physical domain. Of the using model bounded by
that magnetization within plus and minus one per
normalized for the total number of spins.
So.
We are seeing. Good sanity checks at.
At high temperatures and at low temperatures, at
least in the case of a non-structural field, there
was only this one possible self-consistent
solution coming from the main field approximation
corresponding to the the ordered face value of the
magnetization.
And of plus or minus one. When that field is
turned off and the temperature is low, there is
this interesting behavior that there are actually
three intersections
within the allowable or accessible domain.
For the easy model. One at the the disorder
magnetization were advantages and another at the
two now degenerates. Ordered phase ground states
with with no external field to energetically
prefer one or the other spin orientation, we have,
as always, that equal balance between.
The two degenerate ground states that differ only
by reversing every single spin from spin up,
flipping the spin down and spin down spontaneously
flipping to two point up.
But a little bit of thought. Reveals that in the
slow temperature phase. The solution is zero, even
though it exists is an unstable solution and
unstable root of the difference between these two
curves, which. We can. Figure out just by looking
at graphs of this sort of thinking about them in
the appropriate way. So if we zoom in. To the
origin here, if the tablet responds to that zoom
and we think about what happens if we are not
exactly at that self-consistent point, that
happens to randomly fluctuate just a little bit
off of it. Then for this blue curve at this, the
lowest temperature case, the attention.
Is the blue curve, and it is larger than the
magnetization itself, which I'll just call X for
simplicity. So that is to say, X is too small.
For the system to be self-consistent. And
therefore, you know, any algorithm that we set up
to search for a root of the difference between
these functions would say that, well, if X is too
small, we need to look at. Larger values. Of
course, in order to recover self-consistent seat.
So.
The the set up, the structure of. This this plot
or this route finding routine. Is such that it
pushes the system or the system flows.
Two larger values of X, which take us up. To even
larger values of that hyperbolic tangent, which
are, in fact, even further away, even greater than
X actually increasing the the disagreement and the
violation of consistency. So we keep being pushed
even further to a larger, larger efforts to try to
regain this balance between the. The two curves
whose intersection we're trying to find and we
follow along this curve all the way until we reach
its ordered phase intersection, which is the the
stable route to the stable solution at these low
temperatures when these multiple intersections
exist. So another way of visualizing this is by
plotting the difference itself, again, against
that expectation value of the memorisation and
putting the arrows on here, just as we did above.
Seeing which way the system wants to flow, if it
happens to be displaced from one or another of
these routes where it vanishes.
Probably also something that can be seen by by
taking the the derivative and looking at where
that is minimize or maximize to identify the
stable and unstable solutions or the minimal
maximum of that stability condition. But the
conclusion is that this new approximation is not
only allowing for the possibility of an order
phase at low temperature, but by having that being
the only. Stable solution, it is correctly
identifying.
That there is a transition between the order phase
and the disorder phase as the temperature
increases going from order to low temperature to
disorder at high temperature, and by virtue of
having an exact analytic solution for the
partition function and for the expectation value
of the magnetization. In the form of this tension,
we can then from the bean field approximation, it
is simple enough to get an expression for the. The
critical temperature at which. The stability of
this disordered phase route changes from being
stable at high temperatures to being unstable at
low temperatures, that happens exactly when. The
tension at the origin has the same slope as just
the expectation value Y equals X, which is to say
the the slope of the Tange has to equal one at
that critical temperature. And by expanding the
tension, a series approximation, we can take that
derivative to to define the slope,
it's the derivative and use that variable X again.
Just to.
Reduce the amount that I need to write. Executed
at X equals zero, which is just. Well, the
argument to. PETA claims the dimensionality and
then. Doing the derivative brings down one of
those factors of X, so we only have.
Something that depends on. The magnetization
squared as the next correction, but of course,
when we set that magnetization to zero to look at
the slope in the the relevant intersection between
these curves, then everything that depends on him
is going to drop out. And we have just two better
times of dimensionality equals one or that
critical beat up is whatever to the political
temperature is just to D.
And that turns out to be wrong.
For for the actual interacting easing model, this
is where we see the Medfield approximation
revealing itself to be just an approximation and
not an exact solution of this interacting system
in the in the two dimensional case where an exact
solution is possible. That exact solution predicts
this funny expression for the inverse critical
temperature being a sea of about zero point four
for. Whereas, you know, our prediction of a
critical bit of one over two times two dimensions
is point to five is off by very nearly a factor of
two. So it's the right order of magnitude. So
qualitatively acceptable, but not not a very
reliable guide to that two dimensional case. Just
as a fun historical note,
this two dimensional critical temperature for the
easy model was actually determined exactly even
before the easy model itself was solved
analytically by Einziger in the 1940s.
And that was done through a technique known as
developing by a couple of folks called Kramers and
Vania. They were able to find that the. So Kramers
body found a relation between the behavior of the
easy model in its high and low temperature,
Faison's something that's now it is called Kramers
finding a duality and by requiring that.
This is the this relation be satisfied in both the
high and low temperature phases at the same
temperature. That is the temperature at which both
the high and low temperature phases are
simultaneously valid. You can identify as the
critical temperature and solving the Kramers self
to reality condition produces this. Funny, one
half of a log of one plus square root two, which
was then a consistency check that Oddsmaker was
able to derive from his exact solution of the
using model and in the zero field case. And just
as the last note to. To wrap up today and wrap up
these synchronous sessions, the Medfield
approximation turns out to fail badly in
relatively low numbers of dimensions. The one
dimensional easy model does not show a transition
at all in contrast to the main field approximation.
But the meaningful approximation does become exact
in the sort of formal mathematical limit where
each site has an infinite number of neighbors, or
we have a simple cubic lattice in an infinite
number of dimensions. And the. The qualitative or
conceptual reason for that is because in that case,
each site is interacting with a larger and larger
number of nearest neighbors forward and backward
in every one of those dimensions.
It feels the overall adverse effects of a larger
and larger number of spins so that the the mean
value of the spin that goes into this effective
magnetic field and windfield approximation becomes
more and more like what each spin is seeing by
virtue of its interactions with more and more of
its neighbors. So that is.
Showing the know the limitations of approximations
that allow us to solve this interacting system
approximately by making it not interacting in a
clever or refined way in the.
The regime in which that approximation becomes
more or less reliable, working in a larger or
smaller number of dimensions, I'll wrap up there
with my spiel for today. Shut down the recording
and back for the last round of scheduled office
hours, though, at the individual office, hours can
still be booked by appointment through the
assessment period. And with the end of this
recording to say, I hope you enjoyed. Some of the
statistical physics stuff we were able to to see
this term and good luck with that final assessment
in your preparations for it.