Hello and welcome to statistical physics math
three to seven in the spring term of twenty twenty
one, I am David Schaich, the coordinator for this
module, and I will be coming at you through these
asynchronous recorded videos for the remainder of
the academic year, as well as through synchronous
sessions and indirectly through the lecture notes
being written up for this module as we go along.
So let me in this introductory and logistical
overview video, just provide some commentary about
how this module is going to be delivered, what the
plans are, and what the scope is to change those
plans. If we all decide that they aren't working
as well as they should be, and it might be worth
experimenting with something different. The module
is following the notes driven delivery model that
was developed by by the department over the over
the summer and the previous terms of trying to
incorporate lessons learned from the autumn term
during which I was not delivering any course, any
modules. So this is going to be new territory for
me even compared to to your experience. And in
that notes driven delivery framework, the bulk of
the asynchronous content is coming to you through
typeset notes that I am producing as we go along
in the term and there will just be order. Twenty
minutes of video recordings like this every week,
primarily as far as I'm concerned, to give more of
a human element to the course, especially while we
are not able to meet in person, and especially for
those of you who are not going to be able to join
the synchronous sessions. Speaking of the
synchronous sessions, they are currently and
hopefully finally scheduled for Monday mornings at
nine a.m. and Thursday afternoons at 1:00 p.m. and
I'll have some remote office hours in the hour
immediately following those synchronous sessions
on both of those two days, as well as by
appointment that you can schedule online if those
times don't work for you.
Now, if you're watching this, you've presumably
found it through the canvass site for the course
because that's for the module, since that's the
only place where I expect to upload it. You can
also find there the lecture notes. And I'll just
say a bit about those lecture notes which you can
have in front of you or have already read as you
listen to these recordings, if indeed anyone is
listening to this. The idea that I have with a
roughly 20 minutes of speaking a week is that I
won't go through those lecture notes in detail.
You can read just as well as you can. Listen, I
will instead provide a sort of introductory video
that reviews the big picture, context, motivation
and organizational logic of the topics being
covered each week. Then that should be about ten
minutes long as a reasonably bite sized overview.
And then I will provide a similar roughly ten
minute video covering the big takeaway messages
that hopefully were made clear. As you work
through those lecture notes and I say work through
the lecture notes. And I sort of mean that
literally because these lecture notes have gaps in
them where you were asked some questions or asked
to perform some task in order to complete the
notes. And the action of carrying out that
exercise or answering that question is going to be
the main way that you really learn the material
and are able to apply it to resolve the or
complete the homework problems, homework
assignments and the final assessment that we
discuss in just a few minutes.
And this insight is not just my opinion, it's
coming from the literature on how learning happens
from this book, Make It Stick The Science of
Successful Learning, which is listed among the the
reading list for the module and the additional
resources in the lecture notes. Something that
might be interesting to check out, the take away
message from that is that the the more active the
you're learning is, the more you actually have to
do stuff in practice. The the skills and
information that you're trying to learn, the
faster you will learn it and the longer it will
stick. And the counterexample, which makes the
learning very slow and very transient, very easily
lost, is the more passive, non-active approach of
listening to recordings like this or reading
through those lecture notes. Now, incorporating
these gaps mean that existing lecture notes have
to be refactoring pretty substantially. So I'm
going through that as we proceed through the
course week by week, which also provides some
flexibility to adapt to how the the current
approach is working and how you all are are
finding it and enjoying it. So do feel free to
give me feedback or suggestions about
what changes or what different ways of doing
things you would like to experiment with. And
depending on the time available, we will do all
the experimentation that that we can. This is a
relatively small module and also a relatively new
module. So there is a great deal of scope for
experimentation with its delivery, especially in
these exceptional circumstances. This is only the
second time the module has been offered in its
current form, and it's also the first time that I
am delivering it myself in its entirety. I
assisted as delivery last year coming in just as
the university campus shut down and the existing
lecture notes that we had then designed to be
followed along with during a live in-person
lecture, were all converted to slides for online
synchronous lectures of the sort that the
department decided we should absolutely not do
this year. So second time through the course, the
third delivery style, this hybrid mixture of
asynchronous material, mostly lecture notes
supplemented by these video recordings, plus the
synchronous sessions that I will also try to make
as active as possible. And the way I have in mind
to to do that, at least as a starting point to a
first approximation, is to focus on the gaps and
the gaps in the lecture notes that I just asked
you to to make sure you can fill. We'll look at
those, make sure everyone was able to fill them
successfully, answer any questions that came up
out of them. And if all that proves to be much too
easy, well, that gives me feedback to make the
gaps less trivial in the coming weeks as well as
while we are there in the synchronous sessions, we
can generalize the material go beyond what was
encapsulated in the lecture notes and highlighted
in the video recordings, and look at some of the
further applications of statistical physics.
Before we wrap up talk about the expected
background and assessment, I just want to say
briefly that in the expected course, the expected
schedule for the module that is on the first page
of the lecture notes, you can see a few weeks
focusing on topics in quantum physics. So I want
to emphasize that you do not need any background
in quantum physics to successfully complete this
module. Everything you need from there will be
provided.
And I will also just wrap up by looking at the
assessment we are, you know, in order to make sure
that the both the load of the content you're
expecting to learn as well as the assessment
you're expected to complete, are all reasonable.
We're keeping all of that the same as last year,
just reorganizing everything for this hybrid
remote delivery. We are also changing the weights
of the assessment so that more of the weight is
distributed evenly throughout the term
with deadlines that are centrally scheduled within
the department in an attempt to assure that
there's as little pile up as possible with lots of
things all due at the same time with the variety
of modular combinations. That's possible in years
three and four. This won't be a perfect system,
but it's better than just letting us, US module
coordinators be free to do whatever appeals to us.
So the assignment deadlines we we were assigned
for this module are Tuesdays in weeks, four, six,
seven and nine. And two of those assignments are
simple sort of traditional homework assignments
that will be released at least a week in advance.
The other two are a two part computer based
project where you will do a little bit of
programming to solve some statistical physics
problem that really cannot be very easily handled
with pen and paper techniques. So you're going to
have plenty of time to complete that project. And
it split into two parts to make sure that feedback
from the first part can be returned to you and
used to guide the second part, which may be useful
for those of you without any background in
programming. Background programming also not
assumed all the necessary information will be
provided and you will be free to complete the
project using whichever programming approach you
prefer or that. So I'm going to be focusing on
Python, which is a very widespread very.
Easily accessible free programming language that
is designed to be simple, to start using, starting
from no background in programming at all. I'll be
going through some demos showing all the necessary
programming techniques for the project in Python.
You're also free to use any other approach that
appeals to you that C are even matlab using the
the university site license.
I would advise against PayPal even if you're used
to it, because it may not be sufficient for the
the project that that will be completed, but that
is all something that we can explore in the coming
weeks. So with that, I've gone on more than long
enough on logistical issues. So if anything was
not covered that you want to know about or if you
have any questions that was that were brought up
by the past 10 or 12 minutes, feel free to toss
those into the campus discussion. Contact me
directly by email
or even raise an issue in the repository that is
being used to to develop and release the lecture
notes, which I really should have mentioned before
now. That gives you an opportunity to do a bit of
co creation, point out any issues with the lecture
notes as opposed to issues with the mathematics to
be discussed in the synchronous sessions or the
canvass discussion board and also even make
corrections yourself if you are so inclined,
entirely optional. But another way for you to have
contact with me and with all of the all of your
fellow students taking this module, which I hope
will be both interesting and as enjoyable as
possible in the current circumstances.