Hello and welcome back to the end of week four of
statistical physics, a wrap up video of
summarizing the highlights and learning outcomes
of Idil gases. And with the new screen shared set
up, I'm experimenting with. This week, some of
these key takeaway messages may have been clear to
see as we went through just the introductory
overview in the previous video, I will say
different things about them this time going
through, starting with the assumption that you've
gone through, read the written material and
checked your comprehension with those gaps. The.
The activities put in place just to make sure
everything is falling into place, so in terms of
the definition of ideal, gas is what really
matters here is the definition of the energy. And
all of these adjectives and English is essentially
defined by how we specify the energy and writing
the energy in this form, that there are no
relativistic corrections, there are no
contributions from particle interactions, and
there are no contributions from quantum effects,
really defines what we mean by this non
relativistic classical ideal gas.
And another aspect of the definition of the energy
is the ZATZ reimposed that the momenta are
descriptivist or quantized, which does turn out to
come from quantum mechanics and leads to discrete
values of the energy corresponding to the discrete
moments that are possible in the volume that we
have to define as a place for this ideal gas to be
situated. So even the. Construction of the
partition function from which all the
characteristics of the system are derived depends
on having a finite volume of finite L with the
volume of L cubed. That gives us these quantize
momentum and energy levels here as nonsense in
nature, as an aspect of quantum physics and.
A related aspect is you may you may have picked up
as we went through this derivation of the
partition function, that we first democratized the
energies into discrete energy levels so that we
could do a well-defined sum over microstates. And
then we made the assumption that all those energy
levels were close enough that we could go back to
treating them as continuous and approximates these
sums as continuous integrals. And this here is the
condition that allows us to go back and forth. And
this is another aspect of what it means to have a
classical, non relativistic ideal gas in this
mathematical context. And in particular, we are
making the assumption that the particle masses,
the temperature and all this parameter that
controls the volume of the gas are all large in
units of Planck's constant, which is just a unit
conversion factor that in most fields of physics
just gets set to one here. We keep it explicit to
remind ourselves of the the classical and quantum
limits where this ratio is small or not so small,
respectively. And this also shows up in the
generally wavelength defined to simplify some of
the notation, see that this depends on the.
Critical mass and the temperature, and it shows up
in combination with the volume. So that, say, when
if we jump down to the result that we got from the
partition function for the entropies right here,
we see that the volume over the cube of the
thermal wavelength always show up together and.
As the temperature is very small, the severally
wavelength gets relatively large, and when it
becomes comparable to the linear size of this
volume, l getting the volume L cubed, that is when
this law vanishes. And that is why we have to
start worrying about quantum effects. And a
similar sort of behavior can happen with the
devilly wavelength becoming comparable to the
total volume of the system when the mass similarly
gets very small, or if we turn things around, we
can keep the wavelength fixed and imagine the
volume becoming very small, which will also break
down the. Approximation of classical, non
relativistic ideal gas. So that is how all of
those aspects of the systems we're considering
show up in the mathematics here
and the other aspect that. Was emphasized even in
the overview was the. Effect that the intrinsic
information content of the system had on the
entropy, though not on the average internal energy,
that depending on whether or not the particles
were distinguishable, we would count different
numbers of microstates for a. Particular set of
momentum for the particles. Which in turn led to
both different amounts of entropy and also
different dependence of the entropy on the.
Possibility of particle exchange and the
introduction of additional particles into these
canonical systems.
And. What I glossed over in the overview was the
connection to the so-called Gibbs paradox and how
paradoxes avoided where the Gibbs paradox is.
What you get if you are too quick to use arguments
that assume indistinguishable particles and apply
those to the distinguishable particle case where
we saw in the case of indistinguishable particles,
removing or reinserting the barrier between two
canonical ensembles has no effect. On the system
and in particular, the entropy is simply unchanged
as they go through that process.
When we compute the. Entropy for this case of
distinguishable particles, when we remove the
barrier, double the number of particles and double
the volume of the system, we find this non-zero
mixing entropy. And if we repeat the same argument
that led to this result, we would seem to see the
entropy increasing as we go from the initial set
up to the combined system and then decreasing back
to that final set up at the end once the barrier
is reinserted. And the key is that the.
Distinguishable particles allow us really to
distinguish the micro states that we're starting
off with so that there is only one possible way to
get back to those in. What typically happens is
that the initial microstates are scrambled as the
barrier is removed and reinserted, so we end up
with possibly or quite likely the same number of
particles in each of the final systems, but.
Different particles with different labels as we
remove and reinsert that barrier compared to our
starting position. So the final system can no
longer be identified with the initial one and the
full calculation has to be carried out, which does
end up it's not a calculation that's worth doing
in in this module. In this context, it ends up
being consistent with the second law of
thermodynamics. And the final topic we have is a
physics result that is just as famous as the
second law of thermodynamics and a bit more of a
concrete. Application to physical systems carried
out over the years. This is the ideal gas law that
results from defining the pressure as the
adiabatic change or response of the internal
energy of a system to a change in volume. And this
negative sign here is what we would expect from
everyday experience that say if we decrease the
volume, we squeeze the system, we expect its
energy to increase. There's more stuff being
crammed into a smaller volume. So the overall
change is an increasing numerator, decreasing
denominator. So a negative sign there that cancels
out that overall negative sign and gives the
positive pressure of squeezing a volume. And. Yes,
adiabatic simply means a constant entropy process,
which is related to this particular combination of
the volume and temperature that appear in the
entropy for both the cases of distinguishable and
indistinguishable particles. And. Perhaps the.
Final comment to emphasize here is that as we.
Talk about these adiabatic processes that change
both the volume and the temperature of the system
so as to keep this combination constant and keep
the entropy constant. We can notice that we are
doing a bit out of the bounds of the canonical
ensemble, which started by fixing the temperature
through thermal contact with a large external
thermal reservoir. What we went through last week
here, when we consider processes that are changing
the temperature, we really have in mind that we
are. Moving our system from. Being described in
terms of one canonical ensemble with a particular
initial temperature to a final state, where is
described in terms of a different but related
canonical ensemble with the same number of
particles, but a different volume and different
temperature. So in particular, we take our system
and disconnect its certainly contact with an
existing reservoir at the initial temperature and
reconnect it to a different thermal reservoir with
a different temperature at the end. And in that
process, we also change the volume in order to
keep the entropy constant, ending up with the
ideal gas law of the equation of states describing
how the macro state of the system changes with
this change in temperature and volume, with the
number of particles fixed connecting the pressure
of volume, temperature and number of particles,
and through the definition of the pressure, also
bringing in the internal entropy sorry internal
energy and constant entropy as a function of
volume in that ideal gas law is.
The most famous equation of state out there, that
there is the equation of state being a relation
between these macroscopic parameters and next week
looking at through dynamical cycles, we will take
this equation of state and apply it to do work by
moving heat around or equivalently apply work to
move heat around as a physical application of
statistical physics and the canonical ensemble.