Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
This is the second video for week eight, wrapping
up our brief summary of the context, motivations
and Kilani outcomes of this week's material on
quantum gases of bosun's analyzed in the grand
canonical ensemble. So let's bring up that
material back onto the screen. Picking up where
the previous part of the summary left off at the
grand canonical potential for the photon gas as a
specific realization of a quantum gas of bosons
where the particular protons we consider photons,
particles of light are relativistic and defined by
the frequency of the wavelength of the particles,
the photons that relates how. The energy levels
depend on the quantize momentum in the system and
all of that is to say that's the answer. That's
where the conjecture that we have adopted in the
hopes of gaining a system that would be
interesting to analyze with the statistical tools
that we have developed in the next section is
demonstrating just how interesting those analyses
can be by seeing that the resulting mathematical
model coming from the simple ideal, not
interacting of photons provides really an
excellent description of. Real physical systems in
the universe, ranging from some of the hottest
locations like the surface of the Sun and other
stars to some of the coldest locations in the
universe, the intergalactic voids that are not
quite empty space, but instead permeated by a very
low temperature gas of photons known as the cosmic
microwave background. In the both of those cases,
the information that we have available from
observations that we can.
Compare with the mathematical model we're
developing is measurement through satellites,
observatories, telescopes and other tools,
measurement of how many photons, how much light
arrives with a particular frequency. That is, we
have access to. The integration in this expression
that ends up over all frequencies to the average
energy density for the photon gas. That is being
measured. In practice, frequency by frequency,
by doing a quick calculation through a gap.
We find that the ideal not attracting and gas, the
photons produces this expression for the.
Essentially, the energy density per unit frequency
as a function of that frequency, Omega, which is
known as the Planck spectrum and is shown in this
figure here for three temperatures of a few
thousand Kelvin.
Plotted here versus the wavelength rather than the
frequency. And compared to the classical
prediction for the energy density or in this case,
the the power of light. Which from our work last
week, connecting quantum statistics to the high
temperature of temperature, classical Régine, we
expect to come into agreements in. The high
temperature classical regime where quantum in
classical physics should coincide. A further
calculation.
Allows us to confirm that at high temperatures and
this factor here.
Beta is approximately zero at high temperatures
this. Denominator that cancels out to leading
order and leaves just an overall one over
wavelengths of the fourth dependence in the power
spectrum. This is the classical result plotted up
here that we see agrees with the quantum result at
large wavelengths, which is known as the infrared
regime, but disagrees enormously, in fact,
infinitely in the limit of high energies, short
wavelengths known as the ultraviolet. And this
breakdown between. The classical prediction and
actual observations like that shown in this plot
of the solar radiation that reaches the earth,
which drops down to zero as the wavelength gets
smaller, the ultraviolet, rather than diverging
towards the infinite energy predicted classically
that was known as the ultraviolet catastrophe and
was the motivation for Max Planck more than 100
years ago to heuristically develop the. Spectrum
we are studying that we have now derived from the
first principles of quantum statistics rather than
a heuristic argument and shown as illustrated in
this figure, very good agreement with the real
physical system of the radiation, the light
emitted by our sun. Despite the fact that we have
assumed the particles we are working with are
completely not interacting and.
Do not have any influence on each other, which
could in principle be a severe assumption or
approximation, but turns out to allow a very good
reconstruction or model of the energy density
released by the sun that reaches us here on Earth
and moving from that high temperature regime of
the sun to the cold temperature regime of not
quite empty intergalactic space observations done
more recently by satellites have produced this
sort of picture, which is looking at the full sky.
Using measurements of that same energy spectrum,
the energy density as per unit frequency to define
a temperature point by point in the sky. And then
color small fluctuations about that temperature,
either red or blue, depending on whether they are
hotter or colder than average respectively, where
the scale of fluctuations.
Is on the scale of nearly killed in thousands of
of Kelvyn.
The red regions are about point zero zero zero two
Kelvin, hotter than the cool ones and an example,
reconstruction of that temperature from the
measured photon spectrum is shown here in this
figure that's led to a Nobel Prize 15 years ago
where the energy emitted by that cosmic microwave
background permeating intergalactic space was
measured as a function of frequency, giving the
empty squares here the size of which roughly
indicates fairly cautious estimates of
uncertainties and are fit to precisely the blank
spectrum that we have derived in this module,
predicting in this case a temperature of about two
point seven Kelvin, which was confirmed by
subsequent measurements with the following
generations of satellites. So even though our
derivation of the blank spectrum relied on making
the assumption that. The particles we are working
with are ideal in the sense that they don't
interact with each other. We end up with a truly
excellent mathematical models for these real
physical systems, and these are, of course, not.
Not the only places where our work is applicable
to the real world, similar spectrums of radiation
are coming out of your oven and. Out of everything
else, emitting light and heat and other forms of.
Of radiation. So with that.
With those examples out of the way, we can wrap up
for this week by. Doing a few more quick
calculations based on the technical potential
computing, some of the other large scale
thermodynamic properties of the photon gas from
that fundamental defining quantity and putting
them together to come up with the equation of
states describing the relations between those
those quantities, the fresher, average internal
energy, average particle number and entropy just
in the same way that we did for the canonical
ensemble and the classical non relativistic ideal
gases back before the term break. And all this is
is the the same sort of derivatives of the great
canonical potential.
Being applied to determine the average particle,
no, in addition to the average internal energy
that we looked at.
To determine that blank spectrum, followed by the
entropy and using the entropy and in particular
the condition of constant entropy to determine the
radiation pressure of the photon gas, we can put
everything together. Define the same sort of
relations that we saw in the classical non
relativistic case of an ideal gas, that the
average internal energy is related to the average
particle number of times the temperature that can
be done. Relativistic case equation 50 for this
relation was. A somewhat simpler equals three has
a.. That was a very useful relation when analyzing
it in cycles here, the numerical factor is a bit
more complicated coming from just the details of
how the energy's depend on the quantized momentum.
And the story is similar for the equation of state
relating the pressure volume particle, no
temperature or possibly the energy that just like
the ideal gas law, PV equals A.. We have the same
functional form with just a different numerical
factor in front. So in that sense, the. The
quantum gas of photons is behaving similarly to
the the more familiar, more everyday ideal gases
that we have already considered with.
On the other hand, we look at not the large scale
thermodynamics, but the detailed frequency
dependence of the energies there is. Significant
divergent differences between the classical and
quantum theories in the appropriate low
temperature quantum regimes, and we will see if
anything, even more striking effects next week
when we return to fermions, which exhibit the less
familiar behavior that only a single forensic
particle can occupy any energy level.