OK, welcome back to the second part of this.
Summary of the full week, five asynchronous
material on through a dynamic cycles. Where we'll
just pick up with going through both the context
overview and some of the key learning outcomes to
take away, starting from the third section of the
week's material, which builds on the earlier
definitions of work and heat in the statistical
physics context to produce bona fides over the
dynamic cycles where, again, just to complete that
orientation, we are applying the canonical
ensemble to ideal gases in containers with a
particular volume. So the volume, particle number
and temperature are all controlled parameters of
these systems. So we saw in the previous parts of
the material that. Work is the change in the
internal energy of our ideal gas when its volume
is allowed to change with the entropy being kept
fixed and on the other hand, heat is the
corresponding change of the internal energy when
the entropy is allowed to change with the volume
gets fixed. And now we can generalize to the
situation where everything is allowed to change
both the entropy and the volume. And I'm
expressing that internal energy in terms of the
entropy and volume, inverting the usual relation
between entropy, temperature and volume. We can
quickly write down a leading order multivariable
Taylor expansion, which becomes exact in the limit
of infinitesimal changes. And provides. This
important equation, sixty seven, which is the
generalization of the first law of thermodynamics,
two systems described by the canonical ensemble
that are able to exchange energy with their
surroundings. So while the overall energy of the
universe is conserved, the energy of the system is
able to fluctuate by that energy exchange. It can
fluctuate in two ways by the exchange of heat or
by doing work, either having work done on the
system, by its surroundings or the system itself
doing work on its surroundings
and that change in the energy. Now, in the micro
canonical case, that was zero. In the canonical
case, it has to match the heat, plus the work that
moves energy between the system and its
surroundings. And all together from this week and
last week, we have these four key equations that
allow us to consider a variety of manipulations we
can do to a system of ideal gases by varying the
control parameters, in particular the temperature
and volume. We have relations between the internal
energy and the temperature. The condition for
adiabatic processes or the entropy is constant,
that relates the volume to the temperature, you
have the ideal gas law from last week and now the
first law of thermodynamics connecting the change
in internal energy to heat and work. So. We can
imagine doing many. Different things to the system,
we can compress it, we can expand it, we can do so
isothermal idiomatically, we can heat it up
because of volume or heat it up the constant
pressure. And if we do a lot of those changes, we
can imagine trying to end up after a sequence of
changing the system, ending up back at the
original starting macro states defined by the
pressure, volume, temperature, internal energy and
entropy. And that
generic situation where some sequence of changes
leaves the system back. Where it starts is what is
our definition of the thermodynamic cycle. It is a
cycle because by ending up where it started, that
process can simply be repeated over and over and
over again.
Motivating the. Calling it a cycle, that is what a
cycle does, something same process repeated over
and over and the particular cycles of the
interested in are those that either use heat to
have the system do work on its surroundings, which
is a form of cycle known as an engine. Or
alternately, we can use work to have the system
move heat around its surroundings, providing
refrigerators in an easy or a convenient visual
way of keeping track of these changes. And the
cycles they produce is by plotting them as shown
here in on the axes of the pressure and the volume
of the gas. By the ideal gas law, the pressure and
volume, assuming a fixed number of particles,
which we always do with a with the canonical
ensemble, the pressure, volume and particle number
to find the temperature, the temperature then
gives the internal energy. And the interview
itself is also derived from all of these
controlled parameters, so the plot here is
illustrating the isothermal expansion of, I guess,
where the. Pressure changes as the volume
increases, I've already put in some knowledge that
the pressure decreases as the volume increases.
And that's something that you can work out, and
the line that is produced by changing the volume
at a constant temperature is known as Nisso Thurm
representing that isothermal process. Similarly,
if we change the volume with no change in entropy.
We. Do you expect to see a change in temperature
and it's another? Application of the ideal gas law
and an entropy condition to figure out how the
pressure changes as we change the volume
idiomatically, which produces on these pressure
volume diagrams or PV diagrams, this red curve
known as an idea that.
And to illustrate. Those ideas and how isothermal
native ads and other forms of lines in TV diagrams
can be put together to produce thermodynamic
cycles, you go through in some detail. One of the
most famous thermodynamic cycles there is the
Karno cycle proposed by Saudi Karno in the 20s.
Which is this sequence of isothermal expansion,
followed by adiabatic expansion, followed by
isothermal compression and finally adiabatic
compression. That in principle should allow us to
get back to that starting point, it's not obvious
from looking at the cycle that this will be
possible and that's a calculation we need to go
through.
And. While doing that, it can be useful to keep in
mind this more physical picture. Of those four
processes, isothermal expansion that happened
slowly, it allows heat to come into the system,
followed by adiabatic expansion that happens
quickly with no heat exchange, followed by
isothermal compression that happens slowly,
allowing heat to go out of the system. And finally,
adiabatic compression with no heat exchange. And
one key aspect of the cycle that is generic to
these sorts of thermodynamic cycles for engines
and refrigerators is that we're picturing the
system of an ideal gas in a volume in contact with
two distinct thermal reservoirs with different
temperatures, one with one hot reservoir with the
temperature T h and one cold reservoir with a low
temperature T.L.. And we don't call T. C, so it's
not confused with that particular point, see in
the AP diagram.
So in order to establish that this is a
self-consistent cycle, there's a bit of.
Checking that has to be done to make sure that if
we imagine. Setting up the the system and
expanding it first isothermal and then
idiomatically we have to show that it is
impossible to compress the system in such a way to
get back to the starting points. In other words,
we have to show that the. Parameters that are not
fixed by that proposed set up can all be
consistent with the given input data that are
colored red in this plot. So we have to show that
all the pressures at point speak and in the
unknown volume at D can be chosen in such a way
that the cycle closes, which it does turn out to
do.
Now, given a three week cycle, we can ask, what
does this cycle do in the case of the Karno cycle,
as we presented above, it uses the flow of heat
from the hot reservoir, the cold reservoir, to do
work on the surroundings. And we can illustrate
this by considering the efficiency with which this
work is done, the efficiency being defined as the
the benefit that we get out the network that is
done by the system and surroundings, not counting
the work that the surroundings have to do on the
system in order to get the cycle to close. And
that is then normalized by the cost that has to be
put in to the cycle in order to get this benefits
of the work out. And that cost is just the amount
of input work that has to be fed in from the
reservoir, ignoring any and all waste heat that
gets expelled to the cold reservoir in the course
of each repetition of the cycle
and computing the well.
We can check that this efficiency is a
well-defined ratio for an engine, it is always
positive. We do we assume we do more work than is
required to run the cycle. And by the first law of
thermodynamics, the efficiency can be no no larger
than one. And so this eight of the efficiency is
always between zero and one. So we can interpret
it as the fraction of the input heat that the
engine is able to use to do work on its
surroundings.
If we look at the Curnoe cycle specifically. The
computation of the efficiency breaks up into a
sequence of much smaller little steps, figuring
out the heat that is done by or to the system at
each of the four stages of the cycle and. It is
convenient when doing that to.
You subscripts to keep track of whether the heat
is flowing into or out of the system or the work
is being done on the system by its surroundings,
were being done by the system on its surroundings,
rather than trying to keep track of all the
negative signs. That correspond to heat and work
flowing in and out in the definitions earlier on.
So all of these.
Input and output, heat and work are defined to be
positive quantities and going around each of the
four cycles and computing them in some cases we
know right off the bat the first antibiotic cycle.
There's no heat flow. We can quickly combine all
of those small results and find a famous result
for the efficiency of the Kado cycle, that is one
minus the ratio of the. Of the temperatures, of
the cold versus hot reservoirs. So since the cold
reservoir is colder than the hot reservoir, we
confirm that the efficiency is always positive.
And as the hot reservoir becomes infinitely hotter
than the cold reservoir, this ratio vanishes and
the efficiency approaches one the theoretical
maximum allowed by the first law of thermodynamics.
In fact, the.
The results here for the efficiency of the cardio
cycle efficiency of one minus the temperature
ratio turns out to be the maximum possible
efficiency that any fellin anemic engine can
attain. And that is a consequence of the second
law of thermodynamics, which relates those
temperatures to the. Or at least the efficient,
the efficiency and the flow of heat to the entropy
that comes into the system from the hot reservoir
is expelled by the system into the cold reservoir.
So after each repetition of the cycle, entropy has
moved from the hot reservoir into the system and
then been expelled to the cold reservoir and the
second law of thermodynamics says that in that
process, the entropy cannot decrease. It may be
constant, but generically increases, which means
that the efficiency can be at most one minus the
temperature ratio and is generally less than that
for any thermodynamic engine. So you can freeze
this to say that the first law of thermodynamics
by imposing the maximum of Ayda equals one means
that a a thermodynamic engine can never win. It
can never get out more work than energy was put in
in the form of heat. While the second law is
saying that you can't even break even for any
finite temperatures of the hot and cold reservoir,
the maximum possible efficiency is always strictly
less than one. Some amount of energy is lost to
the production of entropy, and the amount of work
that can be done is always less than the amount of
heat that is put in to the system. And if we were
to run the kind of cycle in reverse, we would have
hopping back up to the diagram here.
We would have heat coming into the system during
the isothermal expansion connected to the low
temperature reservoir. And then we would expel
heat into the high-temperature reservoir by
compressing.
The system in connection to the hot reservoir and
work would be required to do that, moving heat
from someplace cold to someplace hot and operating
as a refrigerator. Again, the cycle is the. Most
efficient refrigerator when run in reverse and.
Despite that efficiency, it is not a really not
really a practical system, not a usable.
Cycle to apply to. Actual real world devices that
either do work or or cool reservoirs, and that is
because the isothermal stages. Just operates so
slowly that running the Karno cycle would take too
long to get any useful work out of it is the
engine or get any useful cooling out of it as a
refrigerator. And real devices have to sacrifice
some of that theoretical efficiency for practical
functionality. So that's the note on which will
end the consideration of ideal gases,
thermodynamic cycles and the canonical ensemble
moving on next week to the final statistical
ensemble for the module, the grand canonical
ensemble, where both of the internal energy and
the particle no will be allowed to change. And
we'll get into that here. We'll come back with the
green canonical ensemble next week.