Hello and welcome back to week two of the
statistical physics module, math 327.
This is the overview video for the week, which
will aim to serve as an introduction to the
lecture notes, doing two things in approximately
the next ten minutes. So first goal of this video
is to orient this week in the overall scope of the
module across the entire term, seeing how it
builds on what we went through the previous week,
week one, and then how it's going to be built on
in turn as we go on and develop things further in
the coming weeks. And after looking at that very
big picture very abstractly, we'll focus in on
some of the main topics in the lecture notes for
this week for you to keep an eye out for as you
read through those. And then we will come back
around to them and just summarize the takeaway
points in the separate video after you've gone
through those notes. So looking at the big picture,
there's going to be what feels like a significant
change in style or focus this week compared to
last week. So last week we were focusing on the
essentials, the essential foundations from
probability theory. And this week we are going to
start applying those to statistical physics and in
particular, statistical ensembles. So this week is
going to be sort of the model for much of the rest
of the term. We will be looking at three different
types of statistical ensembles, all of which have
a few basic things in common. First of all, they
are grounded or they are based on the probability
foundation that we established last week. But now
that we are focusing on developing these ensembles
as a no more higher level framework and applying
that framework to interesting systems and
phenomena, that probability theory is going to
fade into the background a bit. We'll know it's
there providing the foundation for the work we're
doing, but we will mostly be focused on exploring
and applying the frameworks that are built on top
of those foundations. And as I said, that's this
is this week is the first example of one of those
frameworks in the form of the micro canonical
ensemble, which I probably should have mentioned
earlier, as it is the title of the week. The other
two ensembles we will be looking at in later weeks
are called the Canonical Ensemble and Grant
Canonical Ensemble, and all three based on the
same probability foundations and also all three
based on the same qualitative idea that these are
mathematical frameworks. Each of these ensembles
is a mathematical framework or specifically a
probability space that is designed to describe the
behaviour of systems that involve large numbers of
particles where all use particles interchangeably
for degrees of freedom. A bit more formal term. We
have large numbers of particles that are evolving
in time, subject to certain constraints. And in
each of those three cases, micro, canonical,
canonical and grand canonical, the detailed form
of the constraints will be different, reflecting
different physical situations in the micro
canonical ensemble. What we have in mind is a
system that is completely isolated from the rest
of the universe. It has some number of particles
that have some amount of energy and because it is
isolated, it can exchange neither particles nor
energy with its surroundings or with anything else
in the universe. So both particle number and
energy are conserved quantities for this system
and that conservation of energy
is hopefully a familiar concept. It was to some
extent developed by considering the source of
statistical systems. So in this context,
conservation of energy in an isolated system is
given a rather grand, grand or grandiose sounding
name. The first law of thermodynamics, which is
one of the things being seen this week, along with
the second law that will come to in just a bit.
Now,
one key both. For the MicroCon article ensemble,
as well as all the others, so this is a third
thing that all three have in common in addition to
their probability foundation and their
interpretation as physical systems evolving in
time, in addition to both of those, we are only
going to be considering these ensembles in what is
called thermodynamic equilibrium. And you will see
a detailed discussion of thermodynamic equilibrium
in the notes, along with two definitions of this
concept that are equivalent for the micro
canonical ensemble. The big idea is that we are
looking at systems that, as they evolve in time,
are fairly stable, fairly steady, like the air in
this room. There are no wild changes just
happening spontaneously with no outside influence.
We don't have all the air rushing over to that
corner to my right or that corner to my left. At
any point, it's all feels very smooth and and
steady over time. Of course, that's this is the
overview video. This is all the qualitative
literally handwaving idea that is then more
carefully defined mathematically and elaborated on
in the in the lecture notes and based on the micro
canonical ensemble in thermodynamic equilibrium.
We will after defining that concept mathematically,
we will use it to introduce two important derived
quantities, at least one of which I'm sure you've
heard of. These are first, the entropy and then
the temperature. And again, without going into
details in this big overview, the fact that both
of these are derived quantities might be
surprising if you are used to thinking of the
temperature as a sort of intrinsic property of
some system. So I have in this coffee cup, there
are say ten of the twenty five molecules. And I
can sort of feel that at this point I've been
talking too long and they're relatively cold. The
temperature is a very intuitive thing I'm able to
pick up on from here. In the micro canonical
ensemble, we're thinking of systems that are
completely isolated from the environment. So those
differ from this coffee cup. I can't just look in
feel and say, oh, it's got a unfortunately cold
temperature. We have to define the temperature as
some mathematical function of the more fundamental
quantities that define the ensemble, specifically
its energy and its number of particles, number of
degrees of freedom, or more generally, the number
of states that the system can realize based on
those two defining features, the number of degrees
of freedom and the amount of energy. And I'll call
the individual states that the system can realize
those will go by the term microstates going
forward because they are descriptions of the whole
set of microscopic degrees of freedom in the
system. And based on all of those microstates, we
define these derived quantities of temperature and
entropy, entropy. I suspect
many of you have also heard of, though it's a more
specialised concept that we intuitively think of
measuring the amount of disorder in a system and
we will see mathematically what that amounts to in
the definition of temperature sorry, the
definition of entropy. See how this concept
matches on to the number of available states or
the number of available available microstates. I
should be careful to use the terms of define. And
I also want to highlight the example that we will
be using throughout this week to illustrate all of
these both fundamental concepts and derived
quantities. We will be looking at a system of
particles where the particles can only take one of
two orientations. They can be so they can be sort
of pointing up or pointing down is the usual
picture. And we have the terminology that we use
for this is that these particles are a spin. Each
particle is a spin that can have one of two
orientations up or down and. This is to some
extent an artificial example, because it's very
much an oversimplification compared to the sorts
of systems we will be interested in later on in
the term the air moving in the room or the coffee
moving around in my cup. The benefit of spin
systems is that the mathematics is extremely
simple because there are only two possibilities.
The mathematics is essentially the same as that of
flipping a coin. And we talked about last week and
at the same time, despite being so simple, it's
not a terrible approximation for several physical
systems, particularly magnetic systems, magnetic
molecules or systems of the underlying physics of
Ferrol. Magnets can be modeled as simply spins
that are either pointing up aligned with a
magnetic field or pointing down aligned against a
external magnetic field. That external magnetic
field introduces a temperature sorry. It
introduces an energy for these spins, and that
energy in turn defines the corresponding
temperature
details which you will see in the in the lecture
notes. I will summarize in the next video.