Hello and welcome back to a statistical physics.
This is the first video for week seven resuming
after the break. So let's start with a couple of
minutes. Just reviewing where we are in the module
and where we are going. As usual, with the aid of
taking a look at the written materials here. So in
approximately the first half of the module, we
have introduced the three core statistical
ensembles that form the bulk of of what we work
with in statistical physics, these being the micro
canonical ensemble, canonical ensemble and granth
canonical ensemble. And just as a quick reminder,
the micro canonical ensemble is defined by
conservation of energy and particle under the
canonical ensemble. No longer enforces
conservation of energy, but instead fixes a
temperature while keeping the particle no
conserved. And the grand canonical ensemble
doesn't conserve either energy or particle. No,
but instead fixes the temperature and chemical
potential. And just as we previously. Developed
and gained familiarity with the canonical ensemble
by applying it to investigate ideal gases and the
thermodynamic cycles, over the next few weeks, we
will gain familiarity and and expertise with the
grand canonical ensemble by applying it to
investigate quantum gases, which requires the
content of this week getting to grips with quantum
statistics. And what's quantum really means in
this context, with no assumption that you've seen
anything quantum before and no intention of really
teaching you about quantum mechanics, which is an
entirely different module in its own right. What
we're doing is taking some of the key features of
quantum physics and basically assuming those
adopting them as offsets or conjectures and seeing
what results when we apply our statistical toolkit
to the resulting systems.
There are still some conceptual subtleties here
that are the focus of this week, so you will see
that the materials are. Largely conceptual,
there's not much in the way of calculations and
and little exercises for you to work on and in in
the two videos that I have planned for this week,
I'll focus on what I think are the two trickiest
concepts here having to do with the contrast
between classical and quantum statistics, where if
you recall from way back in week for the ideal gas,
the word classical simply means not quantum and
anything. Quantum is not classical.
Now, the sort of obvious condition for quantum
physics is that the the system is quantized and in
particular the energies that we sum over and the
definition of either the canonical or grand
canonical partition function are those energies
are themselves quantized or discrete, falling into
energy levels of the sort that we saw back in week
three, four systems of spin's. But of course, back
in week three, even though we had these quantize
energy levels, we hadn't mentioned the concept of
of quantum physics and everything was still being
done classically. So there's a different change in
perspective that really distinguishes between
classical and quantum physics. And to give a
slightly different approach to that in this video
compared to the written material. Let me jump to
the statement of this difference at the end of
Section seven point one, and then go back and see
how this manifests in. In the earlier parts of the
section, so the difference between quantum and
classical statistics is that in the quantum case.
And we have to define this sum over the
microstates that gives us either the canonical or
in this case, the grand canonical partition
function and then all the properties of the system
from that in order to define the microstates in a
quantum system, we consider each possible discrete
energy level in turn and some over all of the
possible occupation numbers that this energy level
could have in. This contrasts with the quantum
approach where we consider each particle in the
system one by one and some over all of the
possible energies that that single particle could
have.
That classical approach is still applicable even
in the current canonical ensemble, where different
microstates have different particle numbers, just
some over all of the particles that there are.
What happens when we do so? We saw in week three,
we actually overcount the same micro state
multiple times when the particles are
indistinguishable, which they always are in the
context of quantum physics.
In that overcounting well, we corrected for it's
classically by.
Counting how many times the same system was
included, which turned out to be that factor of
one over and factorial and then just divide it
through by that one over. And Vectorial, a
normalization gave us the correct partition
function for indistinguishably articles with the
assumption that was hidden in a footnote, there
was the assumption that all of the particles were
in distinct energy levels in the case where the
energy level is defined by. The momentum and
retreat, the momentum is approximately continuous
numbers then.
It is essentially guaranteed that every particle
will have a a different momentum. There are
uncountable infinite numbers of possible momenta
and only a finite number of particles in the
universe. So there's a vanishingly small chance
that any of them have the same momentum. But when
the energy levels are. Discreet and quantize to
depending on how many energy levels are accessible
for the system, there may be a negligible chance
of having multiple particles, multiple identical
particles in the same energy level. And to show
what that does in this section, we go through a
simple little exercise of considering a canonical
system with a fixed number of two particles and
only five different energy levels, and we count
explicitly how many microstates there are to some
over and how many we would predict from the
classical argument we use in the past, refine
where you will find when you fill in this box a
nonsensical prediction. Whereas going over the
calculation more explicitly leads to. The
exhaustive list here, which is not. A, not
something that can be obtained by counting all of
the microstates for the single particles and
dividing by any overcounting factor, we have to go
through energy level by energy level, count the
possible occupation numbers for each energy level,
and then that gives us the correct accounting of
all the microstates with no additional
overcounting factor that has to be included. So
I'll wrap up this video just with a further
comment on. What occupation numbers are possible
for typical physical systems, and it turns out for
somewhat technical reasons of quantum physics,
that there are two distinct classes of
possibilities that have the funny looking names of
those islands and fermions. Those names come from
being named after some 20th century physicists.
And really the fundamental distinction between
bosons and fermions is precisely the possible
occupation numbers for identical particles in a
given energy level. So bosons are somewhat
familiar or perhaps intuitive case where it is
possible to have any non-negative number of
particles in the same energy level.
And the particles that behave, this so-called
Bosnich statistics are photons, particles of light
and subatomic particles like pions, the Higgs
boson that was discovered almost a decade ago, as
well as many atoms, including helium for. The
other class of particles, there can be at most one
particle in any energy level. This is for fermions,
so. There cannot be multiple fermions in an energy
level, the energy level is either occupied by a
firm hand with occupation, number one, or it is
unoccupied. If occupation number zero, which is
behavior that was observed before quantum physics
was fully developed and became known as the the
exclusion principle, before the reasons behind it
were understood.
And the fact that only a single thermionic can
occupy any energy level is extremely important. It
is necessary for the existence of chemistry and
the existence of life, and it also gives rise to
very different quantum statistics compared to both
to to quantum bosons as well as to the classical
accounting that goes under the name of Maxwell
Walsman statistics and was reviewed in Section
seven point one. This long paragraph here is a
brief story, somewhat imprecise to explaining why
exactly those are the fermions differ in this way.
It does not have to do with any sort of direct
repulsion or pushing on each other in terms of how
many particles can occupy the same energy level.
It is a a more fundamental aspect of quantum
physics that you can skip if you are. Uninterested.
So in the next video, I'll briefly look at the
resulting statistics and then focus on the second
tricky conceptual issue, which is how do the
quantum and classical worlds reconnect, given the
knowledge that the classical physics were familiar
with from everyday experience is fundamentally
arising from quantum physics at a smaller distance
scales.