The hello and welcome back to the end of week one
of statistical physics, a brief wrap up video that
we'll try to highlight and summarize the key
learning outcomes of this first week's content on
probability essentials that underlie statistical
physics, as well as the central limit theorem and
its role in diffusion. So I'll try to keep this
about 10 minutes to keep from overloading you with
too much content that is picking out information
that you do already have in full form. In the
lecture notes, I'll go through and just say a few
things on my mind for each of these sections,
starting with the the probability foundations. And
I'll mention that the distinction we draw here
between states that are produced by experiments on
the one hand, and the outcomes that are produced
by measurements on the other, is really rather
formal and not something that so many treatments
of this topic do. What this does is really justify
rigorously how we are able to put the outcomes of
random experiments in a solid mathematical
framework where we don't have to worry about the
in principle possible but very unlikely states
that could result from experiments in full
generality. So just to illustrate what I mean here,
if I go back to the example of flipping a coin
once, a process that through the measurement of
whether the coin landed, heads up or landed tails
up, I have a solid probability space to work with.
And I don't have to worry about the much less
likely but in principle possible states that could
result from the basic experiment of flipping a
coin. For example, the the state where I flip the
coin and a rogue seagull comes in and swallows the
coin out of the air. And I never know whether it's
heads up or tails up. There is obviously a low
probability of that occurring, especially since my
windows are closed. But it is in principle a
possible outcome or a possible state produced by
that experiment. And by processing those states
through a measurement, we discard that possibility
and end up with the simple set of outcomes that
can be straightforwardly analyzed through
probability theory, defining the probabilities
that map each of those outcomes to their
probability of occurring.
The probability is also define the mean and
variance, which are very important concepts. I
imagine you've seen that before. You'll be seeing
them again. These are formally defined by
something over all of the outcomes in the outcome
space, weighed by the corresponding probability
for that outcome
at the same time. And this gets us to to one of
the key learning outcomes. The the law of large
numbers is the statement that we don't necessarily
have to sum formally over every possible outcome
in the outcome space in order to determine the
mean and variance with some accuracy. It turns out
that as an experiment is repeated a large number
of times, if we measure the outcome of interest
and then just average over all of those
repetitions, the arithmetic mean that we get out
of that process reliably and steadily approaches.
The true probabilistic been defined by something
over all of the elements of the outcome space. And
when we consider outcomes spaces with infinite,
either countable or uncountable numbers of of
possible outcomes, then this becomes the law of
large numbers, becomes a crucial tool that allows
us to determine the mean and the variance and the
properties of our system without knowing the
exhaustive probability measure that is mapping all
of the possible outcomes to the corresponding
probabilities. So that is one of the formal
ingredients that is going to underlie the
application of probability theory to large scale
systems in statistical physics and really put it
on a firm mathematical foundation, even though
moving forward we will take that foundation for
granted and focus on the applications that can be
built on it.
I mentioned just now the the possibility that the
outcome space is unaccountably infinite, which
makes it not obvious how to define a sum over all
of the elements of that outcome space. It's not
possible to enumerate an uncountable number of
possibilities, essentially by the definition of
unaccountability. What we have in this situation
is really a probability distribution or
probability density function rather than a
probability itself in the relation between
probabilities and probability distributions. Is
that the the probability is the integral integral
of the probability distribution over an
appropriate interval that defines the sort of
outcome that we can consider formally in a a
finite system. So if we want to extract some
probability for some finite number of outcomes, we
integrate over the corresponding range of the
outcomes space. We integrate the probability
distribution weighted again by whatever function
for which we want to determine the the expectation
value or the variance in this arises in the
context of the central limit theorem, which is
very powerful for for several reasons. First of
all,
the the central limit theorem
provides a very good approximation to the
probability distribution for.
A sum and outcome of a collective process that we
obtained by repeating some elementary single step
core process, a large number of times, as the
number of repetitions increases, we can
approximate a probability distribution from the
underlying probabilities of the elementary single
step process. And the central limit theorem tells
us exactly how the mean and the variance for that
elementary single set process govern the
probability distribution for the continuous
outcome that we can approximate in the limit of a
large number of repetitions so that the the sum is
essentially or effectively a continuous,
continuously valued parameter.
Another important aspect of the central limit
theorem is that the probability distribution
obtained in that manner is a Gaussian distribution
or a normal distribution whenever the mean and the
variance of that elementary single set process
exist. And the consequence of this is what's known
as the law of diffusion, which we illustrated
through the example of a random walk, which is a
very generic framework that can be used to analyze
all sorts of statistical physics systems. So here
we gave the simplest possible example of some
walker that can take a step of a fixed length,
either to the right with some probability or to
the left with the remaining probability. But it's
very easy to generalize that simple situation to
all sorts of more abstract situations. To give
just one example, we can think about the physics
of protein folding, which is a major topic in
molecular biology and mathematical biology. And we
can model the process of protein folding by
considering the protein to be carrying out a
random walk through the high dimensional space
that is defined by the possible configurations it
could take. So this is an abstract vector space
where each basis vector is some aspect of the
configuration of this protein and the process of
this protein folding is then a walk through that
space, a random walk, because there's some
elements of randomness and probability to it and
obviously a directed walk that is biased towards
the stable ground state that the protein wants to
end up in. So the probabilities here are
present. They are probabilistic, but it's not
completely random in the sense that anything could
happen. The probability is describe the most
likely outcome and by working or by translating
the walk into a process that occurs over some
amount of time. So we imagine that each step in
this walk takes some fixed length of time. We can
treat the random walk as a process evolving in
time, which lets us see how the the basic features
of the system evolve in time as the week goes by.
So we define the drift velocity that governs how
the expectation value for the location of our
random water or our system, how that evolves in
time as well as the diffusion length which governs
the scale of fluctuations around that that average
out, that expected value of the outcome. So this
diffusion length we saw that as time goes on, the
diffusion length becomes larger and larger,
proportional to the square root of the time that
has been taken, which is known as the law of
diffusion and turns out to be a very general
result. And by applying the central limit theorem
to the case of this random walk, we were able to
see how exactly the law of diffusion arises from
the fact that the probability distribution
provided by the Central Limit Theorem is a
Gaussian distribution, that Gaussian distribution
gives us the law of diffusion.
So we get both of those whenever the assumptions
of the Central Limit theorem hold, in particular
that the elementary single step process has both a
finite mean and a finite variance, so long as that
holds the central limit theorem and the law of
diffusion hold and in the computer projects in a
few weeks, we will numerically investigate what
happens when those assumptions break down and the
law of diffusion no longer results. And we will
need to use numerical computing to analyze that
case because things get much more complicated when
we are no longer able to bring to bear the very
powerful mathematical tool of the central limit
theorem. So that's something to look forward to.
And at the same time, we'll be going through
additional learning material in the coming week of.
Flying these probabilistic foundations to the case
of our first statistical unsalable, the micro
canonical ensemble.