Hello and welcome back to statistical physics,
this is the second video for week 11, which may be
a shorter one since after wrapping up the previous
discussion of numerical computations through
Monte Carlo important sampling techniques, the
other sections in week 11 materials are shorter
and a bit more qualitative. And also outside the
mainstream of this module's materials, though. No
less important for all that, the goal here is to
take a step back, even beyond this miserable
itself, and consider and appreciate how the
statistical physics concepts and tools that we
have been learning about and working through find
very broad applicability throughout.
A whole range of areas of scientific investigation
in the mathematical sciences and beyond. Part of
the. Reason for the broad applicability of the
statistical physics tools is an important concept
related to phase transitions that is known as
universality, a bit too technical to get through
in in rigorous detail in the scope of this
molecule, but useful to to be aware of and have
some familiarity with. The basic idea is that. The
critical exponents of the sort that we saw for the
U.S. model last week that described the behavior
not only of the order parameters, but also other
observables in the vicinity of second order phase
transitions are close to critical points. The same
critical exponents historically were observed to
appear in different systems with phase transitions
that don't seem to have anything to do with each
other. And a famous example being this critical
exponent that I call B here. It's more widely
known as Beda, I don't want to get that confused
as the inverse temperature this be for the three
dimensional easing model is precisely the same as
a critical exponent that shows up if we consider
the phase transition between interacting a liquid
and gas phases of, say, water and steam. And in
particular, the independence of the inverse
density of those two phases around the critical
temperature. Exactly the same critical exponents
show up in both of those transitions and many
others, which is or was eventually understood to
be a reflection that at phase transitions the.
Details, the specifics of these statistical
systems cease to matter, they become irrelevant in
such a way that completely different systems like
interacting spins in a regular cubic lattice or
water boiling are governed by precisely the same
mathematics, the universality class into which the
critical exponents of the corresponding transition
happen to fall. And as a brief aside, for those
with philosophical interests, this universality
can be taken as at least a partial response to one
of the first footnotes that came up in the
materials for for the module where we mentioned
the famous essay on the unreasonable effectiveness
of mathematics in the natural sciences.
Universality can be used to argue why. The
effectiveness of mathematics is more reasonable
than it may seem. If all of these. Details become
irrelevant in critical systems, so that is
something to be aware of and another thing to be
aware of at a much less technical level are the
and the broader implications and the.
The wide variety of systems to which. Statistical
physics tools are applicable and the power that
that they have when used to analyze. Questions
ranging from not only physics and mathematics, but
all the way to the life sciences and even
sociology, so there are just three examples here
that aren't going to be worth summarizing in too
much detail in this video. But in the sociological
context, there is a.
Wide range of work being done actively on what are
called voter models that resemble in some ways.
The interacting spin systems that we saw in the
context of the easy model, but also describe the
outcomes of polls and elections where voters
opinions on particular questions or topics are
represented as integer spins, possibly with
generalizations to allow for neutrality or to
allow for people who are especially committed to
the opinion that they hold. And based on that
simple setup, all sorts of realistic behavior can
be observed. This figure here showing how.
Connections between groups with differing opinions
can evolve over time and can be used to modify the
opinions of those groups, where there are phase
transitions between phases where one opinion
becomes a consensus compared to other phases where
there are what are called stable, non consensus,
non consensus phases where multiple opinions
persist indefinitely among communities that to an
extent just stop talking to each other. They exist
to some extent in clusters. Or we might call
bubbles in a sociological context and speak mainly
with people who who share their same opinion with
fewer interactions with those holding the opposite
opinion.
So moving on to further examples, epidemiology,
the study of, for instance, the spread of disease
in a population is something we've probably all
seen over the past year and change where know
precisely statistical physics models of
interacting degrees of freedom can be used to
model how individuals move, contact and interact
with each other and thereby spread infections and
diseases through a population in between different
populations, as well as modeling the likely
effects of restrictions on people's movements,
like not holding lectures in person, but recording
these videos and having secret assume sessions.
And, you know, the the example shown here that you
can go and and run through this link is an
extremely simplified a simulation, but it is the
case that precisely these sorts of numerical
calculations based on models of interacting
particles, you know, not ideal gases for the an
important piece of input that goes into government
deliberations over what restrictions ought to be
imposed to control the spread of disease and how
long those restrictions need to remain in place.
And the final example is a phenomenon known
alternately as flocking or or swarming, which is
another biological application where various
species of animals from birds such as starlings to
schools of fish, swarms of insects or crowds of
people. Exhibit large scale coordinated behavior
as a result of of the interactions between the
individual members of those crowds. This being a
representative picture of a bunch of birds forming
distinct flocks that all
fly through the sky and turning and spinning about
in. Surprising amount of unison just to to look at
them and that. That amount of unison, that
coordination between these flocks of many
interacting, degrees of freedom, many interacting
birds, turns out to be very well modeled by
interacting statistical physics systems. One
example known as the Big Six model, the big stick
was only one of about half a dozen researchers who
developed it in the 90s
simply introduces an interaction that encourages
these animals to align with the directions in
which their neighbors are moving in. Much the same
way that the interactions of the easy model
encourage it spins all to align. With each other
and seeing in this bottle of flocking a phase
transition, in this case, a discontinuous first
order phase transition between two phases in which
the emotion of the animals is either random and
disordered or a. A high density ordered phase
where a collective motion sets in and yeah,
there's a bit more to read in the materials
themselves. But the idea is that these three
examples of broader applications beyond
mathematical sciences are far from exhaustive, but
give a flavor of the ways that the concepts and
tools we've been looking at this term find
application really throughout science research in
everyday life and with the understanding and
appreciation for these tools that that we now have,
you can stay on the lookout for further examples.
And I will wrap up there and not go through this
final section, which just summarizes and
synthesizes the information that we've seen in the
topics we've gone through in the previous 10 weeks
of doing a summary of a summary would be a bit of
overkill. This can serve as a quick reference
section while you're revising for the exam in a
few weeks just to check that you recall the topics
discussed in each week and provide quick links to
hop back and take another look at any that seem
unfamiliar or may require a bit of revision to
wrap up the. The term as a whole.