Hello and welcome back to a statistical physics.
This is the first video for the week five material,
and I will continue experimenting with the format
of these videos, in particular continuing that
screen share. And when I first tried this. Last
week, it seemed as though it was hard to keep the
overview separate from the the take away and wrap
up summary of the key learning outcomes, so tried
to just do a single pass through the material for
this week, both putting it into context and
emphasizing what to take away from it. And we'll
see how that works and if it's worth continuing
for the remainder of the term. Still aiming for
the same amount of time in these videos. So that's
not too much of the written material is duplicated
redundantly. So as I said, read five is our last
week looking at the canonical ensemble, the
probability space that fixes the temperature and
the particle number. And as we saw last week, in
some contexts, the volume is also a key parameter,
a control parameter of the canonical ensemble. And
this week we continue applying those canonical
tools to look at thermodynamic cycles and in
particular cycles that act as engines or
refrigerators. And this begins quite directly from
where we left off last week, where we defined the
thermodynamic pressure as the response of the
average internal energy to an adiabatic change in
the volume adiabatic, meaning the entropy is fixed,
finding the ideal gas law and motivating that
definition of pressure by thinking about squeezing
or compressing a system of an ideal gas, which
then brings in a connection between pressure and
force, which may be familiar to those of you who
have encountered Newtonian mechanics before, where
pressure is just the force exerted per unit area
of a surface. And that is precisely the connection
that we begin by deriving this relation between
the thermodynamic pressure as the response of a
probabilistic system to the idea of a force acting
on some area. And this relies on the role of the
volume as a control parameter in the ensemble.
That volume is providing the area. Where?
Skip ahead quickly to this illustration, we have a
picture of ideal gas particles in some container
where one wall of that container is a movable
piston with that area, A, which we can push in to
compress the gas or pull out to expand the gas by
applying an appropriate force. And that process
changing the volume. As we saw, that raises the
energy of the gas and if it's done idiomatically,
then the change in energy raising, if it's
compressed and falling, if it's expanded, that
change in energy is given by the work done by this
force. Another concept from the 17th century,
Newtonian mechanics. The work is the product. The
inner product of the force got it into the
displacements it causes, both in three dimensions.
So a simple example you can work through, if this
is unfamiliar, is thinking about an object falling
from a height under the force of the Earth's
gravity, which is directed downward. The object
falls downward so that work is just a simple
product of the force times. The light falls that
changes the energy from, say, zero if it starts at
rest to a classic result for the momentum or the
velocity of a particle that falls some distance
from rest. In this example, with the movable
piston, the force is again directed in the
parallel, in the same direction as the
displacement it causes. So the work it produces is
positive, and that corresponds to a change, a
positive change in the internal energy coming from
a decrease in the volume. And we can connect the
thermodynamic definition of the pressure from last
week to the usual force per unit area that comes
from the 17th century. And.
More generally, the work is still given by that
pressure times the change in the volume with that
negative sign.
Correctly mapping the decreasing volume to an
increasing internal energy, but if the entropy is
allowed to change, then there is another possible
way to introduce changes to the energy without
changing the volume or doing any work in this
simple relation generalizes to an integration when
the pressure is not constant. Typically, as we
change the volume, we change the pressure that is
familiar from trying to say, compressible doing
the. As the volume could squeeze, the pressure
gets larger and the total work done has to be
integrated over that changing pressure as a
function of volume. But if we suppose that the
volume stays constant so that no work is done, W
equals zero. It's still possible to change the
internal energy of the gas, which we actually
looked at all the way back in the micro canonical
ensemble and week to.
The internal energy is related to heat and the
economical ensemble, the exchange of heat with the
system's surroundings.
So from last week for an ideal gas, we found that
the average internal energy is just given by the
temperature. So even if we. Keep the volume fixed
so that no work is done, we can increase that
temperature by adding some heat. And the process
of increasing the temperature we expect since the
energy changes for you is zero, the entropy must
also change in order to be consistent with the
work in the previous section and. Running through
that calculation. Produces a change in the entropy
that is directly proportional to the change in the
energy, and it is precisely that.
Change in the energy that we define as the heat in
terms of the temperature and the change in entropy.
And just as for work, this heat is positive when
the internal energy of the gas increases, negative
when it decreases, and if the temperature changes
in that process, we need to express the
temperature as a function of the entropy,
inverting the usual relation that we looked at
even a couple of weeks ago. Or the canonical
ensemble and integrates over the change of the
entropy in this process.
And the one last thing I'll say before.
Stopping this video and starting a new one to keep
them relatively bite sized is that.
This relation between heat exchange and the change
in entropy gives us some important physical
intuition for what it means for a process to be
adiabatic. Remember, adiabatic means that the
entropy does not change. And this equation. Sixty
five. The definition of heat then means that no
heat is exchanged due to the constant entropy. So
in adiabatic process is one that does not exchange
heat, which we can interpret as typically being a
process that occurs quickly enough that there's no
time for heat to be exchanged between the system
and its surroundings. In other words, adiabatic
processes are fast, and the opposite extreme is to
consider a slow process where enough heat is
exchanged at every step in the process to keep the
temperature fixed in verbalised with the
surrounding systems. Where the system's
surroundings, I should say, that fixed temperature
is known as isothermal situation or nicer thermal
process, and that is the opposite exchange of what
happens when changes in the system are done very
slowly and the system is allowed to recalibrates
to its constant temperature thermal reservoir at
each step in that process. And those real
processes exist in between those two extremes,
usually closer to the adiabatic limit and. With
that, I will. Pause the recording and pick up with
applying these ideas of heat and work to look at
bona fide thermodynamic cycles.