Hello and welcome to the overview video for the
first week's content of the statistical physics
module, where the title for this week is Central
Limit Theorem and Diffusion. But that's really
encompassing all of the fundamental aspects of
probability theory that are going to form the
groundwork for everything we are looking at in
this term, really. And having said that, I should
say that once we go through this groundwork in
this week, it's going to be largely in the
background and we won't be doing exactly the the
sorts of work that that we'll be seeing in the
lecture notes in the synchronous sessions this
week. Considering formal definitions of
measurements and outcomes and probability spaces,
what we will be doing is building upon those
fundamentals a larger superstructure of of
applications that rely on these concepts of
experiments, measurements, outcomes and
probability spaces without explicitly giving those
a big role. So the flavor of this week is going to
be a bit different compared to those that are
coming up. And I'll see a bit more about that for
the moment. I'll just take a step backward to talk
about the the big picture overview of statistical
physics and this module more generally, which at
its essence is the is based on the application of
probability theory to
probabilistically predict physical phenomena, the
outcomes of experiments, whether those experiments
be things we actually do in a in a laboratory or
things we think about conducting experiments in
idealise systems, the the domain of statistical
physics. This application of probability theory to
predict properties of large scale systems grew out
of work in the in the late eighteen hundreds to
understand the empirically observed laws of
thermodynamics and how those could be understood
to emerge from the more fundamental behavior of
the atoms and molecules of which these large
systems of of gasses and fluids were built. And
this is obviously still relevant today because we
are still building systems out of atoms and
molecules and want to know how those large scale
systems behave without having to go through the
formal work of applying Newton's laws of mechanics
to all of the atoms and molecules that are in the
game, whether that be in the physics of neutron
stars, the physics of the atmosphere and climate
change, or the physics of internal combustion
engines or refrigerators, all of which rely on the
statistical physics that we will be seeing in this
module. And one of the remarkable things about
this whole domain of physics is the fantastic
accuracy with which this probabilistic analysis,
based in
the idea of random fluctuations, can really
predictably describe the large scale properties of
these systems, which, looking back historically,
this was a big puzzle in the eighteen hundreds and
there was a very long running debate even about
whether atoms and molecules, as we understand them
today, could be thought to exist at all. The
argument being that if we imagined systems like
the air being composed of a large number of
randomly jostling air molecules, why don't we
observe all of that random jostling when we work
with the air? Instead, we see behaviour that seems
to be very stable, very smooth. And the essential
answer at the qualitative and handwaving level is
that there are just so many molecules that their
effects all smooth each other out. And these
fluctuations are unobservable at the macroscopic
scale. We can easily observe and to quantify how
large is large. It's worth more worthwhile to keep
in mind Avogadro's number, which is about ten to
the power, twenty three, about a thousand billion
billion or ten thousand billion billion in round
numbers. That is the number of watermill. He rules
that there are in 18 grams of water, which is not
very much. So we're talking about an enormous
number of degrees of freedom in the systems that
are governed by statistical physics, which also
helps us understand why we have the idea that
these are described by random fluctuations in
principle using the classical laws of Newtonian
mechanics from the sixteen hundreds we could
imagine track tracing of the positions and
momentum and interactions of all of those thousand
billion billion particles in a few drops of water
and predicting exactly how those particles and the
water as a whole is going to behave. That is
simply impossible in practice because there are
too many particles to many degrees of freedom to
keep track of. Instead, thanks to the law of large
numbers that we will see in the lecture notes for
this week, we can really
make the approximation that the behavior of all
those particles is just randomly fluctuating
around some collective average in this turns out
to give both accurate or both correct results that
are very precise and very accurate. And this is
perhaps remarkable, but we will take advantage of
it to learn about all sorts of different systems
throughout the course of this term. Again, relying
on this law of large numbers and the the related
central limit theorem that will put this
discussion on an actual mathematical basis rather
than the very qualitative handwaving overview that
I'm getting in this video. So just looking through
the few sections that the notes for this week are
split up into, the first section is looking at
some probability fundamentals, the concept of
experiments, measurement, outcome and probability
and how those are all interrelated and.
I will say, just keeping an eye on the big picture
and looking forward, the idea of experiment is
what underlies the so-called statistical ensembles,
that the module as a whole are organized around
things that are called the micro, canonical and
canonical ensemble and grand canonical ensemble,
all of which are based on the idea that an
experiment can consist of just getting a bunch of
degrees of freedom together, a bunch of molecules,
letting them evolve for some amount of time,
governed by Newton's laws, for example, and then
measuring the some aspect of the state of the
resulting system that that framework applied to
these probability fundamentals provides the
concept of ensemble that we will then use to
analyze ideal gases, quantum gases and all sorts
of of systems throughout this module right here.
We're going to be using these concepts of
probability and outcome to define some familiar,
quite hopefully familiar quantities like the mean
and standard deviation or variance of a
probability space, which leads to the law of large
numbers. The the fact that a empirical observed
arithmetic average over many repeated experiments
reproduces the theoretical mean that is predicted
by the probabilities themselves of the
mathematical level, as well as the central limit
theorem that governs the behavior of systems when
large numbers of particles are are all at play.
And we will use a few example applications to
illustrate aspects of the central limit theorem
and the the way in which repeated experiments can
provide that sort of smoothing or averaging out
process that leads to these very precise
mathematical approximations, even when the the
large and limit of the number of degrees of
freedom is not necessarily as large as 10 to the
power. Twenty three. So one of those examples is
looking at the game of roulette and thinking about
how much we or how likely we are to win or lose a
certain amount of money when playing a game of
roulette after some number of spins of the
roulette wheel. The second example being the case
of a random walker or an object that can move
randomly, which is a very versatile way of
modeling all sorts of physical phenomena. We'll be
looking at the very simplest case of a random
walker that can just take steps of a fixed length,
either to the right on a line or to the left on a
line, which, when
a sufficient number of those steps are taken, can
both be analyzed by the central limit theorem and
illustrates the process of diffusion and the law
of diffusion that turns out to be very general and
will be revisited in the computer project in a few
weeks where we will see how that law of diffusion
can break down, which is associated with the
applicability of the central limit theorem where
that comes from and what that produces. But for
now, let's start with the the basic fundamentals
of the probability central limit theorem and how
that is all related to the law of ordinary
diffusion in very general circumstances.