Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
This is the second video for week 10 wrapping up.
That's a brief summary of the context, motivations
and key of learning outcomes for interacting
systems and in particular, doing so more briefly
than the first video for this week, which went
significantly over the target of time. So without
further ado, we'll just pick right back up where
we were in this week's materials, having
introduced the mathematical definition of phase
transition and how it is distinguished from a a
smooth, gradual crossover by the existence of a
discontinuity in either the order parameter itself
that distinguishes the different large scale
phases of the system. Or in derivatives of that
order parameter with respect to the control
parameters. So in the case, the easy model, the
order parameter is the magnetization. And the
control parameter is the temperature, and when we
have a discontinuity in the order parameter in
general, that is known as a first order phase
transition, and we will see in the last section
for this week that in two or more dimensions, the
easy model has been said, a second order phase
transition where the order parameter itself is
continuous, but it has a kink where its first
derivative is is discontinuous, where divergence.
And we will we will figure this out, we will
establish that result by considering an
approximation that will allow us to get some
results for this interactive system where by
virtue of those interactions, the calculation
immediately becomes enormously more difficult than
the non distracting spend system we considered
back in weeks, two and three. And the starting
point for this is.
Noticing that the order parameter or the
magnetization is related to the order parameter is
just the average spin over all of the degrees of
freedom in the system. And if we take the
expectation value of this, every spin, we will
have Mison, this mean magnetization is the origin
of the meaning in the so-called Medfield
approximation, though, you don't need to worry too
much about that terminology, which is largely
historical. But the approach, the the way this
Medfield approximation works is to right. That
interaction term involving two factors of spins on
nearest neighbor sites in terms of fluctuations
about this constant mean. And we make the
approximation that for a system with a sufficient
number of particles sufficiently large n the
average fluctuations about the mean and.
Magnetization are going to be small, at least when
we sum over all of the links, all of the nearest
neighbor pairs in the lattice in the sun that
appears in the energy. The individual terms may
not be small from site to site, but something over
all sites can reliably approximate this
interaction term by dropping the quadratic piece
of two factors of this small quantity and keeping
something that is only linear in the spins in both
of these terms and the sum over the links and the
sum over the sites which can then be combined into
this form where.
There is a constant factor in the energy that
doesn't affect any expectation values and then the
same sort of some overspends with an effective
magnetic field. That depends on this mean spin,
the average magnetization, which is another aspect
of being fields being involved in this calculation.
And I should mention here that we didn't have to
have a slight change in the design convention for
the external magnetic field in order to keep it
consistent with the magnetization defined in the
previous section. So sorry for having to change
that on the fly for that relative negative side is
going to be easy to keep track of in these
calculations and with the. Energy cast into this
approximate form involving this average, this
effective field, depending on the mean
magnetization, the calculation is very much like
what we did back in week three and we can get the
corresponding protection function in terms of the
average, the expectation value of the
magnetization. Which appears both in an overall
exponential factor as well as in the hyperbolic
cosine to the power in that should look familiar
from the non interacting case
and. To get another handle on this expression, we
can take the usual derivative of the log of the
partition function so the derivative of the
elbow's free energy and considering just for a
moment, the fully using model with its interaction
restored, we can see that the total magnetization
sum over all and spin's appears in that energy
through its connection with the the average spin.
So taking the derivative of the Helmholtz free
energy with respect to that external magnetic
field. Gives us another relation between the
expectation value for the magnetization and the
the factors of that.
Expectation value that appear in the main field
partitioned function, and we end up with a still
non-trivial equation involving this expectation
value. Where because it appears on both sides, we
want to consider this as a condition of the
magnetization. That depending on the
dimensionality, these intercepts are data and
exterminate it feel each has to satisfy this
requirement in order to have a self-consistent
solution for the order parameter.
Now solving.
The self consistency condition is equivalent to
finding the roots of the difference between these
two functions. The expectation value that we're
after and this is hyperbolic tangent. And quick
and easy way to. To find those roots and see how
they behave is to look at the intersections of
these two functions on either side of the equals
sign plotted against the order parameter so that
that expectation value is just the constant
straight line with slope one. And this is how the
hyperbolic tangent looks, picking parameters so
that all the factors of BTD and age cancel out
here. And just in two dimensions for illustration.
And as we change the magnetic field H and the
inverse temperature beat up, of course, the
expectation value of M, the dotted line stays the
same, but the hyperbolic tangent gets shifted
around for different magnetic fields. Moving the
intersection from the point zero zero to non-zero
points in which the destines are all
preferentially aligning with that external
magnetic field, and if we decrease the temperature,
then. We see that the intersection moves even
closer to its limiting values out of one or minus
one, corresponding to the ordered phase discussed
in the previous video. I guess the most
interesting case is turning off that external
magnetic field and looking at a few different
temperatures from a low temperature and blue to a
high temperature in red, where the the low
temperature is the interesting one, because it has
three intersections with the expectation value of
the magnetization of the intersection at zero
magnetization. That could correspond to a
disordered phase, but also possible intersections
at
high and low values of the mechanisation. So some
plus or minus and not that. We could interpret as.
As a. Sign of an ordered phase developing
spontaneously, even in the absence of an external
magnetic field for
to guide the spin's alignment. And with just a
little reflection, we can see that in the low
temperature case with these three intersections,
the intersection at the point zero is unstable. If
we fluctuate just a little bit off of that point,
then looking here at the difference between those
two functions that we want to equal zero, we see
that when this difference is positive. That means
that's the magnetization which also appears on the
horizontal axis, is too small compared to the
hyperbolic tangent, and we want to push off to
higher values of the magnetization in order to
recover the.
The solution that we can identify with the ordered
phase, so just as we checked in the asymptotic
limits in the previous video, this Medfield
approximation.
Correctly predicts that at high temperatures, the
easy model is in a disordered phase, while at low
temperatures it is an ordered phase by considering
the slope of the hyperbolic tangent around. This
critical solution of mechanization equals zero,
you can determine the. The temperature at which
the zero solution becomes unstable and the ordered
phase solution develops and the question then is
whether or not there are any discontinuities at
that. At that temperature, which would make a true
critical temperature. So.
We can do this with one further approximation,
just truncating the expansion of the hyperbolic
tangent at Kubic Order, so dropping Firepower's.
And which is permissible when we consider values
of the temperature that are close to this TSI at
which the zero solution becomes unstable. But
still
still smaller than it so that the. As the value of
the magnetization is non-zero, but still very
small in the overall argument of the hyperbolic
tangents itself is therefore still. And a quick
calculation gives us.
An expression for the order parameter that depends
on the square root of the difference between the
temperature. And this this I'll start calling it
the critical temperature, see, because we can see
with a first derivative of this. Word parameter, a
quantity that diverges at the critical temperature
while the order parameter itself is continuous,
establishing a second order phase transition in
any number of dimensions.
Another interesting aspect of this prediction is
the the power dependence that shows up in the
order parameter of this factor of a half is known
as a critical exponent, which here the bean field
approximation predicts to be a half in again in
any number of dimensions, whereas the critical
temperature itself depends on the dimensionality
of the lattice moving to higher and higher
temperatures as the. Number of dimensions
increases.
In one dimensions, this result is completely wrong,
using his work in his PhD thesis in the 1920s
found that in one dimensions there is no phase
transition at all. But in two dimensions on
Secours exact solution, establish that there is
indeed a second order phase transition with a
temperature that's about a factor of two different
from what the battlefield approximation predicts
and a critical exponent. That's all that we get
rolling through the minefield approximation by a
factor of four. And as we go to higher and higher
dimensions, the agreement becomes better and
better with, in fact, exact agreement for the
critical exponents in four or greater dimensions
and
in fact, an exact agreement for the full solution
itself in the forward limit of an infinite number
of dimensions where the the Medfield approximation
becomes exact qualitatively because each spin has
an infinite number of nearest neighbors that allow
it to exactly feel the the expectation value.
Of all of those nearest neighbor spin's. And
because there is no known exact solution in three
or higher dimensions, these this minefield
approximation has to be compared with numerical
calculations, which were mentioned briefly in the
previous video.
Where I noted that a brute force solution with the
computer would take far longer than the age of the
universe. So next week is as part of a broader
application. We'll see some tricks that will allow
quite accurate results for critical temperatures
and critical exponents to be computed in a
reasonable amount of time.