Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
This is the first video for week 10 in the module,
providing a brief summary of the context,
motivations and key learning outcomes for this
week's material on interacting systems, which I
will bring up onto the screen, starting with just
a brief orientation, because getting to the point
that there's not too much left to to go through in
this module, interacting systems is the last. Big
topic building on the concepts, tools and
understanding that we have developed for
statistical systems over the previous nine weeks
of the course, looking at simplified systems that
consist of constituent particles that do not
interact with each other. So I've already said a
few times, but it's no harm in reiterating that
when the particles that compose a large scale
statistical system do not interact with each other,
enormous simplifications can result, which we've
seen even going back to week three on the
canonical ensemble.
How? With or in the absence of interactions, the
objects like the canonical partition function just
break up or factories into products of many
identical partition functions for each individual
product, which we only have to compute once and
are much easier to compute for one particle than
for a whole statistical ensembles worth of
particles.
Of course.
That's not interacting approximation, although it
can describe very well things like the the ferry
pressure that holds up white dwarf stars or the
spectrum of radiation emitted by the sun or by the
cosmic microwave background, it is still an
approximation to the real world in which objects
are able to interact with each other, is dancing
off each other rather than passing straight
through without realizing any other object is in
its way. And there are many important physical
phenomena that rely on the presence of
interactions. The one will be focusing on in in
this week's material is the concept of a phase
transition where systems composed of the same
particles can exhibit extremely different
Large-Scale behavior depending on the control
parameters that we've seen before, things like the
pressure and temperature
and depending on, say, the temperature, we can
have water molecules, H2O that behave like a
liquid of water or like a solid ice or even like a
gas in the form of steam. There are many other
examples ranging from the courts on plasma in the
early universe to Byler graphene in in physics
labs just down the road here, where there are
these transitions between two different types of
behavior in the case of graphene.
Electrical insulator that does not allow electric
field to flow versus a superconductor that allows
an electric field to flow with no electrical
resistance or no loss of energy in the form of
heat. And in all of these cases, the interactions
between the particles in these systems play a key
role. And we will. Get a grip on this with our
usual spin system that was introduced all the way
back in week three or week to even analyzing the
canonical ensemble in week three, where in the.
Not attract, in case we just had this expression,
for the energy of the system in an external field
of strength h where we will assume that all of the
spins are distinguishable by their location in a
fixed grid or a lattice such as the the two
dimensional lattice that is drawn here. We can
label each of these spins by its position and see
whether it is pointing upwards. We'll give a value
of plus one or pointing downwards, which
corresponds to a value of minus one. This is for a
two dimensional lattice and mathematically at
least, we can define a lattices of any dimension.
From zero to infinity, though, only one, two and
three dimensional lattices are physically
realizable in the three spatial dimensions that we
live in. So to get a start, we. Intuitively have
an understanding of what it means for particles
not to interact with each other, they don't even
realize each other, are there? We can put this on
a more rigorous mathematical footing by defining a
system to be not interacting. If the change in its
total energy that results from some change in one
particular degree of freedom is independent of all
of the other degrees of freedom in the system,
which is easy to check for. That system of and not
interacting spins the change in the energy upon
changing spin. I am the only possible way depends
only on speed. I am not from any of the others.
But if we add terms that multiply together two or
more spins. Then this will no longer be the case.
In the simplest possible interaction, given the
the lattice structure mentioned just above, is to
suppose that. Only pairs of spins can interact, so
there's there are no terms in the energy that have
more than two factors of s multiplied together,
and we also assume that spins interact only with
the spins that are closest to them in that fixed
structure of the lattice. So this defines a. So
called nearest neighbor Perre, which is maybe
easiest to get a handle on with some pictures,
where if we pick out one skin in a two dimensional
lattice, we can see that it has. For nearest
neighbors that are the same distance away from,
it's the next closest site after that is a route
to factor further away, about 40 percent along
that diagonal. And we can.
Take or introduced an accounting for these nearest
neighbors by defining what are called links that
connect these nearest neighbor pairs of so-called
sites where the spin degrees of freedom live. And
there are similar concepts like placates or cubes
for two or three dimensional human cells. With a
bit of accounting.
We can figure out how many terms there are in the.
Energy, we have generalize here to include a
nearest neighbor, sphincter interaction, and in
this it's.
A simplification is provided by imagining that the
Latisse is. Connected to itself along its edges
are glued together. You could say similarly to
that old video game, Pacman. I'm sure many other
video games where if you run off one side of the
screen, you just appear. At the same height on the
other side of the screen in this corresponds to
introducing extra links between the sites that one
edge connected to the sites of the other edge,
that these sites are now considered themselves
nearest neighbors. All the sites are therefore the
same. You don't have to worry about whether or not
they may be on the boundary. And it's easy to
count how many links there are in any number of
dimensions. And the only lattice structure we're
considering is the simple cubic lattice, which,
with periodic boundary conditions, is existing on
a dimensional hyperfocus, which is a top logically
flat surface that doesn't introduce any
complications itself. So with those
simplifications, we can just by inspecting this
picture, see that an instant system with periodic
boundary conditions in one dimension involves in
Linc's or in nearest neighbor pairs. That
increases to two and in two dimensions. And you
can work out the generalization to an arbitrary
number of dimensions. So this system is is known
as the easy model, which to my knowledge is the
simplest possible interacting system we can
consider. And in part for that reason, it has been
used and continues to be used in thousands of
scientific studies where the interactions matter.
But the interactions can be modeled just by this
simple nearest neighbor interaction of spin's. And
there is a.
Well, a story that I find very interesting
historically around the development and
understanding of this, this model, it was not
until really the 1960s that it was realized the
easy model could. Provide a very good
approximation to a vast array of systems, both
within and beyond mathematical sciences, including
things like social sciences and in biology, and
maybe as a reflection of. Or one aspect of this
history to take away is just how hard it is to
solve even such a simple system exactly in a
closed form expression. So this was in one
dimension. It's not so hard. It was done as a
project for the fellow or by the fellow using
whose name is now attached to the model. But the
the two dimensional solution, even in a simple
case for the external magnetic field, was turned
off and said to zero was not completed until the
1940s in work by Lawrence Einziger. That is
a famously difficult calculation and has not yet
and may be impossible to reproduce in of three to
three dimensions or higher numbers of dimensions.
Now.
Yeah, and. Another reflection of the difficulty of
solving these interacting systems is that now
instead of being able to consider a single spin
and then just multiply the resulting partition
function to get the overall partition function for
an instant system, that factorization is no longer
possible because of this quadratic term and spins.
And we have to really consider how many terms
there are in the partition function that sums over
all possible microstates, all of the possible ways
the end spins can be orientated. And if we try to
solve this numerically with the computer the way
you did for anomalous diffusion in your project.
You can pretty easily estimate that it would take
even for simple systems with hundreds or thousands
of of particles far below the typical number, ten
to the twenty three that shows up in any physical
systems, a calculation exactly. Evaluating this
partition function numerically on a modern
computer or indeed any computer that can possibly
be foreseen would take far longer than the age of
the universe. So rather than attempting a an exact
solution in our work for this week, we'll just
quickly consider the. Two limits, as we did in
week three of high and low temperature and at high
temperatures of the partition function is. Quite
easy to evaluate, and we find that every possible
micro state effectively has varnishing energy and
equal probability. So in order to distinguish
between those different micro states, which we can
no longer tell them apart by looking at their
energy, which is sort of invisible underneath the
the thermal effects of that high temperature, we
can look at the magnetization, which is the
difference between how many spins are pointing in
one direction versus how many are pointing in the
other direction. And if we normalize by the total
number of spins, that the magnetization is between
zero and one. So in the high-temperature phase,
because the all of the microstates are equally
probable and there are many more microstates with
approximately equal numbers of up and down
pointing spins, we predict that the magnetization
will vanish. And this is called a disordered phase,
reflecting that relatively equal number of up and
down putting spins which can be distributed
randomly or the disordered way throughout the the
lattice. And not surprisingly, in low temperatures,
we end up with a so-called order order phase, and
this is this follows from the sort of calculation
that we did in week three, looking at the low
energy ground states and the the first excited
states of these systems and seeing that the ground
states where all the spins are aligned and the
organization takes its maximum value, one is
dominant with only exponentially suppressed
effects coming in from excited states with with
higher energies and smaller monetizations. So
as the temperature changes from high to low, the
large scale system or the large scale behavior of
the system changes from being disordered with
varnishing magnetization to being ordered with a
nearly maximal magnetization, which identifies the
magnetization as what is known as an order
parameter distinguishing between the possible
phases of the system, whether it is disordered or
disordered.
It is. Possible for.
There to be. Two different or two distinct ways of
getting it from one of those phases to the other,
one of which is a bona fide hit phase transition
and the other of which is a a gradual and smooth
evolution that is is called a crossover in in the
lingo where the the rigorous definition of a phase
transition involves the appearance of a
discontinuity, either in the order parameter
itself or in derivatives of the order parameter
with respect to control parameters. In the case of
the using model, the only control parameter in the
zero field limit is the temperature in any phase,
transition with a discontinuity would occur at a
so-called critical temperature.
So the two. Most common types of face transitions
are known as first order and second order. We're
in a first sort of phase transition, the order
parameter itself is this is discontinuous at that
critical temperature with a.
Not varnishing jump happening
as the temperature passes through the critical
temperature to see a second order phase transition,
the order itself is continuous, but it has a kink
at the critical temperature that corresponds to a
discontinuity or a divergence in its first
derivative. And we will see in the next video,
which I suspect will be shorter than this one,
that.
The easy model. In two or more dimensions has
precisely this second order phase transition in
its order parameter of the magnetization.