Hello and welcome back to statistical physics
this week three overview video on the canonical
ensemble. And before getting into that overview,
just a brief logistical note. Over the past few
days, I've been experimenting with these
recordings and I believe I found a way to reduce
the file size by roughly a factor of five with
only a modest decrease in the video quality. So
that's what I'm trying now. And I want you to let
me know if the quality decrease is more sufficient
or more severe than it seems to me. And any issues
are arising that would motivate going back to the
larger size recordings, but moving on to the
actual content for this week, the canonical
ensemble is the second of three statistical
ensembles we will be looking at in this module. So
we only spent one week on micro canonical ensemble
last week and have moved straight on to the
canonical ensemble, in part related to some
something I emphasized in last week's videos that
the micro canonical ensemble, while it features
this fundamental connection to the. Conserve
energy that is conserve by the first law of
thermodynamics. This requires imagining systems
that are completely isolated from the rest of the
universe, which is not very realistic or relevant,
not the sort of problems that we want to apply
statistical physics to analyze and solve. So the
canonical ensemble gets around this by fixing the
temperature. Instead of imposing conservation of
energy directly on the system being analyzed, the
idea here is that the system we're looking at is
in thermal contact. It's allowed to exchange
energy with a large thermal reservoir. So. Some
other much larger system that sets the temperature
that is then picked up by the system that we are
studying so that the temperature can be considered
fixed for the energy of the system is allowed to
fluctuate while still conserving the overall
energy of the universe through exchanging energy
with this surrounding or external thermal
reservoir that it is in contact with. And a big
part of the lecture notes for this week consist of
putting that basic idea on a more rigorous
mathematical framework. You know, highlight some
of the key features of that in the the wrap up
overview video at the end of the week, rather than
here at the overview,
will say that part of this process introduces a
very important quantity known as the partition
function, which. In essence, it is the the
canonical ensemble that contains all of the
information about the probability space with this
constraint of a fixed temperature and the Kanala
and the partition function for the canonical
ensemble itself can be.
Replaced by or is equivalent to a related quantity
with the dimensions of energy that is known as the
Helmholtz free energy. This is the logarithm of
the partition function. Times the temperature will
pop up in the lecture notes and the only
motivation for swapping back and forth between the
partition function and the Helmholtz free energy
is just sort of ease of calculations and notation
as we derive quantities and analyze systems based
on this canonical ensemble. And maybe I should
reiterate, the basic idea of statistical ensembles
obviously will be reusing some of those concepts
that were developed last week and the micro
canonical context where these statistical ensemble
is a physical system and that evolves through time
probabilistically sampling the possible
microstates that it's microscopic degrees of
freedom can can realize. And subject to the
certain constraints which now for the canonical
ensemble are the six temperature as well as the
conserved particle number that we also had for the
canonical ensemble last week. So the big
difference going from micro, canonical to
canonical is that. Now, instead of the temperature
being a derived quantity based on the conserved
energy, which was the situation for the micro
canonical ensemble in the canonical ensemble, we
have the energy of the system or the average
energy, the expectation value that is a derived
quantity based on the fixed temperature that's set
by the large thermal reservoir. In both cases, the
entropy is another derived quantity, and we'll go
through that a bit more rapidly this week. Having
gotten an introduction to the concept of entropy
last week in the microRNA canonical context, and
one other derived quantity that we look at here is
known as the heat capacity, which basically
dictates how the energy of Earth or the average
internal energy of the system depends on the
temperature. Just as we looked at in the
microeconomics case last week, the temperature
depended on the energy and in agreement. Well. We
get the expected results, which I will revisit and
save for the wrap up overview video at the end of
the week,
the last section of this week's lecture notes is a
detailed investigation of a first application of
the canonical ensemble, which is focusing on the.
The same sort of spin systems that we introduced
last week, that simplest possible mathematics of
degrees of freedom that can take one of two
possible values, either aligned with a magnetic
field that is externally applied or aligned
against it. So the mathematics is. Very similar to
that of flipping a coin. But at the same time, we
can define the energy and temperature and entropy
for this system. In this last subsection of the
lecture notes for this week, we look at the.
Physically observable effects that result,
depending on how much information is knowable
about the spin system we consider. So we look at
two distinct cases, one in which we have a bunch
of spins and we can distinguish between them. We
can tell them apart. And then the the realization.
Focus on here, we suppose that the spin's are
embedded in some solid material, so they have a
definite position and we know that a spin can be
distinguished by looking at each individual
position.
And we contrast this with the case of now that
same bunch of Stenz that's no longer embedded with
a fixed position for a spin, but the spins are
allowed to sort of mix together because they don't
interact. They can even overlap with each other
and occupy the the same points in space so that
there's no way of knowing by any method.
Which spin we we might be looking at when we try
to measure or observe any individual features of
them, so. The information of distinguishing
between the various spins, knowing which spin we
are looking at is something intrinsic to the
system, it's not a matter of practicality whether
we are sufficiently clever to measure this
information in a given realization of the spin
system. It's really something that is intrinsic to
the system itself and depending on. That different
amount of information in the system, we will see
as we go through the notes in some detail.
That's predictions for physically observable
quantities differ depending on the information in
the system, so information is physical. In this
context, and that has many far reaching
implications that remain at the forefront of
modern day research. One example you might have
heard of being the black hole information paradox,
which is dealing with the same sort of issues, the
physically observable consequences of what
information can in principle be determined about a
statistical system, though in the black hole case,
this involves quantum mechanics and the general
relativistic theory of gravity. So that's why
we're looking at our usual spin system as the
example we consider in this module the first
example of the canonical approach which we will
follow in the next couple of weeks by applying the
canonical approach to ideal gases and
thermodynamic cycles. But before that, I will be
back with a wrap up video for this week
summarizing the highlights after you've gone
through those lecture notes.