Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
We'll do a couple of videos on the week six
material introducing the grand canonical ensemble
and we'll do that with the screen shared following
the same pattern as last week. And to start by
putting this week in the context of the overall
module this week, six on the grand canonical
ensemble is. Playing the final piece, the
foundations for the module, we've discussed that
we are going to be looking at three particular
statistical ensembles, which are probability
spaces for systems, either physical or
hypothetical, that sample their microstates as
they evolve in time subject to certain constraints.
And those obvious constraints are conservation of
energy and particle number, which define the micro
canonical ensemble, but require that a micro
canonical system be completely isolated from the
rest of the universe. And if we bring that system
into thermal contact with its surroundings and
allow it to exchange energy while still preserving
a fixed number of particles, that defines the
canonical ensemble that we saw a few weeks ago and
then applied to analyze ideal gases and the role
in thermodynamic cycles. And now we take the next
step and allow our system to exchange both energy
and particles with its surroundings, which defines
the grand canonical ensemble. So now, instead of
just a thermal reservoir that we had in the
canonical ensemble, we promote that to a particle
reservoir, a large external system that our system
of interest is in contact with and can exchange
both energy and particles. And just in the same
way that the thermal reservoir, in the canonical
context, fixed the temperature of our system and
that fixed temperature took the role of the sort
of constraint that was initially played by the
internal energy and the micro canonical case. We
expect that. By exchanging particles with this
large external reservoir or some other quantity
will be kept fixed in that quantity, turns out to
be something known as chemical potential. Which is
unlike the temperature is not something that we
have the sort of day to day experience of working
with, but mathematically it comes from very much
the same sort of considerations. How does the
entropy of the system respond to changes in the
the control parameters? The temperature we saw all
the way back in week two is defined as the inverse
of the interviews, response to a change in the
energy with a fixed number of particles. And to
define the chemical potential, we just interchange
the role of the energy and particle no in that
relation. Also adding a couple of features here, a
overall factor of the temperature and a negative
sign, both of which you can explain qualitatively
and then see how they are applied and how they
impact the quantitative mathematics.
So the temperature. To start with that, we can
recognize this factor of tee times deaths from the
first law of thermodynamics. This has the same
dimensions as entropy and maybe I should not be
jumping around too much in these notes, since you
didn't have to skim back to to where we were. And.
The negative sign here means that with a positive
temperature for a natural system, we generically
expect the chemical potential as a whole to have a
negative value. That is because we've seen both in
general and in particular, examples of the spin
system, an ideal gas that as we have more degrees
of freedom, more particles, those particles can
contain more information and that additional
information corresponds to a larger entropy. So
this partial derivative, how the entropy changes
with respect to the number of particles
generically arises even in fixed energy.
So what we have are generically negative chemical
potentials, and the negative sign is motivated in
order to. Ensure that particles flow from regions
or systems with larger values of the chemical
potential over here, larger means less negative,
smaller in magnitude with a negative sign, and
they flow from those.
Larger chemical potentials to regions with smaller
chemical potentials as though they were, say,
balls rolling down the hill, going from a higher
altitude to a lower one. And that, of course, is
the same thing that happens with the temperature.
Energy flows from hotter systems of higher
temperature to colder systems with lower
temperature.
And by having the negative side there, we get the
same behavior for the chemical potential.
Whereas if we had chosen a different convention
where the chemical potential was defined without
that negative sign, which is mathematically
legitimate, you would have had to keep in mind
that particles would have flown. That flowed in
that case from lower to high, in contrast to the
temperature flying from high to low. So what we
have in this standard convention. Is putting the
temperature and chemical potential on the same
intuitive foundation so that we can think of both
of them in the same way, governing, on the one
hand, the energy flow and on the other hand, the
particle flow of the system, both of which flow
from large to small values. So with that chemical
potential, we are in a position to formally define
a grand canonical ensemble as a statistical
ensemble where both the energy and particle number
are allowed to fluctuate and are no longer
conserved. But they always fluctuate by exchange
with a large external reservoir that fixes both
the temperature of the system and its chemical
potential. Which we will always represent with the
Greek letter MU.
And now let me charge through. The next step in
this this week's material, which is going through
very much the same mathematical consideration as
we did when introducing the canonical ensemble
back in week three, which is proposing a well
motivated on ZATZ for the form of that particle
reservoir, and then showing that the details of
the ANZAAS all drop out in the behavior of the
grand canonical ensemble, allowing us to describe
the system just with reference to that fixed
temperature and fixed chemical potential with no
other information even knowable about the external
reservoir that fixes those parameters. And we do
this so. The same spirit of baking a well
motivated on size by having a reservoir be the
same stuff as the system, but just more of it. We
again introduce a large number of replicas of our
system single out one of them as the system we
actually care about and all of the others form
that reservoir as illustrated in a way that does
not quite fit on my screen.
Here,
so this is a very similar picture to the replicas
that we considered for systems in week three here.
By contrast, we picture an ideal gas with
particles like particles of gas bouncing around
with some momentum and corresponding energy. And
hear all of the boxes that we draw around each of
these replicas is fictitious. It's not something
real. It's something that we mentally impose on
the system in order to organize our calculation.
And the particles are able to freely move from any
of these boxes, any of these replicas to any other.
So the particle numbers, as well as the energy in
each replica is fluctuating, subject to
constraints on the overall system of the small
subsystem of interest, plus the larger reservoir
which that overall total system is we can think of.
That is the entire universe, and that is still
subject to conservation of energy and conservation
particle number.
If we represent the system in terms of the
occupation numbers and occupation probabilities,
recalling that the occupation number is the number
of replicas that occupy a particular microstates
of the single. System of interest. Is the
occupation probability is then the corresponding
probability that. He randomly chosen replica will
be in the corresponding microstates then a lot of
the mathematics works out exactly the same as in
the canonical case. So we don't need to repeat
that here. The number of microstates just counts
how all of those replicas can be assigned to all
of the microstates. And if we assume that the
number of replicas and each occupation number is a
very large number, then we get the same result.
For the total energy of the system, plus its
reservoir, so we now have the usual task of
maximizing that entropy corresponding to
thermodynamic equilibrium, subject to the
constraints, two of which we've seen before.
Probabilities have to add to one in the energy. Of
each replica, which we can express in terms of the
occupation probabilities, has to add up to the
conserved total energy of the universe. And we
have this one new constraints that now the
fluctuating number of particles in each replica,
which we can also cast in the form of a sum over
occupation probabilities, has to add up to the
conserved total number of particles in the
universe. So now when we do our maximization, we
need three legrange multipliers and imposing those
three constraints then fixes the form of each of
those three three parameters in terms of the
overall total energy and particle number that is
conserved in the system. So that's a
straightforward, if sometimes messy calculation.
And at the end of it we find. That's the parameter
Beita is exactly the same inverse temperature as
we found for the canonical. Ensemble, the new
parameter Gamma is not surprisingly related to the
new fixed quantity mbewe the chemical potential,
and there is a proportionality factor of the
temperature.
Essentially providing the the appropriate units in
these relations and the final Louvre's multiplier
can be identified as the grand canonical partition
function, a very direct analogue to the canonical
partition function that we've been working with
for the past three weeks, which is given by the
sum over microstates of this generalized bowsman
factor, which includes not only the energy of the
micro state being sold over, but also its particle
number waited by the chemical potential. So this
is the fundamental quantity from which we will
derive all the other quantities of interest.
Internal energy, entropy, particle number and so
on, which I will make a separate video to keep
these relatively bite sized.