OK, welcome back to the second part of this
summary of the week six material on the Koran
canonical ensemble. So picking up where we left
off with the previous parts, we saw by going
through the the replica trick, just as we did for
the canonical ensemble, that's the great canonical
ensemble can be formulated entirely in terms of
its fixed temperature and chemical potential, with
no reference to any nonsense for the large
external particle reservoir that fixes the
temperature and chemical potential and with which
the system of interest is allowed to exchange
energy and particles. And based on the temperature
and chemical potential, we have the partition, the
grand canonical partition function Z Somji, which
is the sum over all microstates of our system of
this extended bozsum factor that depends on both
the energy and the particle number, both of which
can now fluctuate through exchange with that large
external particle reservoir. And essentially at
this point we are done the grand canonical
partition function. Fully specifiers the. The
information present in our statistical ensemble or
probability space for this system that is allowed
to evolve in time with fluctuating energy and
particle number and the remainder, the last few
pages of the written material for this week are
just going through and completing the mathematical
calculations to extract those derived quantities
of interest from their basis in the grand
canonical partition function. And again,
continuing the analogy with our development of the
canonical ensemble a few weeks ago, we expect the
logarithm of the green canonical partition
function to play a particularly prominent role in
these relations. So just to remind you, now that
the energy and particle number are both
fluctuating, the specific energy or particle
number of that particular microstates is no longer
really a meaningful observable. It's not a
property of the thermodynamic macro state that we
have now become familiar with by working with
ideal gases and through the mix cycles. What is a
property of that micro state is the macro state is
the average internal energy and particle number.
The expectation value, which from the definition
of expectation value, is obtained from the average
over all micro states. So
microstates are the individual pieces with their
corresponding probabilities, something over all of
which gives us information about the large scale
thermodynamic macro state that emerges from the
dynamics, the properties of the degrees of freedom
of which it consists through.
Through the machinery of statistical physics.
In anticipating that both of the internal energy
particle number and entropy will depend on the
logarithm of that grand canonical potential, we
define an analogue of the Helmholtz free energy,
which is this capital five that now depends on
both of these fixed quantities, the temperature
and chemical potential, which just as the
Helmholtz free energy was the negative temperature
at times logarithm of the canonical partition
function. The grand canonical potential is the
negative temperature at times the logarithm of the
grand canonical partition function. Which allows
us to invert this equation, right, the great
canonical partition function in terms of its grand
canonical potential and insert that into the
Boston factor, the Walsman distribution for the
probability of each micro state. And just to
highlight the similarity with the help, those free
energy, this grand economic potential is sometimes
called the land of free energy after the Russian
physicist Lev Landau. And at this point. There are
a few derivatives to grind through, some of which
are straightforward, some of which are messier and
can benefit from some preparatory work. And at the
end of those calculations, we obtain a relation
between these derivatives of the grand canonical
potential that potential itself or equivalently,
the logarithm of the grand canonical partition
function. Along with the internal energy and the
average particle, No. All with three factors,
giving them the the same dimensions, the same
units, and by considering the entropy and plugging
in. The result that we found from. For
maximisation, Villefranche multipliers for the
micro say probability carrying out that
calculation gives us relations among these three
derived quantities and the grand economic
potential. That look. Quite similar to what we had
for the energy and entropy in terms of derivatives
of the Helmholtz free energy, when the particle
number was fixed and the chemical potential was
not in the game, these derivatives of the free
energy with respect to temperature and derivatives
of the ratio of the free energy divided by
temperature of the log of the partition function
also showed up in that case in the canonical
ensemble. So these are the. Useful relations that
we will be. Putting into practice after the break,
in applications of the grand canonical ensemble
focus on quantum systems, which will need some
additional consideration of what exactly makes a
statistical system, quantum or otherwise. But
before we move on to the break and eventually
those applications. We can get a little bit more
insight into the chemical potential just by seeing
how it appears in these sorts of relations that
also involve the energy and entropy. This
connection between energy and tea time times, the
entropy was also something that we saw in the
first law of thermodynamics while considering
thermodynamic cycles last week there was this
relation that the change in energy in a
thermodynamic cycle described by the canonical
ensemble was the heat added, plus the work done on
that system where heat was temperature. At times
the change in entropy and work was negative.
Pressure times the change in volume. And we can
now generalize that, considering the. Particle
number two also be allowed to change in our third
Adamick system. And express the. Entropy is a
function not just of energy and the volume of the
system, but all three parameters, energy, volume
and particle number. This here is just the basic
calculus relation, connecting the derivative to
its partial derivatives with in each case, all but
one of those three parameters kept fixed.
Two of which we can identify as the inverse
temperature and. Negative chemical potential
divided by temperature that we have previously
considered, we're putting everything together and
multiplying through by this factor of one over
temperature, rearranging the terms, we generalize
the first law of thermodynamics further to the
case where the particle number can fluctuate. And
now the total change in energy is the heat added
that changes the entropy, the mechanical work,
that changes the volume with a given pressure and
what we might call the chemical work, which
changes the particle number at a fixed chemical
potential.
This equation eighty six is a generalized
thermodynamic identity that is quite useful if we
want to remember or derive relations between these
various quantities energy, entropy, volume and
particle number. As an example, if we fix the
volume of the particle number, then we immediately
get back to the relation that one over temperature
is the response of the entropy to the energy which
we saw already back in week to. And if we
similarly fix the particle number and the entropy
and look at the idiomatic response of the energy
with respect to a change in the volume, that is
just the pressure we. Introduced when considering
ideal gases. And what is particularly interesting
right now, what we're trying to get, trying to
build up some intuition for the chemical potential
is to fix the entropy sudsing zero, fix the volume
so is zero, and then find that the chemical
potential new is the response of the energy to a
change in particle. No, where that change is done
in a fixed volume and idiomatically so the
chemical potential is essentially how much energy
is added or removed from the system as some
particle or degree of freedom is added or removed.
And we can also from this relation, confirm our
argument earlier that the chemical potential is
generically negative for natural systems because
we've argued that adding degrees of freedom to
systems tends to increase its entropy. And in
order to keep that entropy fixed, we have to
counteract that increase in the way to do that,
the natural system with positive temperature is to
decrease the energy. So whenever the particle
number increases, the energy has to decrease. So
the overall sign of that partial derivative is
negative and vice versa if the particle number
decreases at fixed entropy. So that is the
completion of the introduction, at least of the
final of the three statistical ensembles that we
consider in this module, we now have micro,
canonical,
canonical and grand canonical ensembles
appropriate for different situations where. Our
probabilistic system is sampling states through
time, evolution subject to different constraints,
fixed energy and particle number for micro
economical temperature and particle number four,
canonical and fixed temperature and chemical
potential for grand canonical. And once we get
back from the break, we will.
Dive into quantum statistics and use that as the
playground to apply the creative canonical
ensemble, learn about various sorts of quantum
statistical systems, how they behave and connect
that to some familiar. Phenomenon like the. The
sun shining in the sky for now, though, we have
all the basic material and can take a break to
incorporate it and.
Gain more comfort in familiarity with these
foundations.