Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
This is the second video for week nine in the
module, wrapping up the brief summary of context,
motivations and key learning outcomes for this
week's material on quantum gases of fermions,
which I will bring back up onto the screen here,
picking up where previous video left off at the
Fermi function, which had been introduced by
putting the the large scale macroscopic or
thermodynamic properties of the system that into
this equation of state. In this case, the average
particle density number of particles divided by
the volume expressing that in terms of an integral
over the particle energies with a non relativistic
setting for massive particles with relatively
little energy that is given just by their momentum
squared divided by twice the mass and in the set
up here, keeping the cost of factors separate from
the family function, we saw that at the very
function shown here resembles the average
occupation number, which means that its behavior
at low temperatures shown by the solid black curve
in this plot we went through in some detail in the
previous video
corresponds simply to a step function where all of
the energy levels that have energy is less than
the chemical potential. You are occupied or filled
by the maximum single possible for me on that they
can contain and all of the energy levels with
energies greater than the chemical potential have
an occupation. Number zero, they are unoccupied or
empty. And this approximation expressing the
family function as a step function that is one for
low energies and zero for higher energies at small
temperatures, provides the sort of dramatic
simplification that allows these calculations to
be computed in the space of these gaps, providing
both the particle number as well as the average
energy density where the. Integral to a computer
for the energy density is going to differ just by
an extra factor of the energy showing up in the
argument right there. So an energy or a power of
energy, each of the three hands, rather than the
square root, which is exactly as we saw for the
energy density compared to the particle. No
density for the photon gas last week. So that is a
generic connection between the energy and particle
number, regardless of whether particles are bosons,
fermions, not relativistic or ultra relativistic.
And what we're going through this, it's worth
highlighting the Fermi energy, which at low
temperatures is simply the chemical potential and
is the boundary between those filled energy levels
with energy is smaller than the free energy and
the empty energy levels with higher energies that
is given by the particle. No density in over the
race to the power of two thirds coming just from
converting the particle. No density computed above.
And by carrying out the analogous computation for
the internal energy density, you could find that
the average energy for each of these particles at
low temperatures is given by just a little over
half of the Fermi Energy particular nice, odd
round fraction of three fifths
relating the average energy to the average
particle. No. In the rest of the way to the
equation of state requires computing, the pressure,
which requires fixing both the entropy and
particle number in the entropy, is actually an
interesting case in this very low temperature
regime where if we have all of the energy levels
up to the Fermi energy filled, all of the energy
levels with higher energies are unoccupied. That
is a single microstates for this quantum system.
And it turns out to be the only micro state that
we are actually. Accessing with a non-zero
probability in the the limit of low temperatures.
So expressing the entropy in the generic way as
the sum over my cross over the probabilities of
occupying microstates, there's only a single term
in the sum, and it is one times the log of one,
which is simply zero. So the entropy of a low
temperature firmly on gas is zero. And that gives
direct relations between the pressure, the energy
density and the number density, which if we plug
in the very energy in place of the chemical
potential, hmu and define the density as a row.
Just a new symbol for this same concept. We've
been discussing the average particle number per
unit volume. There is an interesting relation
between the pressure and density, which does not
vanish as the temperature goes to zero. This is
also the case, as we can see, for the energy of
the gas and its particles. That also remains
non-zero in the limit of a vanishing temperature,
which is a sharp contrast with the classical non
relativistic gas where we saw that the energy was
three 1/2 times empty and vanished as that
temperature goes to zero. And similarly, the
pressure was given by empty overview by the ideal
gas law equals empty and also vanished in zero
temperature limit. And that is not the case for
fermions simply because it's only possible to have
a single ferme on occupying any energy level with
that lowest energy that we can set to zero. If we
have more fermions of that coming from a positive
chemical potential, then we have to have fermions
occupying energy levels with higher volumes of the
energy, even an absolute zero temperature, which
leaves a strictly positive average energy density
and a strictly positive pressure, as is shown in
the zero temperature limit of of this plant here,
where instead of going straight to zero like a
classical gas, the pressure for the fermions gas
ends up at a positive value at zero temperature
and in the high temperature limit where it
approaches the classical behavior. We see the
onset of that linear dependence that we would
expect from our previous work. So that is the the
key takeaway for low temperature for on is
compared to the high temperature, a classical case
for these non relativistic particles. And there is
some discussion here of some physical effects of
this non-zero pressure at low temperatures, which
in. Astrophysical contexts allows for
a
famous cosmic phenomenon known as a type one, a
supernova that precedes briefly in the following
way the type of a supernova involves what's called
a white dwarf star, which is a star that has
burned all of its its nuclear fuel. That's in
stars like our sun that are shining brightly and
producing lots of heat. They're doing that for
nuclear fusion involving hydrogen and helium. And
eventually, after a long amount of time, a star
made up all of that hydrogen and helium fuel and
no longer be able to generate heat and light and
energy and pressure through the source of nuclear
fusion reactions. And that is what characterizes
the white dwarf star, all of the. Fuel for those
hydrogen and helium nuclear reactions in a white
dwarf has been consumed and is no longer providing
the energy that can counterbalance the enormous
gravitational attraction of the huge amount of
matter present in these stars. And what keeps the
star from collapsing all the way down to a black
hole under the weight of its of its mass of matter
is precisely the non-zero pressure of the of the
gas of the electrons, which are fermions that this
star contains.
And in the in the case where this white wordstar
may be part of a binary system with some companya
that is still burning, it's nuclear fuel and
emitting heat and light and matter, that matter
can gradually accumulate on this way for a start
up being held up by the zero temperature pressure
of its four, its low temperature, me on gas up to
the point that the pressure becomes so large that
new types of fusion reactions involving carbon and
oxygen rather than hydrogen and helium are able to
begin. And once they begin, they proceed very
quickly. And in the space of just a few seconds,
they release something like five billion times the
amount of energy that our sun is putting out,
which is precisely the supernova explosion that we
can observe in the sky and can actually use to
establish the existence of a mysterious phenomenon
known as dark energy is showing that the universe
is not only expanding, but is expanding more and
more rapidly as time goes on. A discovery from the
late 90s that was awarded the Nobel Prize about 10
years ago. Now, one interesting thing about these
Wentworth stars that I glossed over in the
interests of time is that.
Even though their temperatures are small compared
to their energies, they have a fear of the energy
of something like a billion Kelvin. The
temperatures in the interior of the white dwarf
are about 10 million Kelvin, which is relatively
large by our everyday standards. It's still small
enough compared to the very energy identified as
the chemical potential that we can approximate
white dwarfs very well as a zero temperature
firmly on gas. But the temperature is actually so
large that if we convert units to units of mass or
emit our mega electron volts.
You find that the Fermoy energy, the chemical
potential of this electron gas is comparable to
the electron reste energy itself, suggesting that
relativistic effects may be worth considering and.
To go through this last section quite quickly, the
key takeaway in the context of a relativistic
fermoy on gas is that it behaves much like the
relativistic photon gas we consider last week. We
can express the energy in terms of the frequency.
Of these massless fermions, an example of which in
physics are given by neutrinos and carrying out
these same. Considerations and manipulations, as
for the photon. Yes, we conclude that here the
chemical potential is zero here to an excellent
approximation and. The integration over the
frequencies of these relativistic electrons
produces expressions that differ from the the case
of the photon gas only in the relative sine
between the two terms in the denominator. And
again, the energy density and particle no density
differ only by a factor of that energy. Each FA
Omega showing up in the inter grand here and
carrying out these integrals. Again, these are fun
integrals that can be looked up or computed
through some symbolic mathematic program like
maple or mathematical. And computing the pressure
again gives a equation of state very much like the
ideal gas law, just with a slightly different
causal factor involving the remains at a function
that comes out to be not so different from the
classical case that it will reduce to at high high
temperatures. So that is where we will end with
not interacting ideal gases and other idealise
systems of not interacting particles and the
remainder of the module after this will take just
a quick look at appreciating the roles and effects
of interactions, both in the types of phenomenon
or phenomena that they can produce, such as phase
transitions, as well as the practical matter of
how they complicate the analysis and calculations
that we would have to do in statistical physics in
order to make predictions for interacting systems.