Hello and welcome back to a statistical physics.
This is the overview video for a week for an ideal
Agassiz. And before diving into that, let me try
something different in case my face might be less
interesting than seeing how this overview matches
up with the written material. Now that I have
changed the. Software being used to record this
video, I should be able to share my screen and
pull up. That's written material on the lecture
transcript and won't go through the. The full
transcript here, but just be able to point out
where the.
Comments I'm making correspond to the text that
you have available to read at your leisure. So as
I said, week for high gases is coming after a few
weeks of Quick Hits, looking at slightly different
topics, first probability foundations than the
formulation of the micro canonical statistical
ensemble and then the formulation of the canonical
ensemble. And now week four, we're. Dive again a
bit more deeply to the first really large scale
application of these canonical ensembles to
physical systems that historically have been very
important to the development of statistical
physics and remain a very.
Good starting point, a good approximation for a
large number of applications. So these are ideal
gases and specifically a simplified ideal gases
that neglect the effects of quantum physics. The
terminology for that is they are classical. They
neglect the effects of special relativity. They
are non relativistic, and they neglect the effects
of interaction between the particles out of which
this gas is made.
And that is the terminology for ideal gases and
really when we say we're neglecting those
interactions, you mean that they don't impact the
energy of the particular micro state, which is
then just given by the direct some over the
energies of all of the individual particles? And
there is a. Bit of a song and dance, so we have to
go through even to take those energies and define
the partition function with them because the
partition function is a sum over microstates, we
need to make sure that this sum is well defined in
the sense of the microstates are accountable. We
do that with an onsides which turns out to be.
Justified by quantum physics as quantum physics is
not a prerequisite for this module, it is just
Trainspotting exercise for those of you who have
previously taken it to recognize the particle in a
box calculation. Which gives us a well-defined.
Canonical partition function, so we fix the number
of particles, we fix the temperature by having our
ideal gas in contact, thermal contact with a large
thermal reservoir, and then we are able to come up
actually with two distinct partition functions,
both of which are built on this single particle
case. And they differ by.
Assuming whether or not the particles are
distinguishable or indistinguishable in the
disclosable case, the partition function is just
in factors of the single particle partition
function, whereas in the indistinguishable case,
there is a overcounting factor that comes in,
turns out to be a factor in factorial. Assuming
that all of the particles in this gas have. Unique
momento, which is an assumption and a footnote
here that we will get back to when we look at
quantum statistics after the term break. So given
the partition function for both those
distinguishable and indistinguishable cases, all
of the derived quantities that were interested in
predicting from the underlying properties of this
gas come straight out of that partition function.
And most elegantly, in the form of the Helmholtz
free energy, which is directly related to the
logic of that partition function, we get the
average internal energy which depends quite
directly on the conserve quantities or the fixed
quantities of the canonical ensemble, the
temperature and the number of particles, as well
as the entropy. Which turns out to depend on
whether or not the particles are distinguishable
in a way that the energy, the average internal
energy does not. And this has
make some sense if we think of the entropy is
measuring the logarithm of the number of
microstates with the given energy, that depends on
how well we can distinguish the different
particles that form those microstates from each
other. And another aspect of distinguished ability
and the physical effects of pure information
content of the system comes from what is known as
the mixing entropy, where the basic idea to
overview is shown in this diagram that I will try
to fit onto my screen as best I can. We're
similarly to the consideration of heat exchange in
the micro economical context back in week two here,
we consider particle exchange in the canonical
context. So we take two canonical ensembles with
the same fixed number of particles, fixed volume
and fixed temperature. Remove this barrier between
them, let them exchange particles and then
reinsert that barrier. And ask, how does the
entropy change as we go through this process from
one step to the next? The answer turns out to
depend on whether or not the particles are
distinguishable in particular, so in the
indistinguishably case, there is essentially no
difference whether the. Barrier is there or not,
we can make the approximation that. Reinserting
the barrier leaves us with a similar number of
particles on each side. This was a trick that was
proposed way back in the 70s. And it's sort of
like the situation. If you're open and close the
door, a door between two identical rooms, nothing
very dramatic happens in that process is
reversible without changing the entropy of the
universe. In the distinguishable case, instead of
opening and closing a door between two identical
rooms where doing something more like pouring milk
into tea, that once the particles from the two
systems mix, there's sort of no way to reverse
that mixing and disentangle them. And that
manifests itself in the form of what is known as a
mixing entropy, where after removing the barrier,
the total entropy of the system increases by this
non-zero amount. That fact increases linearly with
the number of particles in the system.
The last topic, which is a bit of a transition
from the. Basic framework of ideal gas is in the
canonical ensemble to the following week dynamical
cycles looks at the pressure, the ideal gas law
and equations of state law generally. Based on the
observation from some of the. Fundamental
definitions, the petition function and Helmholtz
free energy depend not just on the number of
particles or the fixed temperature, but also on
the volume into which we place this ideal gas. And
this identifies that volume as what is known as a
control parameter, something that we can imagine
controlling in an experimental setup. And
interesting things happen when we consider the
response of the system to variations in this
control parameter subject to certain conditions,
as usual, the condition we look at here is keeping
the entropy constant, which defines what are known
as adiabatic processes. These are important enough
to merit. Their own fancy terminology, and in
particular, the idiomatic change in the internal
energy of a system upon changing its volume
defines the pressure. Which then, as we go through
that confrontation, shows up in the form of an
ideal gas law relating. The. Large scale.
Properties of the system, its pressure volume,
number of particles and temperature in the
relation that is known for somewhat historical
reasons as an equation of states where the state
being discussed is not the microstates that have
played a prominent role in the formulation of the
micro and canonical ensembles, but rather the
thermodynamic state or macro state of the system
as a whole characterized by these properties and
the internal energy. And it is the.
Historical development of these concepts of states,
macro states and equations of states that connect
to the. Thermodynamic cycles and the. Application
now of the ideal gas law as a further construction
built on top of the framework of the canonical
ensemble that is coming up in the following week.
But before that, I will let you read the. Written
material in detail and come back with the
subsequent wrap up going into a bit more detail
about the key points to take away from this.