Hello and welcome back to the end of week two of
statistical physics, this is the wrap up video
that we'll spend roughly 10 minutes summarizing
the highlights and key learning outcomes, the
micro canonical ensemble. This is the first of the
three statistical ensembles we're going to be
focusing on throughout this module. And of those
three, the micro canonical is arguably both the
most fundamental and least useful. So recalling
that statistical ensembles are what we get when we
allow a system with a large number of particles or
10 to the power twenty three or more to evolve in
time with certain constraints imposed and
depending on what constraints are imposed, we end
up with different statistical ensembles. And in
the case of the micro canonical ensemble, the
constraints are conservation of energy and
conservation of particle number or the number of
degrees of freedom. And that is, I call that the
most fundamental because conservation of energy we
now know is a truly fundamental and generic
feature of physics resulting from a nervous
theorem. And when statistical physics was first
being developed in the eighteen hundreds, this was
not yet well understood and conservation of energy
became known under the more grandiose title of the
first law of thermodynamics. On the other hand,
having the energy of a particular system be
conserved has the implication that this system has
to be completely isolated from the rest of the
universe, which is the sense in which the micro
canonical ensemble is the least useful of the
three? Because that sort of complete isolation in
practice is not possible. And it's not the
conditions that we're interested in when we think
of doing observations or experiments on physical
systems, which necessarily imply some exchange of
energy between us, the observers and the system.
Despite that, because of the foundation and
conservation of energy, the micro canonical
ensemble is the best starting point and a good
place to develop some of the key concepts of
statistical ensembles more generally, the first of
which being the concept of thermodynamic
equilibrium, which is extremely important and will
be the condition that we focus on throughout this.
This module, non equilibrium, statistical
mechanics and not equilibrium thermodynamics is
extremely interesting, but also extremely
difficult and complicated. You have to do a lot
more mathematical work in order to say in order to
make a lot significantly weaker statements about
non equilibrium behavior of statistical systems.
So the thermodynamic equilibrium is to some extent
a simplifying assumption, but it also is a rich
field in its own right, as it describes sort of
the everyday conditions we're familiar with, where
the systems are existing in a fairly steady,
fairly stable state of being. I've tried to avoid
using the state there because I don't want to
confuse the condition of thermodynamic equilibrium
with the concept of microstates that describe the
distribution and characteristics of all the
microscopic degrees of freedom within the overall
large scale system. Anyway, looking at
thermodynamic equilibrium. This week we saw two
different ways of defining it. The first of which
is specific to the micro canonical ensemble and
states that thermodynamic equilibrium corresponds
to every possible micro state having the same
probability. And this may be surprising because it
means that, again, going back to the example of
the air in this room, if I consider a micro state
in which all of this er happens to be often that
quarter to my right, that particular micro state
is just as probable as the microstates I'm
currently in or the air is evenly distributed and
I'm not gasping for breath. And the reason that we
don't expect all of the air to be off in that
corner is because there are many more micro states
with a fairly even distribution of the molecules
compared to the number of microstates with that
more specialized. More surprising large scale
configuration of the system, and this brings us to
the concept of entropy. The first derived quantity
that we looked at in the micro canonical ensemble
and essentially in thermodynamic equilibrium,
entropy amounts to the logarithm of the number of
microstates, which means that the more microstates
there are, the the larger the entropy is. And I
should add as an aside here, that the number of
microstates is an extraordinarily large number for
statistical systems. We've been talking about the
ten to the power. Twenty three degrees of freedom
or particles in these systems. The different ways
that those ten of the power twenty three molecules
can be arranged typically gives rise to something
more like ten to the power, ten to the power,
twenty three microstates. So that even taking the
logarithm of that quantity, we still have an
enormous entropy of order. Avogadro's number.
Now, one property of entropy is similar to energy
and particle number is extensively the statement
that all of these quantities tend to grow as the
size of the system grows. This is sort of
tautological almost in the number of degrees of
freedom. And as each of those degrees of freedom
typically has a constant amount of energy
contributing to the total. It's also clear to see
that the energy increases.
We saw two different ways in which the entropy can
increase when considering larger systems. If the
larger overall system is made up of some systems
that are isolated from each other than the
entropies of those isolated subsystems, simply add
just the same way that the particle number or the
energies add. Something more interesting happens
if those two subsystems are brought together and
allowed to exchange energy between themselves. So
each subsystem is no longer governed by the
microeconomic ensemble. But the overall collection
of both of them still is the overall. Some of
their energies is still conserved. But because the
subsystems can now exchange energy, there are more
possible microstates that this micro canonical
system can adopt, which implies a larger entropy,
which is a form of the second law of
thermodynamics, that if we start off with isolated
systems and bring them together, we see that the
entropy generically increases. There is a formal
possibility that it may stay constant, but that
only happens in extremely special circumstances.
And so the formal statement is that the entropy
never decreases as isolated subsystems are brought
together and allowed to exchange energy. And by
doing some more extensive work that we're omitting
in this molecule, in this module, it can be
established that generically the entropy never
decreases as time passes, no matter what sort of.
Situations you consider so long as those occur in
the context of an isolated system that is that
doesn't have the opportunity to sort of hide
entropy in its surroundings in any way. So a key
takeaway there is the second law of thermodynamics.
The entropy never decreases and generically
increases. This allows us to introduce a more
generic definition of thermodynamic equilibrium,
which is that this is the thermodynamic
equilibrium corresponds to maximal entropy
from which if we then maximize our expression for
the entropy, we can derive our previous definition
of thermodynamic equilibrium in terms of equal
probabilities by using a Legrand's multiplier,
imposing the condition that the sum of the
probabilities of all microstates have to always
add to one part of our definition of probability
last week, and that LeoGrande multiplier trick is
going to pop up a few more times later in this
module, which is why I mentioned it here. Wrapping
up the last topic we looked at was the temperature,
which in the micro canonical context is also a
derived quantity rather than something fundamental.
So we proceeded by stating the formal definition
of the temperature and then showing that it
produces sensible results that we would expect
from everyday experience. And that formal
definition looks at how much the entropy can
change if the energy of the system were to change
with a fixed number of degrees of freedom. So that
partial derivative change in entropy as a result
of change in energy is actually the inverse
temperature, which we can try to intuitively
understand by thinking about some special cases
when we have. Well, we see later on with the
example of the spin system that the the minimal
temperature, which is non-zero, corresponds to the
single minimum energy state, so that adding a bit
of energy can have a relatively large effect
because there are relatively few microstates to
start off with. And adding that same bit of energy,
if we were approaching the infinite temperature
limit with an equal number of up and down spins
would have a much smaller effect. So one over tea
being much smaller corresponds to a larger t a
larger temperature in a self-consistent way. So
that's the qualitative view, how to understand
that partial derivative and using that spin system,
we went through a fairly detailed calculation that
started its life as a tutorial exercise to find
that the temperature in the limit of a large
number of particles, which is the generic
conditions we're always considering, is
approximately negative. In times H squared over E
or H is the strength of that external magnetic
field that introduces the temperature to the spin
system. So this is unusual in that we could have
negative temperatures. The temperature can diverge
when there are an equal balance number of spins
aligned and anti aligned with the magnetic field.
And there's also a non-zero minimum temperature.
The temperature for the spin system cannot be zero.
Some of those strange results are due to working
with the spin system. Some are due to working in
the micro canonical ensemble. But there are still
other results that agree with what we would expect.
First of all, we see that the temperature is an
intrinsic quantity rather than a sorry, an
intensive quantity rather than extensive quantity.
I misspoke earlier. So if we imagine devising a
system into isolated subsystems, those subsystems
have the same temperature as the original system.
The temperature is independent of the size of the
system. We also computed heat exchange for a
similar.
Thought experiment of taking two systems, putting
them in thermal contact and then isolating them,
finding with some assumptions about the the
entropy being continuous and differentiable, you
were able to expand the entropy in a Taylor series
and find that heat always flows. Or I should say
energy always flows from the hotter system to the
colder system of bringing their their temperatures
closer together. This is, of course, what we would
expect. And we will revisit this energy flow in
more detail later on in the module where we
formally introduced the definition of heat. For
now, though, we are going to build on that example
to in the coming week to find the canonical
ensemble where the temperature is the the
constrained quantity as opposed to the energy. So
let me
leave you there with that brief look ahead.