Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
This is the second video for week seven going over
quantum statistics and restarting the screen share
to take a look at the material for this week. Just
checking by recalling that in the first video we.
Reviewed the or summarized the fundamental
distinction between quantum and non, quantum or
classical statistics, which is the approach that
we take to defining the microstates over which we
have to sum to compute the partition function or
grant canonical partition function that defines
the systems we work with. And in the quantum case,
the sum over microstates has to take the form of a
sum over the quantize energy levels. In each
energy level, considering all possible occupation
numbers, the number of particles that energy level
could have. And this contrasts with the classical
treatments of systems with discrete quantize
energy levels, that classical treatment where we
sum over each particle and consider all of the
possible energies that could have leading to
overcounting that can become tricky to correct.
That produces a form of statistics that is known
as maximal Boltzmann's statistics. And in the
quantum case of something over energy levels and
occupation numbers, there are two different
possible versions of quantum statistics, depending
on.
Depending on whether those particles are bosons or
fermions, which differ in terms of the possible
occupation numbers that they have, so in Section
seven point three and seven point four, we go
through the quick computation of the grand
canonical partition function for generic bosun's,
first giving rise to those Einstein statistics and
then for generic fermions for it's a very similar
calculation as advertised. We sum over each energy
level and consider all the possible occupation
numbers where for boatswain's, if we consider the
simple case of a single energy level, then all we
have is the sum over occupation numbers from zero
to infinity, which gives a straightforward
geometric series. So long as the chemical
potential is small enough for this series to
converge. And physically it has to be to keep the
of the Grand Canyon a potential from from
diverging. There are no infinities in any physical
systems. And because we're only considering ideal
gases or ideal systems of not interacting
particles, the generalization from a single energy
level to many energy levels is is very
straightforward. The total political number and
the total energy of the microstates, it's just a
linear sum over the occupation numbers in the
overall sum of sums over occupation numbers for
each energy level, zero energy level one all the
way up to the the last energy level. There could
be infinitely many energy levels so long as they
are accountable. All of those sums factories into.
The combination down here, so.
The generalised bilston factor breaks up into a
product of factors for his energy level, we can
rearrange those into sums for his energy level,
compute them all independently and end up with
just a simple product. We can also get that same
sort of behavior from the Maxwell Boltzmann grand
canonical partition function that was computer
back in seven point one, taking the classical
approach to a system with quantized energy levels.
And we can see the things looked relatively
different, there's an exponential of an
exponential in the next lobotomy case, classical
physics of the Bose Einstein case is the product
over these factors of one minus the exponential.
The case for fermions that gives rise to Firmage
Iraq statistics. Is is different itself, though,
the calculation is essentially identical to the
Bose Einstein one where. The sun's over energy
levels now have only two possible occupation
numbers, zero and one in each case, we can
redistribute the generalized bolson factor amongst
all those sums and end up with just the product of
this one, plus the exponential factor.
Almost the inverse of the Hoseason case with a
different side between the constants and the
exponential, which turns out to be a highly
significant, at least in. A certain regime where
quantum effects are significant.
But as mentioned in the previous video, as well as
in the material. In some regimes, we expect the
quantum approach to provide a very accurate
approximation to the true quantum behavior, which
is the reason that we observe classical physics
and in everyday phenomenon, even though they arise
from quantum physics at a more fundamental
underlying level. And a brief consideration of the
exercise we went through in week three, looking at
the high and low temperature limits of spin
systems with quantize energy levels, leads us to
recognize that the limit in which quantum physics
should reduce to the classical behavior is exactly
the high temperature limit. However, there is some
subtlety to considering the high temperature
limits in the grand finale ensemble, where the
particle number can fluctuate. And it turns out in
the calculation that we go through in this final
Section seven point five, that the particle number
starts to diverge, become infinite if we take the
temperature to infinity to a very high temperature
limit while keeping everything else fixed.
And we see that by going through the the exercise
of computing, the average particle number using
the basics, the fundamentals for the grand
economical ensemble that we developed in week six
before the break, writing down the Grand Chronicle
petition functions computer to both. Determining
the corresponding. Grant canonical potentials and
from them the average particle numbers, which in
all three cases of classical Maxwell Bowsman
statistics, those Einstein statistics for quantum
bosons and Fermi, direct statistics for quantum
fermions, we end up with a sum. Over the average
occupation numbers for each energy level where the
form of the average occupation number in the three
cases classical case, the Bozena case and the
Fermoy on a case are. Similar enough that we can
see they all reduced to each other when these
constants plus minus one factors in the quantum
case are negligible compared to the exponential
factors. So this very large exponential factor
corresponds to a very large argument for the
exponent, this energy level minus chemical
potential or the, I should say, the energy of the
energy level, minus the chemical potential divided
by the temperature very large, which is not what
we might have expected for a high temperature
limit. When the temperature gets large with
everything else fixed, this ratio naively goes to
zero rather than a very large number. And we can
see that the average occupation numbers then
become very large, especially in the business case
for the occupation number actually goes to
infinity thanks to that pesky negative sign in the
denominator as the exponential factor approaches
one. And this argument approaches zero, and this
is exactly where we expect the greatest
disagreements between classical and quantum
statistics. There's a very high probability that
multiple particles are occupying the same energy
levels, which was what led to the breakdown of the
classical approach we took earlier in the cure
that we have to impose is recognizing, as we said
earlier, that the high temperatures lead to very
large numbers of particles of infinite numbers of
particles if there are an infinite number of
energy levels. And in order to retain a finite
number of particles, that is what we have in any
physically, physically existing system, it is
finite. In order to keep the particle no finite,
we have to adjust the chemical potential new at
the same time as we adjust the temperature t and
in particular, the chemical potential has to go to
very large negative numbers faster than the
temperature goes to very large positive numbers or
in mathematical terms, the chemical the negative
chemical potential has to be much larger than the
temperature, even as the temperature becomes much
larger than one in the high temperature limit. So
this is the true high temperature limit where we
should expect quantum and classical physics to to
agree, to predict, to make the same predictions.
And the example of this is shown in this figure.
Which is not quite fitting on the screen,
this figure showing. Precisely that average
occupation number for the three cases of classical
maximum bolstered statistics, the Bose Einstein
statistics of bosons in the very direct statistics
of fermions as a function of that argument of the
multifactor energy minus chemical potential
divided by tea here with the irrelevant unit
conversion factor. So the high temperature limit,
where negative view is much larger than both the
energy and the temperature t corresponds to the
right side of this plot where we see all of the
classical and quantum predictions. Coming together
exponentially, quickly, so that they cannot be
distinguished by even when this ratio is only a
factor of a few in the opposite limits of low
temperatures is where we see dramatically
different behavior, both for the classical case,
which smoothly increases exponentially as the the
temperature decreases as that
as a combination of temperature and chemical
potential decreases to define the the low
temperature regime. You mentioned above that the
average occupation number for those Einstein
statistics actually diverges as this ratio
approaches zero, as the energy approaches the
chemical potential, whereas the very different
accesses can only interpolate between zero and one,
syntactically reflecting the rule for fermions
that at most one odd can be in any energy level.
So this low temperature quantum regime where those
odds and fermions behave much differently from
each other as well as from classical expectations,
is what we will dig into over the next couple of
weeks.