Hello and welcome back to a statistical physics.
This is the first video for eight in the module
and following the pattern established with this
will provide a brief summary of the context,
motivations and key learning outcomes to take away
from the asynchronous materials for this week. And
speaking of those materials, bring them up on the
screen here and see where we are in the module and
where we are headed. So indicate we are digging
into our application of the grand canonical
ensemble in the context of quantum gases of
boatswain's. The first of two weeks investigating
in some detail the behavior of quantum systems for
the different types of particles that we
introduced in in last week's material in quantum
statistics. So just as a brief refresher, the
grand canonical example that we are applying
allows both of the energy and particle number of
our statistical system to fluctuate through
exchange with some large external reservoir. And
we are gaining familiarity with this approach to
analyzing statistical systems by considering
quantum systems this way, quantum gases of those
arms where
quantum as opposed to classical statistical
physics is defined by how we define the
microstates being considered and the definition of
the fundamental grand canonical partition function
that defines our system and its. It's physical
behavior, so in the classical approach, the
partition function was defined by considering all
the particles in the system one by one, and
something over all the possible energies that they
could have in the quantum approach. We saw that
deficiencies in that classical approach could be
fixed or corrected by instead summing over every
discrete energy level in the system and
considering all the possible occupation numbers
that that energy level could have. Where the
possible occupation numbers distinguish between
the two classes of particles of the universe,
bosons that behave in the familiar way where each
energy level can have any non-negative number of
identical particles zero, one, two and so on, as
opposed to fermions for only a maximum single
particle in energy level is possible. So this week
we are focusing on the ozone in case you are
quantum gases of bosons.
Beginning from the grand finale, coopetition
function and potential that were derived in
general terms the last week, looking at quantum
statistics in the abstract, where these. Partition
function and potential depend on the as yet
unspecified energies of the energy levels that are
being sent over to define the system, and in
general, there are two possibilities that we can
consider
characterized by how the energies of the energy
levels depend on the quantized momenta of the
particles that are allowed by by quantum physics,
which we are again doubting as a Anzac's or
conjecture.
Rather than relying on any prior knowledge of
quantum mechanics or quantum physics and the non
unrealistic case we already looked at back in the
week for the classical ideal gas, where we
introduced this relativistic and non relativistic
terminology, and in the quantum context, it turns
out to be a significantly simpler calculation on
the calculation calculational level to focus on
the relativistic case, which is epitomized by.
The behavior of quantum particles of light, what
are known as photons,
these photons, these particles of light are as
relativistic as particles can get in the sense
that they are characterized by energies that are
linearly proportional to the photon momentum as
opposed to the quadratic dependence that we looked
at from the non relativistic case back before the
term break.
And going through the same exercise of quanti
using these momenta.
In a fixed volume V, they can depend only on
integer multiples of this combination pie over the
linear length of that volume times Planck's
constant each bar, we are able to connect these
photon energies that are now quantized to the
behavior, to the wavelength or equivalently the
frequency of the photons interpreted as radiation,
as particles of light, where the conventional
presentation of the conventional definition of a
photon energy is given in terms of its frequency
multiplied by playing scales to convert units
appropriately to get an energy.
So plugging in that background, specifying photons
by how their energy levels depend on their
quantized momenta wavelengths and frequencies. We
can benefit significantly from the simplification
that photons are very easy to create and destroy,
which allows us to consider the system and to
limit where the chemical potential vanishes. And
this is the key simplification that provides the.
Much more streamlined and much more accessible
calculations compared to the the nonrelated tested
case. That while there's still interesting in the
Nominals Vista case, we can consider a quantum
phase transition in a new state of matter known as
those Einstein condensation related to the Bose
Einstein statistics of non relativistic
boatswain's, that turns out to be much more
complicated than the simple case of photons, which
is all that we will focus on in this module.
Though we could discuss the nominals of the case,
at least in general terms, in the synchronous
session if there is interest in doing so. So with
that background set up, it is a fairly
straightforward calculation to. Specify the
particular form of the grant canonical potential
related to the logarithm of the grand canonical
partition function that is specific to the photon
energy levels. Related to their quantize momentum
and given the length of the next section and the
length. The amount of time that is already on the
clock, it will stop this recording here a bit
early and pick up with the remainder of.
Summarizing the remainder of the week's material
in the next video.