Hello and welcome back to Statistical Physics.
This is the wrap up video for week three of the
canonical ensemble, about 10 minutes summarizing
the highlights and key learning outcomes from what
is just the first of three weeks focused on the
canonical ensemble. So the key for this week is to
introduce this concept, see how it works, how it
works, how it's put together, and do a first quick
application to the physics of information. So
beginning from the beginning.
The overview video mentioned that the canonical
ensemble fixes the temperature and particle no, in
contrast to the micro canonical ensemble that
fixes the energy
in particle, no. So. In a lot of more physics
courses, that would sort of be the stopping point,
you would just define that as the ensemble and go
from there. Here we are being a bit more
mathematical and going to provide some of the
mathematical justification
attributed to Gibs that really justifies how and
why we are able to.
Use the canonical ensemble as a basis of of
analyzing statistical systems when we don't have
the. Very clear, direct connection to the
conservation of energy. The first law of
thermodynamics and the trick here is known as the
replica trick. It is a trick that we will see
again later in this module and also has other uses
and applications in.
In mathematical physics, and the idea is so
backtracking just a bit to reiterate the overview
in the canonical ensemble, we posit that the
temperature of our system of interest is fixed.
And we argue that this is done by having our
system in thermal contact with a much larger
external system, a thermal reservoir with which it
is able to exchange energy. And that thermal
reservoir fixes the temperature of the overall
combined system of the system we're interested in,
plus the reservoir is the total system that
temperature is fixed by the reservoir or the
system we're interested in is just a small
probation on that. And because the temperature is
a is an intensive quantity at fixed temperature of
the total system, including the reservoir is
picked up by the system we care about. That's the
handwaving, qualitative idea. And the replica
trick is a way to justify that mathematically. And
the. The overall calculation that we go through is
close to half of the lecture notes for this week,
though, there are
other pieces that we pick up along the way,
including the partition function and Boltzmann
distribution, that we'll get to adjust to bits.
But the basic idea is to introduce some well
motivated onslaughts for the form of this thermal
reservoir. And having specified that, we are able
to analyse it mathematically and we want to see
and do see that the detailed form of this
reservoir that we have proposed the results turns
out not to have any effect. All the details of the
reservoir drop out when we look at the system
itself, apart from the fact that the temperature
is fixed from having this reservoir there. So the
conclusion we draw from that, which is not a not
so much a proof as a self consistency argument,
it's saying that we don't have to worry about what
form this thermal reservoir has so long as it is
there. It will serve this role of fixing the
temperature and mathematically defining the
economical ensemble. And the well motivated Aitzaz
that. That gives came up with is to say, let's
just say we have a system that we want to analyze
with a fixed temperature and the canonical
approach, we say that while the system is
something that is realistic enough and interesting
enough that we are bothering to analyze it. So
let's just suppose that the thermal reservoir is
the same sort of stuff as the system, just more of
it. So we. And we formalized this by saying that
the total system is a large number of replicas,
identical copies of the system we are interested
in, so we can pick out one of those replicas as
the system we want to find out about in all of the
other replicas for collectively that large
external thermal reservoir that we can then
analyze by having specified how this reservoir
behaves, what it looks like in terms of the system
we are interested in studying
and. The way we analyze that overall combined
system in the replica trick is to step back to
that more fundamental micro canonical ensemble
that we spent last week looking at and. We have
the idea that this overall total system with all
the replicas really is the universe that matters.
So we can analyze that with the micro economical
approach that assumes conservation of energy, that
is satisfied by the overall system, even though
it's not satisfied by the small subsystem. The one
particular replica that we want to analyze that is
now able to exchange energy with this thermal
reservoir and applying. The microeconomic analysis
to that overall system of all of these replicas
takes us through the. Well, the same exercise as
it was last week, we count the number of
microstates we throughout all of this work, we are
assuming thermodynamic equilibrium. I neglected to
mention that in the overview. So I'll mention it
here. Everything is a dynamic equilibrium. So the
entropy is the logarithm of the number of
microstates. And by maximizing that subject to the
usual constraints on conservation of energy and
conservation of probability, we come up with a
form for the occupation probability. That is the
probability that if we pick any one of these
replicas at random, it will be in a particular
micro state of the small or smaller system that we
are interested in analyzing. In the form of this
occupation, probability is. A very famous
distribution known as either the both the
distribution or the Gibbs distribution, depending
in part on which side of the Atlantic you're on
and it involves.
Two pieces, one of which is an exponential factor
to the. Minus energy over temperature. I'm jumping
ahead a bit to connect this to the temperature.
That is known as The Ballston Factor, this
exponential dependence, and what it tells us is
that lower energies that have a less negative
argument to this exponential are probabilistically
favored in the canonical approach into a dynamic
equilibrium, which is a big contrast to the
microeconomic ensemble where all of the
microstates had the same probability. Now we have
the additional specification that all microstates
with the same energy have. The same probability
and the extent to which we are sensitive to the
energy is set by the temperature that is
normalizing this. The other piece of the
distribution is the partition function Z, which is
the sum over all microstates of our single replica
system of interest. That. Contains essentially all
of the information about that replica as a
statistical ensemble and by. Maximizing that
entropy to. Get to thermodynamic equilibrium.
Taking the derivative, we get the temperature and
we get the result that I have already referenced
before, that it is the temperature that shows up
in that Boltzmann factor and therefore in the
partitioned function. And therefore it is the
temperature that completely specifies the system
we're interested in. And this is the. Key takeaway
message of the replica trick, all of that talk
about replicas and the total system of lots of
replicas with conserve energy, that all drops away.
All that matters is the temperature that the
condition of the dynamic equilibrium connects to
the partition function and therefore specifies
along with the conserved particle number that's
always coming along for the ride. We have the
temperature and conserve particle numbers
specifying all the details of our canonical system
with no more reference to the form of that thermal
reservoir. It just has to be president to set the
temperature. And beyond that, it doesn't matter.
The one thing I'll say about the derived qualities,
since I'm going on a bit bit long with that story
about the replica trick,
is that part of the homework coming up in a few
weeks will be to derive the heat capacity, which
is the dependence of the average internal energy
of the system on the temperature that is now the
fundamental independent variable characterizing
the system.
If you plug in the expression that we have for the
energy, you will find a relation between. The
fluctuations in the energy about his mean value
and the heat capacity of the derivative or the
response of the average energy to this control
parameter or the temperature. And this is an
example of a fluctuation response relation or for
somewhat obscure historical reasons, what's known
as the fluctuation dissipation relation that.
Appears quite generally in statistical physics,
another example being the relation that while the
law, the law of diffusion that we looked at in
week one, which is what Einstein derived when
analyzing Brownian motion, using statistical
physics, that law of diffusion is another example
of the fluctuation dissipation theorem.
And wrapping up with the example of.
The spin system. And the different behavior of the
spin system, depending on what information is
physically knowable about it, some of the
takeaways to see from this example are. The.
Concept of the Crown State and the excited states
where now the canonical ensemble where the
probability of a microstates depends exponentially
on the energy of that microstates, it becomes
important. So we have some non-zero probability of
sampling any micro state in the system, regardless
of what its energy is, that energy is no longer
conserved. But there is a probabilistic preference
to sample the states with the the lower or the
lowest energy, that lowest energy state being
known as the ground state. And as the temperature
decreases. The factor of the temperature in the
Boltzmann factor to the minus energy divided by
temperature makes that sensitivity to the energy
more and more significant. So as the temperature
approaches absolute zero, the economical system
really freezes in battleground states and the
entropy accordingly vanishes. Because there's
really only one state with a non-zero probability
of being realized and the logarithm of one is the
entropy, which is zero. One day the number of
microstates in that limit of absolute zero
temperature and at low temperatures, we can see
the effects of higher energy, excited states in
these derived quantities, the internal energy and
the entropy. In the case of this spin system, that
effect is exponential in the energy difference
between the ground state and the first excited
state, what's known as the energy gap. That's
generically true for the energy. And systems that
have this non-zero energy gap rather than a
continuous, continuously varying possible energy
use, it's a little bit different. That's. There's
not such a strong statement we can say about the
entropy, what we can look at is contrasting the so
those facts, the. The zero temperature limit of
the energy and entropy is the same, regardless of
whether or not we can distinguish these spins,
what information is intrinsic to the system? There
are bigger differences at non-zero temperature and
in particular physically observable differences in
things like the energy of the system as a function
of temperature. So there is physical content to
the information that is knowable about the system.
And there's also a very striking difference in the
entropy in the limit of very high temperatures
where. We approximately recover the micro
canonical behavior, what's going on there is that
in the high temperature limits, the temperature is
so much larger than the energy of any individual
spin in the system, that to a good approximation,
we can say that the the energy is effectively
vanishing. So all microstates have that same
negligible energy. And we get back to the micro
canonical case as the limit here. But in the case
where the spins are distinguishable. We calculate
that the entropy at high temperatures is the
number of spins and times, the logarithm of two,
whereas in the case where we where it is not
possible in principle to distinguish the spins,
the entropy is much smaller. It is the logarithm
of one plus one. So approximately the logarithm of
N for a large number of spins. So that's an
exponential difference in the energy. That is a
direct consequence of the exponential difference
in the number of possible microstates. We can
distinguish all those things we have to do the n
different microstates that differ by the values
that those distinguishable spins can have. When we
can't distinguish those spins, then the
microstates are characterized only by the energies
that they have and there are only and plus one
possible energy levels in the system of an spins.
So that is the the first application of the
canonical approach, demonstrating that information
is physical and in the next two weeks we will look
at.
A bit broader implications of the canonical
ensemble to ideal gases and so dynamical cycles
that include refrigerators and heat engines. So I
will finally, after a bit of a lengthy diatribe,
wrap up this wrap up. With that.