Hello and welcome back to a statistical physics.
This is the first video for the final week of the
module, week 11, which if I bring the materials up
onto the screen here, we will see is a bit
different than the the previous weeks that came
before dealing with a wrap up for the module,
brief consideration of some broader applications
of the statistical physics tools and concepts we
have developed so far, along with an overall
synthesis and recapitulation of everything that
we've seen. And the starting point for this week
is building a bit on the. Interacting systems that
we introduced last week through the particular
example of the easy model of spins out of lattice
interacting with their nearest neighbors, where
when we talked about the accuracy of the Glenfield
approximation to the using model, you mentioned
that with accuracy actually increases as the
number of dimensions in the system increases,
getting the critical exponents correct for
lattices in four or more dimensions, while the
critical temperature from the main field
approximation becomes closer to the true value as
that dimensionality increases and. What was
mentioned here was that these true values are
being determined by. Numerical calculations and
numerical computations, and this may have caused
some questions based on the earlier discussion of
the extreme difficulty of exactly solving the easy
model or indeed any other interacting statistical
system where we counted the terms that appear in
the partition function and clearly saw that even
with any computer we could imagine, it would take
far longer than the age of the universe to
evaluate all of those terms. So the numerical
methods that are used very broadly, used
throughout many fields of science to analyze
interacting statistical systems are not based on
completely determining the partition function the
way that we have been carrying out calculations
analytically in the simple not track in cases
where factorization turns that into a single
particle problem. The approach that is used in all
of these numerical calculations is centered on the
idea of sampling that instead of computing every
possible term, instead of something over every
microstates that appears in the formal definition
of the partition function, we can just sample some
small subsets of those microstates and hope that
this small sample provides an accurate and
controlled approximation to the overall system.
And there are cases and conditions under which
this turns out to be true.
And perhaps before getting into those conditions,
a bit of background is that these methods were
developed with the advent of numerical computing
machines back in the 1940s and a couple of
mathematicians who pioneered these methods and
gave them the whimsical name of Montecarlo
techniques named after the casino in Monaco. We're
satisfied with William and Jonathan Neumann. And
the idea is that just as we had to do in the
computing project, we no longer had the central
limit theorem and the law of diffusion available
to analyze random walks, we have to carry out some
numerical calculations that involve stochastic
sampling, pseudo random numbers and repeated many
times to get an ensemble of. Of results that can
then be averaged ideally with some controlled
uncertainty in those averaging.
And the sort of basic setting in which these
Montecarlo methods were developed were evaluating
complicated, multidimensional integrals that could
not be done through pen and paper techniques or
through simple analytic approximations, where
maybe the the simplest example of a Montecarlo
evaluation of an integral is to compute the area
of this unit, this embedded in a two by two square
integration domain, which normally normalizes the
counts of the random points in that domain that
gets sampled
so that the ratio of the points that land within
the disk to those that took the total number that
are generated is simply high. And in a few minutes
with, say, a billion samples, we can compute pi
using simply pseudo random numbers to about.
For significant figures in this uncertainty here,
you can see how it is estimated in the Python code
now that sort of sampling could work well in the
high temperature phase of the easing model, we
just sample a vanishingly small subset of all of
the microstates. So sampling, say a trillion
microstates would be one part in 10 to the power
of two hundred eighty eight out of the total for a
thousand particle system and really tiny system in
the context of statistical physics.
But that is definitely not going to work in the in
the low temperature phase, so we call that the
high temperature phase is characterized by. All of
the micro states of the easy model being
approximately. Equal probability so that averaging
over any subset of them is going to be just as
good as averaging over in the other subset, the
low temperature phase, however, the ground stage
becomes exponentially dominant, with excited
states producing exponentially suppressed
corrections to predictions. So if our sampling did
not pick out the the ground state or one of the
two degenerate ground states, then we would get
simply a completely wrong answer. And we can see
that we have a chance of one part in 10 to the
power two hundred eighty eight to randomly select
background state that really controls and
determines the physics and that regime and the the
way around. This was sort of phrased in a very
elegant way by this group of researchers who
developed so-called important sampling back in the
1950s, saying that instead of randomly sampling
states with the probability distribution and
weighting their expectation value or weighting
their contributions to the expectation value with
the exponential Boltzmann factor, we sample states
proportional to that exponential factor and then
simply have a flat. Distribution with which they
contribute to expectation values,
so the the trick so the idea of importance, of
sampling, to say it a bit less elegantly and more
straightforwardly is just to sample the important
states that contribute a lot to the predictions
that we want to obtain numerically. The
complication is that apriori, before we do a full
calculation, we don't necessarily know which
states in this complicated interactive statistical
system are actually important in the. The work
that was done in the 50s was getting around. We're
addressing that challenge through the concept of
Berkoff change that we saw all the way back in
Section one, where each state that is sampled
numerically, I should say, each micro state that
is sampled numerically is built from the
previously considered micro state. Forming a chain
of microstates that evolved from one to the next
in a particular way and. The way that was
developed back in the 50s and remains very widely
used across all areas of science, was to just make
a change to a particular degree of freedom,
compute the overall change in energy, the same
quantity that we used to diagnose whether or not
the system was interacting or not interacting. And
then either accept or reject this proposed change
to the degree of freedom with this particular
probability where if the change in energy is
negative, then the exponential factor is greater
than one and the acceptance probability is one
hundred percent. But if the change in energy is
negative, then the acceptance probability is
exponentially suppressed so that if we do manage
to find that lowest energy ground states, we have,
depending on the inverse temperature data, the
appropriate exponentially suppressed probability
of leaving it again and sampling different
microstates so we can continue in this process to
sample the same microstates over and over and over
again if. All of the other microstates that are
proposed by this algorithm come in with a
significantly higher temperature or significantly
higher energy times, inverse temperature at least
of this exponential suppression.
And yes, the quick calculation reveals that the
probability of ending up in the state A or B based
on this approach is proportional to the
corresponding Boltzmann factor, the exponential of
minus speed of times, the corresponding energy A
or B, so gone on about this A. A fair amount of
time, so I'll wrap up the video here and deal with
the rest of the material in the second video for
this week. But I will just say that these sorts of
numerical calculations based on Montecarlo,
important sampling are.
I emphasize that they date back to the 1950s, but
they remain a cutting edge aspect of research in
mathematical sciences, physical sciences, life
sciences, even beyond the sciences, wherever there
are statistics and where there are systems with
large numbers of individual components. This sort
of Montecarlo important sampling will be a key
tool.