Hello and welcome back to statistical physics.
This is the first video for week nine of the
molecule, providing a brief summary of the context,
motivations and key learning outcomes for this
week's material on quantum gases of fermions. And
bringing materials onto the screen here
can start just by orientating ourselves in the big
picture of the module where we are, where we've
been and where we are headed, where in week nine
we are wrapping up not only our consideration of
quantum gases as an application of the grand
economical ensemble, but actually taking our last
look at idealised systems whose constituent
particles do not interact with each other, which
is all we have been considering in the module up
to this point. And next week we will dive into the
much more complicated situation of interacting
systems where we no longer make this idealized
approximation of not interacting particles. And we
will see that things become much more difficult,
much more quickly in that case. But that is for
next week and for this week. We have formulas to
deal with and in particular focusing on not
relativistic fermions, so particles that obey the
same relation between energy and momentum that we
worked with in some detail all the way back in
week four in the context of the canonical example
where the energy is just given by the particle
momentum squared divided by twice its mass. And
just as in week four, we quantize the particles
momentum and therefore their energy use in order
to make the petition function well defined in this
case this week, the grand canonical partition
function that depends on temperature and chemical
potential, allowing both the energy and particle
number to fluctuate. And we take the quantum
approach of something over all of those discrete
energy levels. And considering the possible
occupation numbers that each energy level could
have rather than the classical approach that we
did back in week four, where we consider the
particles one by one summed over all of the
possible energies that each individual particle
could have and then introduced some correction
factors for or to address the overcounting that
resulted from that classical approach. In the
quantum approach. There is no overcounting and in
particular in the low temperature regime of.
Fermions, we have the somewhat unusual or at least
unfamiliar circumstance where the only possible
occupation numbers for these energy levels are
zero and one in energy level can either be
unoccupied or empty or it can be occupied by a
single FIRREA, which completely fills it and does
not allow any other on to occupy that same energy
level, assuming, as we will, that all of the
fermions in this case are identical. And we don't
have multiple species of particles which would be
described by separate energy levels for each
species.
And with that set up of fermions back in week
seven, we derived the great canonical partition
function and the corresponding great nonlocal
potential for that situation of occupation numbers,
either zero or one in what remains is to plug in
the specific energies for these fermions in in
this case, the non relativistic Régine. So
providing a contrast with the photon gas we
consider last week and at low temperatures,
revealing the effects solely due to quantum
physics or what we are assuming
as an Anzac's that we based on quantum physics but
don't require any background knowledge of the
topic to see how the low temperature fermoy on gas
differs compared to the classical approach that we
investigated back before the term break and
plugging in this energy into the grand economic
potential and importantly retaining the chemical
potential, which for fermions can be either
positive or negative. We can do the same sort of
calculation of integrating over the the possible
momentum rather than something over them. And if
we change variables to express the grand canonical
potential in terms of the Fermi on energy rather
than the momentum or the integer labels that
classify the different quantized values of that
momentum. We end up with this equation, one of
five for the great economic potential that
determines all of the large scale properties of
the system arising from the the quantum statistics
obeyed by each of the individual particles that
that compose it. And. All that we need to do
starting from this potential, is take the
appropriate derivatives to extract things like the
average internal energy particle, no pressure and
entropy. And you will be interested in doing so at
low temperatures, driving the equation of states
and seeing how the quantum gas at low temperatures
smoothly matches on to the classical system that
we saw in week seven is reproduced in the
appropriate high temperature limit, where the
chemical potential goes to a large negative value
as the temperature goes to a large positive value
in order to retain a finite number of particles in
the system. But starting off with some
consideration of the number of particles in the
system and the great canonical approach that is
given just by the negative derivative with respect
to chemical potential of the great economical
potential. And similarly to how you looked first
at the energy density as our last week in the
photon gas context, we looked at the energy
density of a photon gas as an integral over a
spectral density, which matched on to what we
could observe. It will prove useful to take a
similar approach this week and look at the
particle number density and also the internal
energy density as integrals over the energy of
some function of that energy, which is known as
the the Fermi function. And if we keep the
constant multiplicative factors outside of that
family function, in contrast to what we did with
the Planck distribution last week, we end up with
something that looks very much like the average
occupation. No. Arrived back in Section seven
point five, the main difference being that instead
of fixing the particular value of the energy
corresponding to the energy level whose occupation
number we were considering back in week seven,
here we are looking at this exponential function
as a function of the energy, which also depends on
the inverse temperature data and chemical
potential. New and if we. Rearrange this very
function to write it in terms of dimensionless
ratios of that energy divided by chemical
potential in the chemical potential divided by the
temperature, we can highlight its two main
features at both as functions of. The temperature
given by this dimensionless number with respect to
the chemical potential as well as the dependence
on the energy, again, compared to the chemical
potential which is shown in this figure here.
So the two things to pick out are, first, that the
point where the energy is equal to the chemical
potential, that ratio equals one is a special
point in this plot where all of these different
curves for different temperatures intersect at a
value of one half. The argument of the exponential
zero of the exponential itself is then one, and
the family function is one over one plus one gives
us a half or any value of the temperature. And at
lower energies there is a distinct. Temperature
dependent, so rare that the opposite temperature
dependence compared to the situation at higher
energies, so a higher energy is a decrease in
temperature going from a relatively large value
equal to the chemical potential in the solid red
curve down to a much smaller value. Only one
percent of the chemical potential given by the
black curve. You see that at higher energies, this
change in temperature leads to. A rapidly
decreasing family function, in fact, exponentially
decreasing, whereas at lower temperatures, the
family function increases and the exponential
factor itself there is decreasing, heading towards
zero exponentially quickly. So that all that is
left is that one divided by the one in the
denominator. So the primary function is
approaching one from below at temperatures lower
than the sorry energies, lower than the chemical
potential with the speed of approach governed by
the temperature. And it approaches zero for energy
is higher than the chemical potential, again, with
the speed of approach to zero governed by the
temperature. And at low temperatures as shown by
the black curve here, the family function can
become dull, approximated by a simple step
function where it is one for all energies, less
than the chemical potential, which in this context
at low temperatures needs to be positive in order
to have any non-zero number of particles remaining
in our great economical system and at higher
energies larger than that chemical potential. The
family function is zero, and the interpretation of
this is that all of the energy levels that have
values are the energy up to the chemical potential
are filled at these low temperatures, and none of
the energy levels with values of the energy larger
than the chemical potential are filled. They are
all empty or unoccupied.
And that interpretation connects to the similarity
between this Fermoy function in the average
occupation number that we computed a couple of
weeks ago and can also be seen in the computation
of the average particle number and internal energy
that, given how long this recording is already,
you will set aside for the next video and return
to to to go through. In. In that second video for
this week.